<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ebook book="compTia">
<chapter index="9" title="" glossary="51" secondGlossary="74">

<page index="0" type="full" distinction="chapterStart">
			<section>
				<!--new image title set up.-->
				<![CDATA[
				<section>
				
				<div class="chapterStartBox">
					<div class="chapterStartDesc topPadding10">
						Securing Your<br/>System: Protecting<br/>Your Digital Data<br/>and Devices</div>	
				<div class="chapterStartNumber">9</div>
				</div>
				<div class="loader"></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		<page index="1" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="toc">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[

					<span class="largeGreenHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">Major Threats to Your Digital Assets</span>
					<img src="assets/images/pics/cybercrime.jpg" class="noBMargin" style="margin-top:-25px;margin-right:0px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">Cybercrime and Identity Theft</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li ><span class="ul1DigNumber">1.</span> What is cybercrime, and who perpetrates it? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">(pp. 403-405)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<hr class="clearRight">
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/virus.jpg" class="noBMargin" style="margin-right:0px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading"  onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,5)">Protecting Yourself from Computer Viruses</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objectives</span>
					<ul>
						<li><span class="ul1DigNumber">2.</span> What are the types of viruses from which I need to protect my computer? <br/><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,5)">(pp. 405–409)</span></li>
						<li><span class="ul1DigNumber">3.</span> What can I do to protect my computer from viruses? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,10)">(pp. 410–413)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/protecting_your_computer/index.html','_blank')" style="float:right;width:178px;">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Protecting Your Computer
					</div>
					
					<div class="activeHelpdesk"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_20.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
						<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
						Avoiding Computer Viruses
					</div>
					
					<hr class="clearRight">
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/protectingAssets.jpg" class="noBMargin" style="margin-right:0px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,14)">Protecting Digital Assets from Hackers</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objectives</span>
					<ul>
						<li style="width:255px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">4.</span> How can hackers attack my computing devices, and what harm can they cause? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,14)">(pp. 414–418)</span></li>
						<li style="width:255px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">5.</span> What is a firewall, and how does it keep my computer safe from hackers? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,19)">(pp. 419–421)</span></li>
						<li style="width:380px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">6.</span> How do I create secure passwords and manage all of my passwords? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,22)">(pp. 422–424)</span></li>
						<li style="width:380px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">7.</span> How can I surf the Internet anonymously and use biometric authentication devices to protect my data? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,24)">(pp. 424–427)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/layout/playTechTown.png" class="techTown" style="margin-bottom:-3px;" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techtown','_blank')"/>

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<div class="activeHelpdesk"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_21.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
						<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
						Understanding Firewalls
					</div>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/installing_firewall/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Installing a Personal Firewall
					</div>
					
					<hr>
					
					<span class="largeGreenHeading" style="width:380px;" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,30)">Protecting Your Digital Property from Yourself</span>
					<img src="assets/images/pics/spam.jpg" class="BMargin5 shiftUp5" style="margin-right:-20px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading"  onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,30)">Managing Online Annoyances</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li><span class="ul1DigNumber">8.</span> How do I manage online annoyances such as spyware and spam? <br/><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,30)">(pp. 430-434)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<hr class="clearRight">
						
					<img src="assets/images/pics/engineering.jpg" class="noBMargin" style="margin-right:-20px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,34)">Keeping Your Data Safe</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objectives</span>
					<ul>
						<li style="width:250px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">9.</span> What data do I need to back up, and what are the best methods for doing so? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,34)">(pp. 434–440)</span></li>
						<li style="width:250px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">10.</span> What is social engineering, and how do I avoid falling prey to phishing? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,40)">(pp. 440–442)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/managing_computer_security/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Managing Computer Security with Windows Tools
					</div>
					
					<hr>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/physicalAssets.jpg" class="noBMargin" style="margin-right:-20px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" style="width:380px;" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,43)">Protecting Your Physical Computing Assets</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li style="width: 230px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">11.</span> How do I protect my physical computing assets from environmental hazards, power surges, and theft? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,43)">(pp. 443–446)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/surge_protectors_and_ups/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Surge Protectors
					</div>
					
					
					

					<span class="bottomMediaText">
   						For all media in this chapter go to <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techinaction','_blank')">pearsonhighered.com/techinaction</span> or <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span>.
   					</span>

					<span class="verticalRightCreds" style="margin-right:10px;margin-bottom:-14px;">
							(Norebbo/Shutterstock; mmaxer/Shutterstock; IKO/Shutterstock; Timo Darco/Fotolia)
					</span>
					<div class="loader"></div>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			</page>	
			
		<page index="2" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="whiteOnBlack">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[


					
					<div style="width:110%;height:100%;
							background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/cloudStorage.jpg) 0px 0"></div></div>
							<div class="font_9 transform90deg floatRight"
								 style="margin-top:-207px;margin-right:30px;font-style: italic;">(vege/Fotolia)
								 </div>




				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="thinGreenHeading">How Cool Is This?</span>
					<p class="moreSpacing">You have a lot of <strong>information</strong> in your <strong>cell phone</strong>. What happens if you <strong>lose your phone</strong>, damage it beyond repair, or want to <strong>switch phones</strong>? Transferring data can be very time consuming, or even impossible if you lose your phone. Apple’s iOS devices do a good job of backing up your settings either in iTunes or iCloud. But what about backing up Android devices? Not all settings and apps are backed up on Google’s sites. So, apps like <strong>The Missing Sync</strong> provide a solution by allowing you to <strong>back up settings</strong>, contacts, notes, tasks, bookmarks, calendars, music, videos, and photos from your Android phone or tablet to a computer running the Windows operating system. The backups take place automatically <strong>via WiFi or Bluetooth</strong> whenever you are in close proximity to your computer. Then, if your phone is ever lost, stolen, or damaged, or if you are just upgrading to the latest model, you can easily <strong>transfer</strong> your information to a new or replacement phone. So install a backup app on your Android phone today and enjoy some peace of mind!</p>
					
					<div class="scanThis"
						 style="background-image: url('assets/images/pics/Chap9ArrSchip_computer.png')" onclick="window.open('http://www.markspace.com','_blank')">
						Scan here for more info 
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>

		</page>	
		
		<page index="3" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingGreenBackDiagDashes">Major Threats to Your Digital Assets</div>
					<p class="digCompP">The media is full of stories about malicious computer programs damaging computers, criminals stealing people’s identities online, and attacks on corporate websites bringing major corporations to a standstill. These are examples of cybercrime. In this part of the chapter, we’ll discuss the three most serious types of cybercrime you need to worry about: identity theft, computer viruses, and hackers.</p>
					<div class="greenHeadingLineDashed"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/cybercrimeThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">cybercrime and</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:120px;">IDENTITY THEFT</div>
					</div>
					
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Cybercrime</span> is any criminal action perpetrated primarily through the use of a computer. The existence of cybercrime means that computer users must take precautions to protect themselves. The FBI maintains a website (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://fbi.gov/about-us/investigate/cyber/cyber','_blank')">fbi.gov/about-us/investigate/cyber/cyber</span>) specifically to inform the public about types of cybercrimes and methods of protecting yourself.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Who perpetrates computer crimes?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="cybercriminal">Cybercriminals</span> are individuals who use computers, networks, and the Internet to perpetrate crime. Anyone with a computer and the wherewithal to arm him- or herself with the appropriate knowledge can be a cybercriminal.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>What kinds of cybercrimes are conducted over the Internet?</strong> The Internet Crime Complaint Center (IC3) is a partnership between the FBI and the National White Collar Crime Center (NW3C). In 2011 (the latest year for which was data available at this book’s publication), the IC3 received over 314,000 complaints related to Internet crime. The top four categories of complaints received are shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(3,0)">Figure 9.1</span>. FBI–related scams involve</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight cond"><span class="shiftLeft7">Top Four Cybercrimes Reported to the IC3 in 2011</span></div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(3,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.1.jpg) no-repeat scroll 14px 55px #FFFFFF; height: 500px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.1</strong> Click to reveal the interactive graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span> <em>(Peter Kim/Fotolia; RabidBadger/Fotolia; viperagp/Fotolia; Donets/Fotolia)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="4" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>people pretending  to represent official organizations, such as the FBI or Homeland Security, to defraud. Non-auction scams involve running auctions of merchandise that does not really exist, wherein the perpetrators just collect funds and disappear without delivering the promised goods. Advance fee fraud involves convincing individuals to send money as a “good faith” gesture to enable them to receive larger payments in return. The scammers then disappear with the advance fees.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Although the top four complaints all relate to some type of fraud, other complaints received involve equally serious matters such as computer intrusions (hacking), child pornography, and blackmail.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What is the most financially damaging cybercrime plaguing individuals?</strong> Theft of personal data such as bank account numbers and credit/debit card numbers is of most concern to individuals because this information is usually used for fraudulent purposes. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Identity theft</span> occurs when a thief steals personal information such as your name, address, Social Security number, birth date, bank account, and credit card information and runs up debts in your name. Many victims of identity theft spend months, or even years, trying to repair their credit and eliminate fraudulent debts.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What types of scams do identity thieves perpetrate?</strong> The nefarious acts cover a wide range:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Counterfeiting your existing credit and debit cards</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Requesting changes of address on your bank and credit card statements, which makes detecting fraudulent charges take longer</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Opening new credit cards and bank accounts in your name and then writing bad checks and not paying off the credit card balances (ruining your credit rating in the process)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Obtaining medical services under your name (you might lose coverage later if the thief’s treatment exceeds the limits of your policy’s covered services)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Buying a home with a mortgage in your name, then reselling the house and absconding with the money (leaving you with the debt)</span></li>
					</ul>	
					
					<p class="start">Many people believe that the only way your identity can be stolen is by a computer. However, the Federal Trade Commission (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://ftc.gov','_blank')">ftc.gov</span>) has identified other methods thieves use to obtain others’ personal information:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Stealing purses and wallets, in which people often keep personal information such as their ATM PIN codes</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Stealing mail or looking through trash for bank statements and credit card bills </span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Posing as bank or credit card company representatives and tricking people into revealing sensitive information over the phone</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Installing skimming devices on ATM machines that record information, such as account numbers and passcodes</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">Although foolproof protection methods don’t exist, there are precautions that will help you minimize your risk, which we’ll discuss later in this chapter.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
			
		<page index="5" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>With all the news coverage about identity theft and other cybercrimes, aren’t people being more cautious?</strong> Although most people are aware of spam, a survey by the Messaging Anti-Abuse Working Group (MAAWG) found that half of e-mail users in North America and Europe have opened spam, some of which are designed to trick you into divulging sensitive information. The MAAWG also discovered that 46% of people who opened spam did so intentionally—out of idle curiosity, to follow links to unsubscribe to unwanted e-mails (which only brings more spam), or because they are interested in the product being touted.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Does cybercrime include the theft of computing devices?</strong> Although theft of computer equipment is not classified as a cybercrime (it is considered larceny), the theft of tablets, cell phones, notebook computers, and other portable computing devices is on the rise. The resale value for used electronic equipment is high, and the equipment can be easily sold online.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashedEnd"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingBO" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/virusThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="dblue">computer</div>
						<div class="orange" style="margin-left:120px;">VIRUSES</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>A computer <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virus</span> is a computer program that attaches itself to another computer program (known as the <em>host</em> program) and attempts to spread to other computers when files are exchanged. Creating and disseminating computer viruses is one of the most widespread types of cybercrimes. Some viruses cause only minor annoyances, whereas others cause destruction or theft of data. Many viruses are designed to gather sensitive information such as credit card numbers.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Why are viruses such a threat to my security?</strong> Computer viruses are threatening because they are engineered to evade detection. Viruses normally attempt to hide within the code of a host program to avoid detection. And viruses are not just limited to computers. Smartphones, tablet computers, and other devices can be infected with viruses. Viruses such as SpyEye Mobile Banking are used to trick users into downloading an infected file to their phones, which then steals their online banking information.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>I have an Apple computer, so I don’t need to worry about viruses, do I?</strong> This is a popular misconception! Everyone, even Apple users, needs to worry about viruses. As the OS X and iOS oper ating systems have gained market share, the amount of virus attacks against Apple operating systems is on the rise.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="6" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What do computer viruses do?</strong> A computer virus’s main purpose is to replicate itself and copy its code into as many other host files as possible. This gives the virus a greater chance of being copied to another computer system so that it can spread its infection. However, computer viruses require human interaction to spread. Although there might be a virus in a file on your computer, a virus normally can’t infect your computer until the infected file is opened or executed.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Although virus replication can slow down networks, it’s not usually the main threat. The majority of viruses have secondary objectives or side effects, ranging from displaying annoying messages on the computer screen to destroying files or the contents of entire hard drives.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Catching a Virus</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How does my computer catch a virus?</strong> If your computer is exposed to a file infected with a virus, the virus will try to copy itself and infect a file on your computer.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Downloading infected audio and video files from peer-to-peer file-sharing sites is a major source of virus infections. Shared flash drives are also a common source of virus infection, as is e-mail. Just opening  an e-mail message usually won’t infect your computer with a virus, although some new viruses are launched when viewed in the preview pane of your e-mail software. Downloading or running (executing) a file that’s attached to the e-mail are common ways that your computer becomes infected. Thus, be</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>extremely wary of e-mail attachments, especially if you don’t know the sender. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,0)">Figure 9.2</span> illustrates the steps by which computer viruses are often passed from one computer to the next.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What types of viruses exist?</strong>  Although thousands of computer viruses and variants exist, they can be grouped into six broad categories based on their behavior and method of transmission.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight"><span>How Computer Viruses Spread</span></div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.2.jpg) no-repeat scroll 16px 42px #FFFFFF; height: 330px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.2</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="7" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Boot-Sector Viruses</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are boot-sector viruses?</strong> A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>boot-sector virus</span> replicates itself onto a hard drive’s master boot record. The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>master boot record</span> is a program that executes whenever a computer boots up, ensuring that the virus will be loaded into memory immediately, even before some virus protection programs can load. Boot-sector viruses are often transmitted by a flash drive left in a USB port. When the computer boots up with the flash drive connected, the computer tries to launch a master boot record from the flash drive, which is usually the trigger for the virus to infect the hard drive.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Logic Bombs and Time Bombs</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are logic bombs and time bombs?</strong> A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>logic bomb</span> is a virus that is triggered when certain logical conditions are met, such as opening a file or starting a program a certain number of times. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>time bomb</span> is a virus that is triggered by the passage of time or on a certain date. For example, the Michelangelo virus was a famous time bomb that was set to trigger every year on March 6, Michelangelo’s birthday. The effects of logic bombs and time bombs range from the display of annoying messages on the screen to the reformatting of the hard drive, which causes complete data loss.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Worms</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What is a worm?</strong> Although often called a virus, a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>worm</span> is subtly different. Viruses require human interaction to spread, whereas worms take advantage of file transport methods, such as e-mail or network connections, to spread on their own. A virus infects a host file and waits until that file is executed to replicate and infect a computer system. A worm, however, works independently of host file execution and is much more active in spreading itself. When the Conficker worm broke out in 2008, it quickly infected up to 15 million computers. It spread through vulnerabilities in the Windows code and compromised computers by disabling certain software services and utility programs, such as Windows Update.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Script and Macro Viruses</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are script and macro viruses?</strong> Some viruses are hidden on websites in the form of scripts. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>script</span> is a series of commands—actually, a miniprogram—that is executed without your knowledge. Scripts are often used to perform useful, legitimate functions on websites, such as collecting name and address information from customers. However, some scripts are malicious. For example, you might click a link to display a video on a website, which causes a script to run that infects your computer with a virus.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="8" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>macro virus</span> is a virus that attaches itself to a document that uses macros. A <em>macro</em> is a short series of commands that usually automates repetitive tasks. However, macro languages are now so sophisticated that viruses can be written with them. In 1999, the Melissa virus became the first major macro virus to cause problems worldwide.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">E-Mail Viruses</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What is an e-mail virus?</strong> The Melissa virus was the first practical example of an e-mail virus. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="e-mail virus">E-mail viruses</span> use the address book in the victim’s e-mail system to distribute the virus. In the case of the Melissa virus, anyone opening an infected document triggered the virus, which infected other documents on the victim’s computer. Once triggered, the Melissa virus sent itself to the first 50 people in the e-mail address book on the infected computer.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Encryption Viruses</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are encryption viruses?</strong> When <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="encryption virus">encryption viruses</span> infect your computer, they run a program that searches for common types of data files, such as Microsoft Word and Excel files, and compresses them using a complex encryption key that renders your files unusable. You then receive a message that asks you to send money to an account if you want to receive the program to decrypt your files. The flaw with this type of virus, which </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight"><span style="font-size:22px;">Major Categories of Viruses</span></div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(8,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.3.jpg) no-repeat scroll 16px 42px #FFFFFF; height: 340px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.3</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span><em>(tribalium81/Fotolia; LoopAll/Fotolia; dedMazay/Fotolia; Theo Malings/Fotolia; Beboy/Fotolia; Andrea Danti/Fotolia)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<p class="moreSpacing">keeps it from being widespread, is that law enforcement officials can trace the payments to an account and may possibly be able to catch the perpetrators. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(8,0)">Figure 9.3</span> summarizes the major categories of viruses.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="9" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Additional Virus Classifications</h2>
					<p><strong>How else are viruses classified?</strong> Viruses can also be classified by the methods they take to avoid detection by antivirus software:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>polymorphic virus</span> changes its own code or periodically rewrites itself to avoid detection. Most polymorphic viruses infect a particular type of file such as .EXE files, for example.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>multipartite virus</span> is designed to infect multiple file types in an effort to fool the antivirus software that is looking for it.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="stealth virus">Stealth viruses</span> temporarily erase their code from the files where they reside and then hide in the active memory of the computer. This helps them avoid detection if only the hard drive is being searched for viruses. Fortunately, current antivirus software scans memory as well as the hard drive.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Virus Symptoms</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I tell if my computer is infected with a virus?</strong> Sometimes it can be difficult to definitively tell whether your computer is infected with a virus. However, if your computer displays any of the following symptoms, it may be infected with a virus:</p>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Existing program icons or files suddenly disappear. Viruses often delete specific file types or programs.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">If you start your browser and it takes you to an unusual home page (i.e., one you didn’t set) or it has new toolbars.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Odd messages, pop-ups, or images are displayed on the screen, or strange music or sounds play.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Data files become corrupt. (However, note that files can become corrupt for reasons other than a virus infection.)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Programs stop working properly, which could be caused by either a corrupted file or a virus.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Your system slows down or takes a long time to boot up.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(9,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						CAPTCHA: Keeping Websites Safe From Bots
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain noTMargin">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_20.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Avoiding Computer Viruses
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about different types of viruses and what users should do to protect their computer from them.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="10" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashedEnd"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/virusThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">preventing virus</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:118px;">INFECTIONS</div>
					</div>
					
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Antivirus software</span> is specifically designed to detect viruses and protect your computer and files from harm. Symantec, Kaspersky, AVG, and McAfee are among the companies that offer highly rated antivirus software packages. Antivirus protection is also included in comprehensive Internet security packages such as Norton Internet Security, Kaspersky Internet Security, and McAfee Total Protection. These software packages also help protect you from threats other than computer viruses. For example, Windows 8 includes Windows Defender, which defends against malware as well as viruses.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Antivirus Software</h2>
					<p><strong>How often do I need to run antivirus software?</strong> Although antivirus software is designed to detect suspicious activity on your computer at all times, you should run an active virus scan on your entire system at least once a week. By doing so, all files on your computer will be checked for undetected viruses.</p>
					<p class="start">Most modern antivirus programs run scans in the background when your CPU is not being heavily utilized. But you can also configure the software to run scans at times when you aren’t using your system—for example, when you’re asleep (see <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(10,0)">Figure 9.5</span>). (However, it’s important </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(10,0)"
						style="height: 276px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.5.jpg) no-repeat scroll -2px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.5</span> In Norton Internet Security, you can set up virus scans to run automatically. This computer will be scanned every day at 4 a.m.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
				
				<br/>
					<p>to note that your computer has to be on and not in sleep mode for these virus scans to take place.) Alternatively, if you suspect a problem, you can launch a scan and have it run immediately.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How does antivirus software work?</strong> The main functions of antivirus software are as follows:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Detection:</em> Antivirus software looks for virus signatures in files. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virus signature</span> is a portion of the virus code that’s unique to a particular computer virus. Antivirus software scans files for these signatures when  they’re opened or executed and identifies infected files and the type of virus infecting them.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="11" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Stopping virus execution:</em> If the antivirus software detects a virus signature or suspicious activity, such as the launch of an unknown macro, it stops the execution of the file and virus and notifies you that it has detected a virus. It also places the virus in a secure area on your hard drive so that it won’t spread to other files; this procedure is known as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>quarantining</span>. Usually, the antivirus software then gives you the choice of deleting or repairing the infected file. Unfortunately, antivirus programs can’t always fix infected files to make them usable again. You should keep backup copies of critical files so that you can restore them in case a virus damages them irreparably.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Prevention of future infection:</em> Most antivirus software will also attempt to prevent infection by inoculating key files on your computer. In <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>inoculation</span>, the antivirus software records key attributes about your computer files, such as file size and date created, and keeps these statistics in a safe place on your hard drive. When scanning for viruses, the antivirus software compares the attributes of the files with the attributes it previously recorded to help detect attempts by virus programs to modify your files.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>Does antivirus software always stop viruses?</strong> Antivirus software catches <em>known</em> viruses effectively. However, new viruses are written all the time. To combat unknown viruses, modern antivirus programs search for suspicious virus-like activities as well as virus signatures. To minimize your risk, you should keep your antivirus software up to date.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>My new computer came with antivirus software installed, so shouldn’t I already be protected?</strong> Most new computers do come with antivirus software preinstalled. However, these are usually trial versions of the software that only provide updates to the software for a limited period of time, usually 90 or 180 days. After that, you have to buy a full version of the software to ensure you remain protected from new viruses.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I make sure my antivirus software is up to date?</strong> Most antivirus programs have an automatic update feature that downloads updates for virus signature files every time you go online (see <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(11,0)">Figure 9.6</span>). Also, the antivirus software usually shows the status of your update subscription so that you can see how much time you have remaining until you need to buy another version of your software.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(11,0)"
						style="height: 230px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.6.jpg) no-repeat scroll -2px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.6</span> Antivirus software, such as Windows Defender, provides for automatic updates but also allows manual updates.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="12" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What should I do if I think my computer is infected with a virus?</strong> Boot up your computer using the antivirus installation disc. This should prevent most virus programs from loading and will allow you to run the antivirus software directly from your disk drive. (<em>Note:</em> If you download your antivirus software from the Internet, copy it to a DVD in  case you have problems in the future.) If the software does detect viruses, you may want to research them further to determine whether your antivirus software will eradicate them completely or whether you’ll need to take additional manual steps to eliminate the viruses. Most antivirus company websites, such as the Symantec site (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://symantec.com','_blank')">symantec.com</span>), contain archives of information on viruses and provide step-by-step solutions for removing them.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How do I protect my phone from viruses?</strong> Because smartphones and other mobile devices run operating systems and contain files, they are susceptible to infection by viruses. Cybercriminals are now hiding viruses in legitimate-looking apps for download to mobile devices. Many antivirus software companies now offer antivirus software specifically designed for mobile devices, like Trend Micro’s Mobile Security for Android.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Software Updates</h2>
					<p><strong>Why does updating my operating system (OS) software help protect me from viruses?</strong> Many viruses exploit weaknesses in operating Systems. Malicious websites can be set up to attack your computer by downloading harmful software onto your computer. According to research conducted by Google, this type of attack, known as a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>drive-by download</span>, affects almost 1 in 1,000 web pages. To combat these threats, make sure your OS is up to date and contains the latest security patches. You can update your Windows OS with an automatic update utility called Windows Update. When you enable automatic updates, your computer searches for updates on the Microsoft website every time it connects to the Internet. Mac OS X has a similar utility for gathering updates.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Do OS updates only happen automatically?</strong> The default option in Windows is to receive updates automatically. There are several other options you can choose from in Windows, as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(13,0)">Figure 9.7</span>. The following options are noteworthy:</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Option 1: Install updates automatically.</em> Selecting this option will automatically download and install updates at a time you have specified. <em>We strongly recommend that you select this option.</em></span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Option 2: Check for updates but let me choose whether to download and install them.</em> This is an appropriate choice only if you have low bandwidth Internet access. Because downloads over dial-up can take a long time, you</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="13" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="noListStyle">
						<li><span class="innerLi">need to control when they will occur. But you need to be extra vigilant with this option because you may forget to install important updates.</span></li>
					</ul>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Option 3: Give me recommended updates.</em> This option ensures you receive recommended (optional) updates as well as critical (necessary) updates.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><em>Option 4: Microsoft Update.</em> This option ensures you receive updates for other Microsoft products besides Windows, such as Microsoft Office.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">If you keep both your antivirus and OS software up to date, you’ll help prevent viruses from infecting your computer.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/protecting_your_computer/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Protecting Your Computer
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn how to use a variety of tools to protect your computer, including antivirus software and Windows utilities.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
			<![CDATA[
				<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:280px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig9.7.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(13,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_7.html','_blank')" style="padding:3.5px;"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;margin-top:5px;">
						<span>Figure 9.7</span> The Windows Update screen makes it easy for users to configure Windows to update itself.
						</figcaption></figure>	
					
						
					<br/>
					<p><em>>To enable automatic updates, access the Control Panel, select <strong>System and Security</strong>, click the <strong>Windows Update</strong> link, and then click the <strong>Change Settings</strong> link.</em></p>	
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="14" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeMidDiagDashes"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB bgPosition00" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/protectingAssetsThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange" style="margin-left:59px;">understanding</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left: 137px">HACKERS</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>Although there’s a great deal of disagreement as to what a hacker actually is, especially among hackers themselves, a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>hacker</span> is most commonly defined as anyone who unlawfully breaks into a computer system—either an individual computer or a network (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(14,0)">see Figure 9.8</span>).</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Are there different kinds of hackers?</strong> Some hackers are offended by being labeled as criminals and therefore attempt to classify different types of hackers as follows:</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="white-hat hacker (ethical hacker)">White-hat hackers (or ethical hackers)</span> break in to systems for nonmalicious reasons such as to test system security vulnerabilities or to expose undisclosed weaknesses. They believe in making security vulnerabilities known either to the company that owns the system or software or to the general public, often to embarrass a company into fixing a problem.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="black-hat hacker">Black-hat hackers</span> break into systems to destroy information or for illegal gain. The terms <em>white hat</em> and <em>black hat</em> are references to old Western movies in which the heroes wore white hats and the outlaws wore black hats.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="grey-hat hacker">Grey-hat hackers</span> are a bit of a cross between black and white—they often illegally break into systems merely to flaunt their expertise to the administrator of the system they penetrated or to attempt to sell their services in repairing security breaches.</span></li>
					</ul>
					<p class="start">Regardless of the hackers’ opinions, the laws in the United States and in many other countries consider <em>any</em> unauthorized access to computer systems a crime.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(14,0)"
						style="height: 340px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.8.jpg) no-repeat scroll 27px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.8</span> Hackers can find lots of personal information about you on the Internet. <em>(Wildt, Chris/Cartoonstock)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="15" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Problems Hackers Can Cause</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Could a hacker steal my debit card or bank account number?</strong> Hackers often try to break in to computers or websites that contain credit card information. If you perform financial transactions online, such as banking or buying goods and services, you probably do so using a credit or debit card. Credit card and bank account information can thus reside on your hard drive or an online business’s hard drive and may be detectable by a hacker. </p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Aside from your home computer, you have personal data stored on various websites. For example, many sites require that you provide a login ID and password to gain access. Even if this data isn’t stored on your computer, a hacker may be able to capture it when you’re online by using a <em>packet analyzer</em> (<em>sniffer</em>) or a <em>keylogger</em> (a program that captures all keystrokes made on a computer).</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What’s a packet analyzer?</strong> Data travels through the Internet in small pieces called <em>packets</em>. The packets are identified with an IP address, in part to help identify the computer to which they are being sent. Once the packets reach their destination, they’re reassembled into cohesive messages. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>packet analyzer (sniffer)</span> is a program deployed by hackers that looks at (or sniffs) each packet as it travels on the Internet—not just those addressed to a particular computer, but all packets coming across a particular network. For example, a hacker might sit in a coffee shop and run a packet sniffer to capture sensitive data (such as debit/credit card numbers)</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>from patrons using the coffee shop’s free wireless network. Wireless networks such as these can be particularly vulnerable to this type of exploitation if encryption of data isn’t enabled when the networks are set up. (This topic was covered in more detail in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.generatePages(7)">Chapter 7</span>.)</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What do hackers do with the information they “sniff”?</strong> Once a hacker has your debit/credit card information, he or she can use it to purchase items illegally or can sell the number to someone who will. If a hacker steals the login ID and password to an account where you have your bank card information stored (such as <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://eBay.com','_blank')">eBay</span> or <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Amazon.com','_blank')">Amazon</span>), he or she can also use your account to buy items and have them shipped to him- or herself instead of to you. If hackers can gather enough information in conjunction with your credit card information, they may be able to commit identity theft.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Although this sounds scary, you can easily protect yourself from packet sniffing by installing a firewall (which we discuss later in this chapter) and using data encryption on a wireless network (which was covered in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.generatePages(7)">Chapter 7</span>).</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Trojan Horses and Rootkits</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Besides stealing information, what other problems can hackers cause if they break into my computer?</strong> Hackers often use individuals’ computers as a staging area for mischief. To commit widespread computer attacks, for example, hackers need to control many computers at the same time. To this end, hackers often use Trojan horses to install other programs</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="16" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>on computers. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Trojan horse</span> is a program that appears to be something useful or desirable, like a game or a screen saver, but while it runs, it does something malicious in the background, without your knowledge (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(16,0)">see Figure 9.9</span>).</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(16,0)"
						style="height: 410px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.9.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.9</span> The term <i>Trojan horse</i> derives from Greek mythology and refers to the wooden horse that the Greeks used to sneak into the city of Troy and conquer it. Therefore, computer programs that contain a hidden, and usually dreadful, “surprise” are referred to as Trojan horses. <em>(RalfKraft/Fotolia)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What damage can Trojan horses do?</strong> Often, the malicious activity perpetrated by a Trojan horse program is the installation of a backdoor program or a rootkit. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="backdoor program">Backdoor programs</span> and <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>rootkits</span> are programs (or sets of programs) that allow hackers to gain access to your computer and take almost complete control of it without your knowledge. Using a backdoor program, hackers can access and delete all the files on your computer, send e-mail, run programs, and do just about anything else you can do with your computer. A computer that a hacker controls in this manner is referred to as a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>zombie</span>. Zombies are often used to launch <em>denial-of-service attacks</em> on other computers.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Denial-of-Service Attacks</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are denial-of-service attacks?</strong> In a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>denial-of-service (DoS) attack</span>, legitimate users are denied access to a computer system because a hacker is repeatedly making requests of that computer system through a computer he or she has taken over as a zombie. A computer system can handle only a certain number of requests for information at one time. When it is flooded with requests in a DoS attack, it shuts down and refuses to answer any requests for information, even if the requests are from a legitimate user. Thus, the computer is so busy responding to the bogus requests for information that authorized users can’t gain access.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="17" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Couldn’t a DoS attack be traced back to the computer that launched it?</strong> Launching a DoS attack on a computer system from a single computer is easy to trace. Therefore, most savvy hackers use a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="distributed denial of service (DDoS) attack">distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attack</span>, which launches DoS attacks from more than one zombie (sometimes thousands of zombies) at the same time.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(17,1)">Figure 9.10</span> illustrates how a DDoS attack works. A hacker creates many zombies and coordinates them so that they begin sending bogus requests to the same computer at the same time. Administrators of the victim computer often have a great deal of difficulty stopping the attack because it comes from so many computers. Often, the attacks are coordinated automatically by botnets. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>botnet</span> is a large group of software programs (called <em>robots</em> or <em>bots</em>) that runs autonomously on zombie computers. Some botnets have been known to span 1.5 million computers.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Because many commercial websites receive revenue from users, either directly (such as via subscriptions to online games) or indirectly (such as when web surfers click on advertisements), DDoS attacks can be financially distressing for the owners of the affected websites.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(17,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Are Your Photos Helping Criminals Target You?
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight">Zombie Computers</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(17,1)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.10.jpg) no-repeat scroll 22px 65px #FFFFFF; height: 470px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.10</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span>Figure 9.10</span> Zombie computers are used to facilitate a DDoS attack.
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="18" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">How Hackers Gain Computer Access</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How exactly does a hacker gain access to a computer?</strong> Hackers can gain access to computers directly or indirectly:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Direct access involves sitting down at a computer and installing hacking software. It’s unlikely that such an attack would occur in your home, but it’s always a wise precaution to set up your computer so that it requires a password for a user to gain access.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">The most likely method a hacker will use to access a computer is to enter indirectly through its Internet connection.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Many people forget that their Internet connection is a two-way street. Not only can you access the Internet, but people on the Internet can access your computer. Think of your computer as a house. Common sense tells you to lock your home’s doors and windows to deter theft when you aren’t there. Hooking your computer up to the Internet without protection is like leaving the front door to your house wide open. Your computer obviously  doesn’t have doors and windows like a house, but it does have logical ports.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What are logical ports?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="logical port">Logical ports</span> are virtual—that is, not physical—communications gateways or paths that allow a computer to organize requests for information, such as web page downloads or e-mail routing, from other networks or computers. Unlike physical ports, such as USB ports, you can’t see or touch a logical port; it’s part of a computer’s internal organization.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Logical ports are numbered and assigned to specific services. For instance, logical port 80 is designated for hypertext transfer protocol (HTTP), the main communications protocol for the web. Thus, all requests for information from your browser to the web flow through logical port 80. Open logical ports, like open windows in a home, invite intruders, as illustrated in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(18,0)">Figure 9.11</span>. Unless you take precautions to restrict access to your logical ports, other people on the Internet may be able to access your computer through them.</p>
					<p class="start">Fortunately, you can thwart most hacking problems by installing a firewall, which we discuss next.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(18,0)"
						style="height: 292px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.11.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.11</span> Open logical ports are an invitation to hackers.</figcaption>
   			</figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="19" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="greenHeadingLineDashed"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/protectingAssetsThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">restricting access to your</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:126px;">DIGITAL ASSETS</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>Keeping hackers at bay is often just a matter of keeping them out. You can achieve this by:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Preventing hackers from accessing your computer (usually through your Internet connection)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Protecting your digital information in such a way that it can’t be accessed (by using passwords, for example)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Hiding your activities from prying eyes</span></li>
					</ul>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">In this section, we explore strategies for protecting access to your digital assets and keeping your Internetsurfing activities from being seen by the wrong people.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Firewalls</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What is a firewall?</strong> A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>firewall</span> is a software program or hardware device designed to protect computers from hackers. It’s named after a housing construction feature that slows the spread of fires from house to house. A firewall specifically designed for home networks is called a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>personal firewall</span>. By using a personal firewall, you can close open logical ports to invaders and potentially make your computer invisible to other computers on the Internet.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>Which is better, a software firewall or a hardware firewall?</strong> Both hardware and software firewalls will protect you from hackers. One type isn’t better than the other. Although installing either a software or a hardware firewall on your home network is probably sufficient, you should consider installing both for maximum protection. This will provide you with additional safety, just as wearing multiple layers of clothing helps keep you warmer in the winter than a single layer.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Types of Firewalls</h2>
					<p><strong>What software firewalls are there?</strong> Both Windows and OS X include reliable firewalls. The Windows Action Center is a good source of information about the security settings on your computer (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(19,0)">see Figure 9.12</span>), including the status of your firewall. Security suites such as Norton Internet Security, McAfee Internet Security, and ZoneAlarm Internet Security Suite</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(19,0)" style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9.12.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent;
							    height: 202px;
								margin-bottom: 5px;">
								
					<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:123px;">
						<span>Figure 9.12</span> The security section of the Windows Action Center provides the status of programs protecting your computer.
						</figcaption>
						<div class="playIcon bottomPos" style="margin-bottom:48px; margin-left:288px;"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_12.html','_blank')"></div>
						</figure>
			<br/>
				<p style="margin-top:-50px;"><em>>To view the Action Center, access the Control Panel, select <strong>System and Security</strong>, and then click the <strong>Action Center</strong> link.</em></p>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="20" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">also include firewall software. Although the firewalls that come with Windows and OS X will protect your computer, firewalls included in security suites often come with additional features such as monitoring systems that alert you if your computer is under attack.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">If you’re using a security suite that includes a firewall, the suite should disable the firewall that came with your OS. Two firewalls running at the same time can conflict with each other and cause your computer to slow down or freeze up.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What are hardware firewalls?</strong> You can also buy and configure hardware firewall devices. Many routers sold for home networks include firewall protection. Just like software firewalls, the setup for hardware firewalls is designed for novices, and the default configuration on most routers keeps unused logical ports closed. Documentation accompanying routers can assist more-experienced users in adjusting the settings to allow access to specific ports if needed.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">How Firewalls Work</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How do firewalls protect you from hackers?</strong> Firewalls are designed to restrict access to a network and its computers. Firewalls protect you in two major ways:</p>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">By blocking access to logical ports and</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">By keeping your computer’s network address secure</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How do firewalls block access to your logical ports?</strong> Certain logical ports are very popular in hacker attacks. To block access to logical ports, firewalls examine data packets that your computer sends and receives. Data packets contain information such as the address of the sending and receiving computers and the logical port the packet will use. Firewalls can be configured so that they filter out packets sent to specific logical ports in a process known as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>packet filtering</span>. Firewalls are also often configured to ignore requests that originate from the Internet asking for access to certain ports. This process is referred to as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>logical port blocking</span>. By using filtering and blocking, firewalls keep hackers from accessing your computer (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(20,0)">Figure 9.13</span>).</p>
					
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes TMargin5">Using Firewalls</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(20,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.13.jpg) no-repeat scroll 42px 40px #FFFFFF; height: 245px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.13</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span>Figure 9.13</span> Firewalls use filtering and blocking to keep out unwanted data and keep your network safe. <em>(Intelligent Computer Solutions)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="21" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How do firewalls keep your network address secure?</strong> Every computer connected to the Internet has a unique address called an <em>Internet Protocol address (IP address)</em>. Data is routed to the correct computer on the Internet based on the IP address. This is similar to how a letter finds its way to your mailbox. You have a unique postal address for your home. If a hacker finds out the IP address of your computer, he or she can locate it on the Internet and try to break into it. This is similar to how a conventional thief might target your home after finding out you collect antique cars by using your street address to locate your house.</p>
					<p class="start">Your IP address for your home network is assigned to your router by your Internet service provider (ISP), but each device on your home network also has an IP address. Firewalls use a process called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>network address translation (NAT)</span> to assign internal IP addresses on a network. The internal IP addresses are used only on the internal network and therefore can’t be detected by hackers. For hackers to access your computer, they must know your computer’s internal IP address. With a NAT–capable router/firewall installed on your network, hackers are unable to access the internal IP address assigned to your computer, so your computer is safe. You can </p>
					<br/>
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain noTMargin">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_21.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Understanding Firewalls
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about how hackers can attack networks and what harm they can cause, as well as what a firewall does to keep a computer safe from hackers.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>use NAT in your home by purchasing a hardware firewall with NAT capabilities. Many routers sold for home use are also configured as firewalls, and many feature NAT.</p>
					
					<div class="soundByteContain">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/installing_firewall/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Installing a Personal Firewall
						</div>
						Firewalls provide excellent protection against hackers on a home network. In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn how to install and configure software firewalls to protect your computer.
					</div></div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Knowing Your Computer Is Secure</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I tell if my computer is at risk?</strong> For peace of mind, you can visit websites that offer free services that test your computer’s vulnerability. One popular site is Gibson Research (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://grc.com','_blank')">grc.com</span>). The company’s ShieldsUP and LeakTest programs are free and easy to run and can pinpoint security vulnerabilities in a system connected to the Internet. If you get a clean report from these programs, your system is probably not vulnerable to attack. See the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,29)">Try This</span> section in this chapter for instructions on how to test your system.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What if I don’t get a clean report from the testing program?</strong> If the testing program detects potential vulnerabilities and you don’t have a firewall, you should install one as soon as possible. If the firewall is already configured and common ports (such as those shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(32)" closescript="compTia.modules.toggleModule(0)">Figure 9.14</span>) are identified as being vulnerable, consult your firewall documentation for instructions on how to close or restrict access to those ports.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="22" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes font_21">Common Logical Ports</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(22,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.14.jpg) no-repeat scroll 60px 36px #FFFFFF; height: 215px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.14</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Password Protection and Password Management</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I best use passwords to protect my computer?</strong> You no doubt have many passwords you need to remember to access your digital life. However, creating strong passwords—ones that are difficult for hackers to guess—is an essential piece of security  that people sometimes overlook. Password-cracking programs have become more sophisticated. In fact, some commonly available programs can test more than one million password combinations per second! Creating a secure password is therefore more important than ever.</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(22,1)" class="readMore"></a>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Creating Passwords</h2>
					<p><strong>What constitutes a strong password?</strong> Strong passwords are difficult for someone to guess. Follow these guidelines to create strong passwords (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)">see Figure 9.15</span>):</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t use easily deduced components related to your life, such as parts of your name, your pet’s name, your street address, or the name of the website or institution for which you are creating the password (i.e., don’t use “Citibank” for your online banking password).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Use a password that is at least 14 characters long. Longer passwords are more difficult to deduce.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t use words found in the dictionary.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Use a mix of upper- and lowercase letters and symbols (such as # or %).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Never tell anyone your password or write it down in a place where others might see it, like in your wallet or purse.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Change your passwords on a regular basis, such as monthly or quarterly. Your school or your employer probably requires you to change your password regularly. This is also a good idea for your personal passwords.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t use the same password for every account you have.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">If you have trouble thinking of secure passwords, there are many password generators available for  free, such as the Strong Password Generator (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://strongpasswordgenerator.com','_blank')">strongpasswordgenerator.com</span>).</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="23" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight">Strong and Weak Password Candidates</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.15.jpg) no-repeat scroll 15px 42px #FFFFFF; height: 195px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.15</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I check the strength of my passwords?</strong> You can use online password strength testers, such as the Password Meter (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://passwordmeter.com','_blank')">passwordmeter.com</span>), to evaluate your passwords. The Password Meter provides guidelines for good passwords and shows you how integrating various elements, such as symbols, affects the strength score of your password.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I restrict access to my computer?</strong> Windows, OS X, and most other operating systems have built-in password (or passcode) protection for files as well as the entire desktop. After a certain period of idle time, your computer is automatically password locked, and your password must be entered to gain access to the computer. This provides excellent protection from casual snooping if you need to walk away</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>from your computer for a period of time. If someone attempts to log on to your computer without your password, that person won’t be able to gain access. It’s an especially good idea to use passwords on laptop computers, smartphones, and tablets because this provides additional protection of your data if your device is lost or stolen.</p>
					<p class="start">Windows 8 allows you to use picture passwords. You select a picture and then draw three gestures on it—either straight lines, circles, or taps. This picture then works as an additional method for accessing your computer. You just unlock your computer by repeating the  gestures (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,1)">see Figure 9.16</span>). But if you forget your gestures, you can always access your computer via the conventional password.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,1)"
						style="height: 240px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.16.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.16</span> Drawing three gestures on your picture (and repeating them three times) sets your picture password options in Windows 8.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
					
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g1OOq1t8Ybk','_blank')">To learn more about picture passwords, click here.</span></p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="24" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Managing Your Passwords</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How can I remember all of my complex passwords?</strong> Good security practices suggest that you have different passwords for all the different websites that you access and that you change your passwords frequently. The problem with well-constructed passwords is that they can be hard to remember. Fortunately, password-management tools are now available. They take the worry out of forgetting passwords because the password-management software does the remembering for you.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Where can I obtain password-management software?</strong>  Most current Internet security suites and web browsers make it easy to keep track of passwords by providing passwordmanagement tools. For example, Internet Explorer (IE) 10 will remember passwords for you. When you go to a website that requires a login, IE 10 will display a dialog box prompting you to have IE remember the password for the site (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,1)">see Figure 9.17</span>). Then, when you return to the site and type in your user name, IE will fill in the password information for you using a process known as auto complete. However, there are some passwords that you shouldn’t have your browser remember, such as your online banking password. So be selective when using this feature.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5" style="width:394px;">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Connecting to Wireless Networks on the Road? Beware of  “Evil Twins”!
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,1)"
						style="height: 169px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.17.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.17</span> The password bar in IE 10 displays whenever you type in a password for a website for which IE hasn’t yet stored the password.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Anonymous Web Surfing: Hiding from Prying Eyes</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Should I be concerned about surfing the Internet on shared, public, or work computers?</strong> If you use shared computers in public places such as libraries, coffee shops, or student unions, you never know what nefarious tools have been installed by hackers on a public computer. When you browse the Internet, traces of your activity are left behind on that computer, often as temporary files. A wily hacker can glean sensitive information long after you’ve finished your surfing session. In addition, many employers routinely review the Internet browsing history of employees to ensure that workers are spending their time on the Internet productively.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="25" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What tools can I use to keep my browsing activities private when surfing the Internet?</strong> The current versions of Google Chrome, Firefox, and Internet Explorer include privacy tools (called Incognito, Private Browsing, and InPrivate, respectively) that help you surf the web anonymously (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(25,0)">see Figure 9.18</span>). When you choose to surf anonymously, all three browsers open special versions of their browser windows that are enhanced for privacy. When surfing in these windows, records of websites you visit and files you download don’t appear in the web browser’s history files. Furthermore, any temporary files generated in that browsing session are deleted when you exit the special window.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Are there any other tools I could use to protect my privacy?</strong> Portable privacy devices, such as the Imation Personal Flash Drive (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://imation.com','_blank')">imation.com</span>), provide an even higher level of surfing privacy. Simply plug the device into an available USB port on the machine on which you’ll be working. All sensitive Internet files, such as cookies, Internet history, and browser caches, will be stored on the privacy device, not on the computer you’re using. Privacy devices such as these often come preloaded with software designed to shield your IP address from prying eyes, making it difficult (if not impossible) for hackers to tell where you’re surfing on the Internet. These privacy devices also have password-management tools that store all of your login information and encrypt it so it will be safe if your privacy device falls into someone else’s hands.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9.18.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent;
							    height: 510px;
								margin-bottom: 5px;">
								<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(25,0)" style="
									height: 458px;
									margin: 10px 0 0 93px;">
								</div>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_18.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 9.18</span> The current versions of the Firefox, Internet Explorer, and Google Chrome browsers all feature privacy tools for web surfing.
						</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="26" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>Is there anything else I can do to keep my data safe on shared computers?</strong> Another free practical solution is to take the Linux OS with you on a flash drive and avoid using the public or work computer’s OS. The interfaces of many Linux distros look almost exactly like Windows and are easy to use. There are several advantages to using a Linux-based OS on a public or work computer:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Your risk of picking up viruses and other malicious programs is significantly reduced because booting a computer from a flash drive completely eliminates any interaction with the computer’s OS. This, in turn, significantly reduces the chance that your flash drive will become infected by any malware running on the computer.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Virus and hacking attacks against Linux are far less likely than attacks against Windows. Because Windows has about 90% of the OS market, people who write malware tend to target Windows systems.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">When you run software from your own storage medium, such as a flash drive, you avoid reading and writing to the hard disk of the computer. This significantly enhances your privacy because you don’t leave traces of your activity behind.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">Pendrivelinux (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://pendrivelinux.com','_blank')">pendrivelinux.com</span>) is an excellent resource that offers many different versions of Linux for download and includes step-by-step instructions on how to install them on your flash drive (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,0)">see Figure 9.19</span>). If you’re a Mac user, the gOS version of Linux provides a close approximation of OS X, so you can feel right at home.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Do I need to take special precautions with my tablet devices?</strong>Tablets like the iPad run their own proprietary operating systems that differ from the operating systems deployed on laptop and desktop computers. Although tablet operating systems do contain security features, they may not be robust enough to satisfy business users who have a great deal of confidential information on their tablets, especially when the devices are connected to wireless networks. Third-party software developers are now offering many apps to enhance tablet security. Comprehensive suites like IPVanish (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://ipvanish.com','_blank')">ipvanish.com</span>) offer features such as government-grade encryption of data, enhanced e-mail security, and anonymous web surfing. So look for security apps that are specifically designed for your tablet device if you often deal with sensitive data on your tablet, such as online banking.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,0)"
						style="height: 215px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.19.jpg) no-repeat scroll 75px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.19</span> <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Pendrivelinux.com','_blank')">Pendrivelinux.com</span> can help you load a version of Linux onto a flash drive.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="27" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Biometric Authentication Devices</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Besides passwords, how else can I restrict the use of my computer?</strong> A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>biometric authentication device</span> is a device that reads a unique personal characteristic such as a fingerprint or the iris pattern in your eye and converts its pattern to a digital code. When you use the device, your pattern is read and compared to the one stored on the computer. Only users having an exact fingerprint or iris pattern match are allowed to access the computer.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Because no two people have the same biometric characteristics (fingerprints and iris patterns are unique), these devices provide a high level of security. They also eliminate the human error that can occur in password protection. You might forget your password, but you won’t forget to bring your fingerprint to the computer! Some notebooks, such as Lenovo, feature built-in fingerprint readers, and companies like SecuGen produce computer mice and keyboards that include built-in fingerprint readers. Other biometric devices, including voice authentication and face pattern–recognition systems (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(27,0)">see Figure 9.20</span>), are now widely offered in notebook computers.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Make sure to use some (or all) of these methods to keep your activities from prying eyes and to restrict access to your digital information.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(27,0)"
						style="height: 365px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.20.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:169px;">
   				<span>Figure 9.20</span><br/>Face recognition software is now available on laptops. You might forget your password, but you won’t forget to bring your face! <em>(Jochen Tack/Alamy)</em>
					<br/><br/><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.pbs.org/newshour/video/2013/05/29/20130529_facial.mp4','_blank')">For a short video about face recognition software, click here.</span></figcaption>
   			</figure>
				
					<br/>	
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to Part 2:</strong>
							<span class="dot">Watch <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/Chapter_9_Part_1/Chapter_9_Part_1.html','_blank')" >Replay Video 9.1</span>.</span>
							<span class="dot">Then <span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(31)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="28" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">Have you ever been infected with a computer virus?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Yes</li>
						<li>No</li>
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="29" type="Full" distinction=""
				customscript="compTia.modules.toggleModule(32)" closescript="compTia.modules.toggleModule(0)">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="30" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingBlueBackDiagDashes">Protecting Your Digital Property from Yourself</div>
					<p class="digCompP">Often, we can be our own worst enemies when using computing devices. If you’re not careful, you might be taken in by thieves or scam artists who want to steal your digital and physical assets. Being aware of the tricks and traps that criminals use allows you to take steps to avoid being scammed.</p>
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashedEnd"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB"
						 style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/spamThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">managing online</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left: 120px;">ANNOYANCES</div>
					</div>
					<p>Surfing the web, sending and receiving e-mail, and chatting online have become common parts of most of our lives. Unfortunately, the web has become fertile ground for people who want to advertise their products, track our browsing behaviors, or even con people into revealing personal information. In this section, we’ll look at ways in which you can manage, if not avoid, these and other online headaches.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Malware: Adware and Spyware</h2>
					<p><strong>What is malware?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Malware</span> is software that has a malicious intent (hence the prefix <em>mal</em>). There are three primary forms of malware: adware, spyware, and viruses. Adware and spyware are not physically destructive like viruses and worms, which can destroy data. Known collectively as <em>grayware</em>, most malware is intrusive, annoying, or objectionable online programs that are downloaded to your computer when you install or use other online content such as a free program, game, or utility.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>What is adware?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Adware</span> is software that displays sponsored advertisements in a section of your browser window or as a pop-up box. It’s considered a legitimate, though sometimes annoying, means of generating revenue for those developers who do not charge for their software or information. Fortunately, because web browsers such as Firefox, Safari, and Internet Explorer  have built-in pop-up blockers, the occurrence of annoying pop-ups has been greatly reduced.</p>
					<p class="start">Some pop-ups, however, are legitimate and increase the functionality of the originating site. For example, your account balance may pop up on your bank’s website. To control which sites to allow popups on, you can access the pop-up blocker settings in your browser (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(30,0)">see Figure 9.21</span>) and add websites for which you allow pop-ups. Whenever a pop-up is blocked, the browser displays an information bar or plays a sound to alert you. If you feel the pop-up is legitimate, you can choose to accept it.</p>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(30,0)" style=" height:170px; background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/fig9.21.jpg) 0px 0; margin-top: 15px;">
							
							<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:169px;">
								<span>Figure 9.21</span> <br/>Firefox’s Allowed Sites - <br/>Pop-ups dialog box lets you control which sites you’ll allow to display pop-ups.
							</figcaption>
							<div class="playIcon" style="margin-top: 75px; margin-left: 245px;"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_21.html','_blank')"></div>
							</figure>
							
							<p><em>>To display the pop-up blocker in Firefox, from the Tools menu, select <strong>Options</strong>, and then click the <strong>Content</strong> tab.</em></p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="31" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="orangeHorzButton" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,0)">
						<span class="largeBoldWhite">ethics</span>
						<span class="medBoldGrey">in IT</span>
						<strong style="font-size:14px;" class="shiftUp10">You’re Being Watched ...<br/>But Are You Aware You’re Being Watched?</strong>
					</div>
					<br/>

					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What is spyware?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Spyware</span> is an unwanted piggyback program that usually downloads with other software you install from the Internet and that runs in the background of your system. Without your knowledge, spyware transmits information about you, such as your Internet-surfing habits, to the owner of the program so that the information can be used for marketing purposes. Many spyware programs use tracking cookies (small text files stored on your computer) to collect information. One type of spyware program known as a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="keystroke logger (keylogger)">keystroke logger (key logger)</span> monitors keystrokes with the intent of stealing passwords, login IDs, or credit card information.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Can I prevent spyware from spying on me?</strong> Anti-spyware software detects unwanted programs and allows you to delete the offending software easily. Most Internet security suites now include anti-spyware software. You can also obtain stand-alone anti-spyware software and run it on your computer to delete unwanted spyware. Because so many variants of spyware exist, your Internet security software may not detect all types that attempt to install themselves on your computer. Therefore, it’s a good idea to install one or two additional stand-alone anti-spyware programs on your computer.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Because new spyware is created all the time, you should update and run your anti-spyware software regularly. Windows comes with a program</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,1)" style=" height:150px; background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/fig9.23.jpg) 0px 0; margin-top: 15px;">
							
							<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:115px;">
								<span>Figure 9.23</span> <br/>After performing a routine scan of a computer, <span class="strongDBlue"onclick="window.open('http://malwarebytes.org','_blank')">Malwarebytes</span> returns a log of problems found on the system.
							</figcaption>
						</figure>	
					
					<p>called Windows Defender, which scans your system for spyware and other potentially unwanted software. Malwarebytes Anti-Malware, Ad-Aware, and Spybot–Search & Destroy (all available from <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://download.com','_blank')">download.com</span>) are other antispyware programs that are easy to install and update. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,1)">Figure 9.23</span> shows an example of Malwarebytes in action.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Spam</h2>		
					<p><strong>How can I best avoid spam?</strong> Companies that send out <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spam</span>—unwanted or junk e-mail—find your e-mail address either from a list they purchase or with software that looks for e-mail addresses on the Internet. Unsolicited instant messages are also a form of spam, called <em>spim</em>. If you’ve used your e-mail address to purchase anything online, open an online account, or participate in a social network such as Facebook, youre-mail address eventually will appear on one of the lists that spammers get.</p>
					<p class="start">One way to avoid spam in your primary account is to create a free e-mail address that you use only when you fill out forms or buy items on </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="32" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">the web. For example, both Windows Mail and Yahoo! let you set up free e-mail accounts. If your free e-mail account is saturated with spam, you can abandon that account with little inconvenience. It’s much less convenient to abandon your primary e-mail address.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Another way to avoid spam is to filter it. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spam filter</span> is an option you can select in your e-mail account that places known or suspected spam messages into a special folder (called “Spam” or “Junk Mail”). Most web-based e-mail services, such as Hotmail and Yahoo!, offer spam filters (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(32,0)">see Figure 9.24</span>). Microsoft Outlook also features a spam filter.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">You can also buy third-party programs that provide some control over spam, including SPAMfighter, which you can download at <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://download.com','_blank')">download.com</span>.</p>
					
					<figure class="TMargin15" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(32,0)" style=" height:188px; background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/fig9.24.jpg) -1px 0; margin-right:-15px;">
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos">
								<span>Figure 9.24</span> In Yahoo! Mail, messages identified as spam are directed into a folder called “Spam” for review and deletion. <em>(SVLuma/shutterstock)</em>
							</figcaption>
						</figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How do spam filters work?</strong> Spam filters and filtering software can catch as much as 95% of spam by checking incoming e-mail subject headers and senders’ addresses against databases of known spam. Spam filters also check your e-mail for frequently used spam patterns and keywords, such as “for free” and “over 21.” Spam filters aren’t perfect, and you should check the spam folder before deleting its contents because legitimate e-mail might end up there by mistake. Most programs let you reclassify e-mails that have been misidentified as spam (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(32,0)">see Figure 9.24</span>).</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How else can I prevent spam?</strong> Here are a few other ways you can prevent spam:</p>
					
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Before registering on a website, read its privacy policy to see how it uses your e-mail address. Don’t give the site permission to pass on your e-mail address to third parties.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t reply to spam to remove yourself from the spam list. By replying, you’re confirming that your email address is active. Instead of stopping spam, you may receive more.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Subscribe to an e-mail forwarding service such as VersaForward (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://versaforward.com','_blank')">versaforward.com</span>) or Sneakemail (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://sneakemail.com','_blank')">sneakemail.com</span>). These services screen your e-mail messages, forwarding only those messages you designate as being okay to accept.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="33" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Cookies</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are cookies?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="cookie">Cookies</span> are small text files that some websites automatically store on your hard drive when you visit them. When you log on to a website that uses cookies, a cookie file assigns an ID number to your computer. The unique ID is intended to make your return visit to a website more efficient and better geared to your interests. The next time you log on to that site, the site marks your visit and keeps track of it in its database.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What do websites do with cookie information?</strong> Cookies can provide websites with information about your browsing habits, such as the ads you’ve opened, the products you’ve looked at, and the time and duration of your visits. Companies use this information to determine the traffic flowing through their website and the effectiveness of their marketing strategy and placement on websites. By tracking such information, cookies enable companies to identify different users’ preferences.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Can companies get my personal information when I visit their sites?</strong> Cookies do not go through your hard drive in search of personal information such as passwords or financial data. The only personal information a cookie obtains is the information you supply when you fill out forms online.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Do privacy risks exist with cookies?</strong> Some sites sell the personal information their cookies collect to web advertisers who are building huge databases of consumer preferences and habits, collecting personal and business information such as phone numbers, credit reports, and the like. The main concern is that advertisers will use this information indiscriminately, thus invading your privacy. And you may feel your privacy is being violated by cookies that monitor where you go on a website.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Should I delete cookies from my hard drive?</strong> Cookies pose no <em>security</em> threat because it is virtually impossible to hide a virus or malicious software program in a cookie. Because they take up little room on your hard drive, and offer you small conveniences on return visits to websites, there is no great reason to delete them. Deleting your cookie files could actually cause you the inconvenience of reentering data you have already entered into website forms. However, if you’re uncomfortable with the accessibility of your personal information, you can periodically delete cookies (as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(34,0)">Figure 9.26</span>) or configure your browser to block certain types of cookies. Software such as Cookie Pal (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://kburra.com','_blank')">kburra.com</span>) also can help you monitor cookies.</p>
					
					<div class="greenHorzButton" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(33,0)">
						<span class="largeBoldWhite">DIG DEEPER</span>
						<strong>Computer Forensics: How It Works</strong>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="34" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9.26.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent;
							    height: 378px;
								margin-bottom: 5px;margin-right:-25px;">
								<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(34,0)" style="
									height: 325px;
									margin: 10px 0 0 93px;">
								</div>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_26.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 9.26</span> Tools are available, either through your browser (Firefox is shown here) or as separate programs, to distinguish between cookies you want to keep and cookies you don’t want on your system.
						</figcaption></figure>
					<br/>
					<p><em>>On the Firefox menu toolbar, click <strong>Tools</strong>, click <strong>Options</strong>, choose the <strong>Privacy tab</strong>, and then click the <strong>remove individual cookies</strong> link to display the Cookies dialog box.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashed"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB"
						 style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/engineeringThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">keeping your</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left: 119px;">DATA SAFE</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>People are often too trusting or just plain careless when it comes to protecting private information about themselves or their digital data. In this section, we discuss ways to keep your data safe from damage, either accidental or intentional, and to keep unscrupulous individuals from tricking you into revealing sensitive information.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Protecting Your Personal Information</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">If a complete stranger walked up to you on the street and asked you for your address and phone number, would you give it to him or her? Of course you wouldn’t! But many people are much less careful when it comes to sharing sensitive information online. And often people inadvertently share information that they really only intended to share with their friends. With cybercrimes like identify theft rampant, you need to take steps to protect your personal information.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What information should I never share on websites?</strong> A good rule of thumb is to reveal as little information as possible, especially if the information would be available to everyone. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,0)">Figure 9.27</span> gives you some good guidelines.</p>
					<p class="start">Your Social Security number, phone number, date of birth, and street address are four key pieces of information that identity thieves need to steal</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="35" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,0)"
						style="height: 235px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.27.jpg) no-repeat scroll -2px 0 transparent;margin-right:-13px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.27</span> Internet Information-Sharing Precautions <em>(Mograph/Fotolia; Kevin Largent/Fotolia)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
			<br/>
					<p>an identity. This information should never be shared in a public area on any website.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I tell who can see my information on a social network?</strong> Social networking sites like Facebook make privacy settings available in your profile settings. If you’ve never changed your default privacy settings in Facebook, you’re probably sharing information more widely than you should.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I protect my information on Facebook?</strong> To begin, you need to change your privacy settings from some of the default options. In general, it’s a bad idea to make personal information available to the public, although this is a default setting for some items in Facebook. It’s a good idea to set most of the options in your profile’s Basic Information section (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,1)">see Figure 9.28a</span>) to Friends or to Only Me because, presumably, these are </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,1)"
						style="height: 233px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.28.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 9.28</span> You should review the (a) Basic Information and (b) Contact Information privacy settings in Facebook to ensure you aren’t sharing too much information.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
			<br/>
			
					<p>personal details you should wish to share only with friends.</p>
					<p class="start">In the Contact Information section (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,1)">see Figure 9.28b</span>), restricting this information only to friends or to yourself is imperative. You don’t want scammers contacting you via e-mail or snail mail and trying to trick you into revealing sensitive information.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Backing Up Your Data</h2>
					<p><strong>How might I damage the data on my computer?</strong> The data on your computer faces three major threats:</p>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Unauthorized access</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Tampering</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Destruction</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="36" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">As noted earlier, a hacker can gain access to your computer and steal or alter your data. However, a more likely scenario is that you’ll lose your data unintentionally. You may accidentally delete files. You may drop your laptop on the ground, causing the hard drive to break and resulting in complete data loss. A virus from an e-mail attachment you opened may destroy your original file. Your house may catch fire and destroy your computer. Because many of these possibilities are beyond your control, you should have a strategy for backing up your files (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(36,0)">see Figure 9.29</span>). <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="backup">Backups</span> are copies of files that you can use to replace the originals if they’re lost or damaged.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What types of files do I need to back up?</strong> Two types of files need backups:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Program files</span> include files used to install software, usually found on DVDs or downloaded from the Internet. As long as you have the DVDs in a safe place, you shouldn’t need to back up these program files. If you’ve downloaded a program file from the Internet, however, you should make a copy of the program installation files on a removable storage device as a backup.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="data file">Data files</span> include files you’ve created or purchased, such as research papers, spreadsheets, music and photo files, contact lists, address books, e-mail archives, and your Favorites list from your browser.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>What types of backups can I perform?</strong> There are two main options for backing up files:</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">An <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="incremental backup (partial backup)">incremental backup</span> (or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="incremental backup (partial backup)">partial backup</span>) involves backing up only files that have changed or have been created since the last backup was performed. Using backup software that has an option for incremental backups will save time because backing up files that haven’t changed is redundant.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">An <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="image backup (system backup)">image backup</span> (or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="image backup (system backup)">system backup</span>) means that all system, application, and data files are backed up, not just the files that changed. Although incremental backups are more efficient, an image backup ensures you capture changes to application files, such as automatic software updates, that an incremental backup might not capture. The idea of imaging is to make an exact copy of the setup of your computer so that in the event of a total hard drive failure you could copy the image to a new hard drive and have your computer configured exactly the way it was before the crash.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21">An Effective Backup Strategy</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(36,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.29.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 37px #FFFFFF; height: 182px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.29</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="37" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>Where should I store my backups?</strong> To be truly secure, backups must be stored away from where your computer is located and should be stored in at least two different places. You wouldn’t want a fire or a flood destroying the backups along with the original data. You have three main choices for where to back up your files (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,0)">see Figure 9.30</span>):</p>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong"><em>Online (in the cloud)</em>: The beauty of online storage is that you don’t need to be at your home computer or lug around your external hard drive to access your data. More important, because the information is stored online, it’s in a secure, remote location, so data is much less vulnerable to the disasters that could harm data stored in your computer or external hard drive. Free storage options include Microsoft SkyDrive (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://skydrive.com','_blank')">skydrive.com</span>) and ADrive (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://adrive.com','_blank')">adrive.com</span>). However, image backups probably won’t fit within the storage limits offered by free providers. For a fee, companies such as Carbonite (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://carbonite.com','_blank')">carbonite.com</span>) and IBackup (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://ibackup.com','_blank')">ibackup.com</span>) provide larger storage capacity.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong"><em>External hard drives</em>: External hard drives, or even large-capacity flash drives, are popular backup options that are usually connected to a single computer. Although convenient and inexpensive, using external hard drives for backups still presents the dilemma of keeping the hard drive in a safe location. Also, external hard drives can fail, possibly leading to loss of your backed-up data. Therefore, using an external hard drive for backups is best done in conjunction with an online backup strategy for added safety.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_15">A Comparison of Typical Data Backup Locations</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.30.jpg) no-repeat scroll 12px 50px #FFFFFF; height: 250px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.30</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong"><em>Network-attached storage (NAS) devices and home servers</em>: NAS devices are essentially large hard drives connected to a network of computers instead of one computer, and they can be used to back up multiple computers simultaneously. Home servers also act as high-capacity NAS devices for automatically backing up data and sharing files.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>How often should I back up my data files?</strong> You should back up your data files every time you make changes to them, which can be difficult to remember to do. Fortunately, most backup software can be configured to do backups automatically so you don’t forget to perform them. For example, </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="38" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">with the Windows 8 File History utility, you can have Windows automatically save your data files from your libraries, desktop, contacts, and favorites to an external hard drive or NAS device. The default setting for File History saves files you changed every hour to the backup location you specify. File History even keeps previous versions of the file on the backup drive so you can revert to a previous version of the file if you need to do so.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">To set up File History, you first need to connect an external hard drive to your computer or a NAS device to your network. You can then access File History through the Control Panel (in the System and Security group) and set it up (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,0)">see Figure 9.31</span>). Once configured, your data files will be backed up as often as you indicate. You can also restore files that you’ve backed up from the File History utility.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How often should I create an image backup?</strong> Because your program and OS files don’t change as often as your data files, you can perform image backups on a less frequent basis. You might consider scheduling an image backup of your entire system on a weekly basis, but you should definitely perform one after installing new software.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How do I perform an image backup?</strong> Windows 8 includes the Windows 7 File Recovery utility, which provides a quick and easy way to schedule regular image backups. You can access this utility from the Windows 7 File Recovery link on the File History screen (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,0)">see Figure 9.31</span>).</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9.31.jpg) no-repeat scroll -4px 0px transparent;
							    height: 336px;">
								<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,0)" style="
									height: 284px;
									margin: 10px 0 0 93px;">
								</div>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_31.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 9.31</span> You can use the Windows 8 File History utility to back up files and restore files from a previous backup.
						</figcaption></figure>
					<br/>
					<p><em>>Access the Control Panel, select the <strong>System and Security</strong> group, and then click the <strong>File History</strong> link.</em></p>	
					
					<br/>
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/managing_computer_security/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Managing Computer Security with Windows Tools
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn how to monitor and control your computer security using features built into the Windows OS.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="39" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>Before starting this utility, make sure your external hard drive or NAS device is connected to your computer or network and is powered on. To set it up, follow these steps:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">When you start the Windows 7 File Recovery utility for the first time, no backups will have ever been configured. Select the Set up backup option to launch the Set up backup dialog box (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(39,0)">see Figure 9.32a</span>) and display a list of available backup devices. Select a device, and click Next to proceed.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">On the next screen (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(39,0)">Figure 9.32b</span>), you have the option to let Windows choose what to back up or to choose for yourself what you want to back up. If you let Windows choose, your backup will include your data files as well as a system image backup. Click Next to proceed.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">On the following screen, you can review your settings and set up a schedule for the backups. When you click the Save settings and exit button, you are returned to the Back up or restore your files screen (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(39,0)">Figure 9.32c</span>), which now shows the scheduled backup. You can also choose to restore backed-up files you have backed up from this screen.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start">From the Back up or restore your files screen, you can also create a system repair disk by clicking on the appropriate link. A system repair disc is a DVD that you can use to boot your computer in case of a serious Windows error. You also use this disc when you need to restore your computer from an image backup, so it’s a good idea to create the repair disc before you begin using your computer heavily.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(39,0)" style=" height:539px; background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/fig9.32.jpg) 0px 0;">
							
							<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:93px;">
								<span>Figure 9.32</span> <br/>The Windows 7 File Recovery utility allows you to perform an image backup. (a) Select your backup destination. (b) Choose locations to back up. (c) Review your scheduled backups, restore files, or start the wizard to create a system repair disc.
							</figcaption>
							<div class="playIcon" style="margin-top: 205px; margin-left: 320px;"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_9_32.html','_blank')"></div>
							</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="40" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What about backing up Apple computers?</strong> For OS X users, backups are very easy to configure. The Time Machine feature in OS X detects when an external hard drive is connected to the computer or a NAS device is connected to your network. You’re then asked if you want this to be your backup drive. If you answer yes, all of your files (including OS files) are automatically backed up to the external drive or NAS device.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Should I back up my files that are stored on my school’s network?</strong> Most likely, if you’re allowed to store files on your school’s network, these files are backed up regularly. You should check with your school’s network administrators to determine how often they’re backed up and how you would request that files be restored from the backup if they’re damaged or deleted. But don’t rely on these network backups to bail you out if your data files are lost or damaged. It may take days for the network administrators to restore your files. It’s better to keep backups of your data files yourself, especially homework and project files, so that you can immediately restore them.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeMidDiagDashes"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingBO bgPosition00" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/engineeringThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="dblue" style="margin-left:59px; color:#166beb">social</div>
						<div class="orange" style="margin-left: 86px">ENGINEERING</div>
					</div>
					
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Social engineering</span> is any technique that uses social skills to generate human interaction that entices individuals to reveal sensitive information. Social engineering often doesn’t involve the use of a computer or face-to-face interaction. For example, telephone scams are a common form of social engineering because it is often easier to manipulate someone when you don’t have to look at them.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How does social engineering work?</strong> Most social engineering schemes use a pretext to lure their victims. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Pretexting</span> involves creating a scenario that sounds legitimate enough that someone will trust you. For example, you might receive a phone call during which the caller says he is from your bank and that someone tried to use your account without authorization. The caller then tells you he needs to confirm a few personal details such as your birth date, Social Security number, bank account number, and whatever other information he can get out of you. The information he obtains can then be used to empty your bank account or commit some other form of fraud. The most common form of pretexting in cyberspace is <em>phishing</em>.</p>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(40,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue">
							<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
							Protect Your Credit Card Number Online
						</div>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="41" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Phishing and Pharming</h2>
					
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How are phishing schemes conducted?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Phishing</span> (pronounced “fishing”) lures Internet users to reveal personal information such as credit card numbers, Social Security numbers, or other sensitive information that could lead to identity theft. The scammers send e-mail messages that look like they’re from a legitimate business such as an online bank. The e-mail usually states that the recipient needs to update or confirm his or her account information. When the recipient clicks on the provided link, he or she goes to a website. The site looks like a legitimate site but is really a fraudulent copy the scammer has created. Once the e-mail recipient enters his or her personal information, the scammers capture it and can begin using it.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Is pharming a type of phishing scam?</strong> Pharming is much more insidious than phishing. Phishing requires a positive action by the person being scammed, such as going to a website mentioned in an e-mail and typing in personal information. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Pharming</span> occurs when malicious code is planted on your computer, either by viruses or by your visiting malicious websites, which then alters your browser’s ability to find web addresses. Users are directed to bogus websites even when they enter the correct address of the real website. You end up at a fake website that looks legitimate but is expressly set up for the purpose of gathering information.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I avoid being caught by phishing and pharming scams?</strong> Follow these guidelines to avoid falling prey to such schemes:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Never reply directly to any e-mail asking you for personal information.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t click on a link in an e-mail to go to a website. Instead, type the website address in the browser.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Check with the company asking for the information and only give the information if you’re certain it’s needed.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Never give personal information over the Internet unless you know the site is secure. Look for the closed padlock, <em>https</em>, or a certification seal such as Norton Secured to help reassure you that the site is secure.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"> Use phishing filters. The latest versions of Firefox, Chrome, and Internet Explorer have phishing filters built in, so each time you access a website, the phishing filter checks for the site’s legitimacy and warns you of possible web forgeries.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Use Internet security software on your computer that’s constantly being updated.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Most Internet security packages can detect and prevent pharming attacks. The major Internet security packages—for example, McAfee and Norton (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(42,0)">see Figure 9.33</span>)—also offer phishing-protection tools. When you have the Norton Toolbar displayed in your browser, you’re constantly informed about the legitimacy of the site you are visiting.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="42" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(42,0)"
						style="height: 212px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.33.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   						<span>Figure 9.33</span> Not sure whether you’re on the eBay website or a cleverly disguised phishing site? Norton Site Safety reassures you that all is well. <em>(Andrea Zanchi/iStockphoto).</em></figcaption>
   					</figure>
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Scareware</h2>
					<p><strong>What is scareware?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Scareware</span> is a type of malware that downloads onto your computer and tries to convince you that your computer is infected with a virus (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(42,1)">see Figure 9.34</span>) or other type of malware. Pop-ups, banners, or other annoying types of messages will flash on your screen saying frightening things like, “Your computer is infected with a virus … immediate removal is required.” You’re then directed to a website where you can buy fake removal or antivirus tools that provide little or no value. Panda Security estimates that scareware scams generate in excess of $34 million a month for cybercriminals. Some scareware even goes so far as to encrypt your files and then demand that you pay to have them unencrypted, which is essentially extortion.</p>
					<p class="start">Scareware is a social engineering technique because it uses people’s fear of computer viruses to convince them to part with their money. </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>Scareware is often designed to be extremely difficult to remove from your computer and to interfere with the operation of legitimate security software. Scareware is usually downloaded onto your computer from infected websites or Trojan horse files.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I protect myself against scareware?</strong> Most Internet security suites, antivirus, and antimalware software packages now detect and prevent the installation of scareware. But make sure you never click on website banners or pop-up boxes that say “Your computer might be infected, click here to scan your files” because these are often the starting points for installing malicious scareware files on your computer.</p>
				<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(42,1)"
						style="height: 233px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.34.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   						<span>Figure 9.34</span> Preying on people’s fears, scareware attempts to convince you that your computer is infected with a virus and you need to purchase a “solution.” <br/><em>(REUTERS/Molly Riley)</em></figcaption>
   					</figure>
				<br/>
					<img onclick="compTia.togglePopup(42,2)" src="assets/images/layout/TrendsinItchapter9.0.png" />
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="43" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="greenHeadingLineDashed"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/phsyicalAssetsThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">protecting your physical</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:126px;">COMPUTING ASSETS</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>Your computer, tablet, and phone aren’t useful to you if they’re damaged. Therefore, it’s essential to select and ensure a safe environment for these devices. This includes protecting them from environmental factors, power surges, power outages, and theft.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Environmental Factors</h2>
					<p><strong>Why is the environment critical to the operation of my computer equipment?</strong> Computers are delicate devices and can be damaged by the adverse effects of abuse or a poor environment. Sudden movements, such as a fall, can damage your computing device’s internal components. You should make sure that your computer sits on a flat, level surface, and if it’s a laptop or a tablet, you should carry it in a protective case.</p>
					<p class="start">Electronic components don’t like excessive heat or excessive cold. Don’t leave computing devices and phones in a car during especially hot or cold weather because components can be damaged by extreme temperatures. Unfortunately, computers generate a lot of heat, which is why they have fans to cool their internal components. Chill mats that contain cooling fans and sit underneath laptop computers are useful accessories for dissipating heat. Make sure that you place your desktop</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>computer where the fan’s intake vents, usually found on the rear of the system unit, are unblocked so air can flow inside.</p>
					<p class="start">Naturally, a fan drawing air into a computer also draws in dust and other particles, which can wreak havoc on your system. Therefore, keep the room in which your computer is located as clean as possible. Finally, because food crumbs and liquid can damage keyboards and other computer components, consume food and beverages away from your computer.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Power Surges</h2>
					<p><strong>What is a power surge?</strong> Power surges occur when electrical current is supplied in excess of normal voltage. Old or faulty wiring, downed power lines, malfunctions at electric company substations, and lightning strikes can all cause power surges. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>surge protector</span> is a device that protects your computer against power surges (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(43,0)">see Figure 9.35</span>).</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(43,0)"
						style="height: 190px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.35.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="rightPos" style="margin-left:260px;">
   						<span>Figure 9.35</span> Surge protectors such as this one are critical for protecting your electronic devices. <em>(aberenyi/Fotolia)</em></figcaption>
   					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="44" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Note that you should replace your surge protectors every two to three years. Also, after a major surge, the surge protector will no longer function and must be replaced. And it’s wise to buy a surge protector that includes indicator lights, which illuminate when the surge protector is no longer functioning properly. Don’t be fooled by old surge protectors—although they can still function as multiple-outlet power strips, they deliver power to your equipment without protecting it.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Besides my computer, what other devices need to be connected to a surge protector?</strong> All electronic devices in the home that have solid-state components, such as TVs, stereos, printers, and cell phones (when charging), should be connected to a surge protector. However, it can be inconvenient to use individual surge protectors on everything. A more practical method is to install a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>whole-house surge protector</span> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(44,0)">see Figure 9.36</span>). Whole-house surge protectors function like other surge protectors, but they protect <em>all</em> electrical devices in the house. Typically, you’ll need an electrician to install a whole-house surge protector, which will cost $300 to $400 (installed).</p>
					
					<br/>
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/surge_protectors_and_ups/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Surge Protectors
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn about the major features of surge protectors and how they work. You’ll also learn about the key factors you need to consider before buying a surge protector, and you’ll see how easy it is to install one.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(44,0)"
						style="height: 220px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.36.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="rightPos" style="margin-right:103px;margin-top:70px;width:140px;">
   						<span>Figure 9.36</span> <br/>A whole-house surge protector usually is installed at the breaker panel or near the electric meter.</figcaption>
   					</figure>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>Is my equipment 100% safe when plugged into a surge protector?</strong> Lightning strikes can generate such high voltages that they can overwhelm a surge protector. As tedious as it sounds, unplugging computers and peripheralsduring an electrical storm is the only way to achieve absolute protection.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Deterring Theft</h2>
					<p><strong>What do I need to worry about if my computing device is stolen?</strong> Because they’re portable, laptops, tablets, and phones are easy targets for thieves. You have four main security concerns with mobile devices:</p>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Keeping them from being stolen</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Keeping data secure in case they are stolen</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Finding a device if it is stolen</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Remotely recovering and wiping data off a stolen device</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="45" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Keep Them Safe: Alarms</h2>
					<p><strong>What type of alarm can I install on my mobile device?</strong> Motion alarm software is a good inexpensive theft deterrent. Free software such as LAlarm (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Ialarm.com','_blank')">Ialarm.com</span>) is effective for laptops. Apps such as SuperAlarm and Alarmomatic help secure your iPad or iPhone. Alarm software either detects motion, like your device being picked up, or sounds near your device and then sets off an ear-piercing alarm until you enter the disable code. Thieves normally don’t like it when attention is drawn to their activities, so alarms can be a very effective theft deterrent.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Keeping Mobile Device Data Secure</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I secure the data on my mobile devices?</strong> Encrypting the data on your mobile device can make it extremely difficult, if not impossible, for thieves to obtain sensitive data from your stolen equipment. Encryption involves transforming your data using an algorithm that can only be unlocked by a secure code (or key). Encrypted data is impossible to read unless it’s decrypted, which requires a secure password, hopefully known only to you.</p>
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(45,0)" class="readMore"></a>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Software Alerts and Data Wipes</h2>
					<p><strong>How can my computer help me recover it when it is stolen?</strong> You’ve probably heard of LoJack, the theft-tracking device used in cars. Similar</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>systems now exist for computers. Tracking software such as Computrace LoJack for Laptops (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://absolute.com','_blank')">absolute.com</span>), PC PhoneHome, and Mac PhoneHome (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://brigadoonsoftware.com','_blank')"> brigadoonsoftware.com</span>) enables your computer to alert authorities to the computer’s location if it is stolen. A similar tracking app for Android and iOS devices is iHound.</p>
					<p class="start">To enable your mobile device to help with its own recovery, you install the tracking software on your device. The software contacts a server at the software manufacturer’s website each time the device connects to the Internet. If your device is stolen, you notify the software manufacturer. The software manufacturer instructs your device to transmit tracking information, such as an IP address, WiFi hotspot, or cell tower location, that will assist authorities in locating and retrieving the mobile device.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What if the thieves find the tracking software and delete it?</strong> The files and directories holding the software aren’t visible to thieves looking for such software, so they probably won’t know the software is there. Furthermore, the tracking software is written in such a way that even if the thieves tried to reformat the hard drive, it would detect the reformat and hide the software code in a safe place in memory or on the hard drive. This works because some sectors of a hard drive are not rewritten during most reformatting. That way, the tracking software can reinstall itself after the reformatting is complete.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What if my device can’t be recovered by the authorities?</strong> In the event that your laptop can’t be recovered, software packages are available</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="46" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(46,0)"
						style="height: 185px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.37.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   						<span>Figure 9.37</span> The Find My iPhone app can help you if your iOS device goes astray.</figcaption>
   					</figure>
					
					<br/>
					<p>that provide for remote recovery and deletion of files. Computrace LoJack for Laptops has these features and allows you to lock your device to keep the thieves from accessing it or to remotely wipe its contents by deleting all your data from your laptop.</p>
					<p class="start">For all iOS devices, Apple offers the Find My iPhone service, which is now part of iCloud. Enabling this service on your device provides you with numerous tools that can assist you in recovering and protecting your mobile devices. Did you forget where you left your iPad? Just sign in with your Apple ID at the iCloud website to see a map showing the location of your iPad (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(46,0)">see Figure 9.37</span>). You can also remotely send a message to be displayed on your lost device, such as your phone number and a reward offer, so that someone who finds it will know what to do. If you can’t recover the device, you can remotely password lock it so no one can use it or, if necessary, wipe all the data off the device to completely protect your privacy.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight cond">Computer Security Checklist</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(46,1)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9.38.jpg) no-repeat scroll 12px 42px #FFFFFF; height: 277px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 9.38</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:10px;margin-bottom:5px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				<br/>	
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I ensure that I’ve covered all aspects of protecting my digital devices?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(46,1)">Figure 9.38</span> provides a guide to ensure you haven’t missed critical aspects of security. If you’ve addressed all of these issues, you can feel reasonably confident that your data and devices are secure.</p>
						
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to Chapter Review:</strong>
							<span class="dot">Watch <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/Chapter_9_Part_2/Chapter_9_Part_2.html','_blank')" >Replay Video 9.2</span>.</span>
							<span class="dot">Then <span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(33)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="47" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">Do you think the U.S. government should censor information on the web, such as instructions for making weapons, to protect the general public?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Yes</li>
						<li>No</li>
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="48" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h1><span class="chapter">9</span> Chapter Review</h1>
				<div class="largerTitle">summary//</div>
	
					<img src="assets/images/pics/cybercrimeSmall.jpg" class="floatPositioned">
					<h2>Cybercrime and Identity Theft</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent1 strong">What is cybercrime, and who perpetrates it?</span>
					<br/><br/>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Cybercrime, is any type of crime perpetrated via a computer or a website.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Major types of cybercrime are identity theft, credit card fraud, computer viruses, illegal access of computer systems, and auction fraud.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Cybercriminals use computers, the Internet, and computer networks to commit their crimes.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/virusSmall.jpg" class="TMargin20 floatPositioned">
					<h2>Protecting Yourself from Computer Viruses</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent2 strong">What are the types of viruses from which I need to protect my computer?</span>
				<br/>	
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">A computer virus is a program that attaches itself to another program and attempts to spread to other computers when files are exchanged</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Computer viruses can be grouped into six categories: (1) boot-sector viruses, (2) logic bombs and time bombs, (3) worms, (4) scripts and macro viruses, (5) e-mail viruses, and (6) encryption viruses. Once run, viruses perform their malicious duties in the background and are often invisible to the user.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<h4>3. What can I do to protect my computer from viruses?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">The best defense against viruses is to install antivirus software. You should update the software on a regular basis and configure it to examine all e-mail attachments for viruses. You should periodically run a complete virus scan on your computer to ensure that no viruses have made it onto your hard drive.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/protectingAssetsSmall.jpg" class="TMargin20 floatPositioned">
					<h2>Protecting Digital Assets from Hackers</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent4 strong">How can hackers attack my computing devices, and what harm can they cause?</span>
				<br/>	
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">A hacker is defined as anyone who breaks into a computer system unlawfully. Hackers can use software to break into almost any computer connected to the Internet, unless proper precautions are taken.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Once hackers gain access to a computer, they can potentially (1) steal personal or other important information, (2) damage and destroy data, or (3) use the computer to attack other computers.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="49" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h4>5. What is a firewall, and how does it keep my computer safe from</h4>
					<h4 class="Lmargin15">hackers?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Firewalls are software programs or hardware devices designed to keep computers safe from hackers. By using a personal firewall, you can close to invaders open logical ports and potentially make your computer invisible to other computers on the Internet.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<h4>6. How do I create secure passwords and manage all of my</h4>
					<h4 class="Lmargin15">passwords?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Secure passwords contain a mixture of upper- and lowercase letters, numbers, and symbols and are at least 14 characters long. Passwords should not contain words that are in the dictionary or easy-to-guess personal information, like your pet’s name.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Online password checkers can be used to evaluate the strength of your passwords.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Utilities built into web browsers and Internet security software can be used to manage your passwords and alleviate the need to remember numerous complex passwords.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<h4>7. How can I surf the Internet anonymously and use biometric</h4>
					<h4 class="Lmargin15">authentication devices to protect my data?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">The current versions of popular browsers include tools, such as Google Chrome’s Incognito feature, that hide your surfing activities by not recording websites that you visit or files that you download in your browser’s history files.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Biometric authentication devices use a physical attribute that is not easily duplicated to control access to data files or computing devices. Some laptops today feature fingerprint readers and facial-recognition software to control access.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/spamSmall.jpg" class="TMargin20 floatPositioned">
					<h2>Managing Online Annoyances</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent8 strong">How do I manage online annoyances such as spyware and spam?</span>
				<br/>	
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">The web is filled with annoyances such as spam, pop-ups, cookies, spyware, and scams such as phishing that make surfing the web frustrating and sometimes dangerous.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Installing anti-malware software tools helps to prevent, detect, and/or reduce spam, adware, and spyware.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/engineeringSmall.jpg" class="TMargin20 floatPositioned">
					<h2>Keeping Your Data Safe</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent9 strong">What data do I need to back up, and what are the best methods for doing so?</span>
				<br/>	
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Data files created by you, such as Word and Excel files, or purchased by you, such as music files, need to be backed up in case they’re inadvertently deleted or damaged. Application software, such as Microsoft Office, may need to be reinstalled if files are damaged, so backups, such as the DVDs the application came on, must be maintained.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">An incremental backup means only files that have changed or been created since the last backup was performed will be backed up. Image</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="50" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="noListStyle">
						<li><span class="innerLi">backups copy all system, application, and data files regardless of whether they changed since the last backup.</span></li>
					</ul>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Websites such as ADrive and SkyDrive are great for backing up individual files. External hard drives are popular choices for holding image backups of your entire system, as are online (cloud) storage sites. Windows and OS X contain solid backup tools that help automate backup tasks.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<h4>10. What is social engineering, and how do I avoid falling prey</h4>
					<h4 class="Lmargin22">to phishing?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Social engineering schemes use human interaction, deception, and trickery to fool people into revealing sensitive information such as credit card numbers and passwords.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Phishing schemes usually involve e-mails that direct the unwary to a website that appears to be legitimate, such as a bank site, but that is specifically designed to capture personal information for committing fraud. To avoid phishing scams, you should never reply directly to any e-mail asking you for personal information and never click on a link in an e-mail to go to a website.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Don’t fall for scareware scams that attempt to frighten you by pretending there is something wrong with your computer.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<img src="assets/images/pics/phsyicalAssetsSmall.jpg" class="floatPositioned">
					<h2>Protecting Your Physical <br/>Computing Assets</h2>
					<span class="prePseudoLi preContent11 strong">&nbsp;How do I protect my physical computing assets from environmental hazards, power surges, and theft?</span>
				<br/>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Computing devices should be kept in clean environments free from dust and other particulates and should not be exposed to extreme temperatures (either hot or cold).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">You should protect all electronic devices from power surges by hooking them up through surge protectors, which will protect them from most electrical surges that could damage the devices.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Mobile devices can be protected from theft by installing software that will (1) set off an alarm if the computer is moved; (2) help recover the computer, if stolen, by reporting the computer’s whereabouts when it is connected to the Internet; and/or (3) allow you to lock or wipe the contents of the digital device remotely.</span></li>
					</ul>	
					
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent semibold textBlack">
							Don't forget to use the study aids included in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or on the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://wps.prenhall.com/bp_evans_techinaction_10/','_blank')">Companion Website</span>. And don’t forget the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/index.html','_blank')">Replay Videos</span>.
						</div>
						</div>
					<br>
					<img src="assets/images/layout/techTouchS9.png" class="techTown" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techtown','_blank')">
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="51" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">chapter 9 glossary//</div>
					
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>adware</span> 430<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>antivirus software</span> 410<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>backdoor program</span> 416<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>backup</span> 436<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>biometric authentication device</span> 427<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>black-hat hacker</span> 414<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>boot-sector virus</span> 407<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>botnet</span> 417<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>computer forensics</span> 433<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>cookie</span> 433<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>cybercrime</span> 403<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>cybercriminal</span> 403<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>cyberloafing</span> 431<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>data breach</span> 442<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>data file</span> 436<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>denial-of-service (DoS) attack</span> 416<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary="distributed denial-of-service (DDoS)">distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attack</span> 417<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>drive-by download</span> 412<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>e-mail virus</span> 408<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>encryption virus</span> 408<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>firewall</span> 419<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>geotag</span> 417<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>grey-hat hacker</span> 414<br/>

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>hacker</span> 414<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>identity theft</span> 404<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>image backup (system backup)</span> 436<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>incremental backup (partial backup)</span> 436<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>inoculation</span> 411<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>keystroke logger (keylogger)</span> 431<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>logical port</span> 418<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>logical port blocking</span> 420<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>logic bomb</span> 407<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>macro virus</span> 408<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>malware</span> 430<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>master boot record</span> 407<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>multipartite virus</span> 409<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>network address translation (NAT)</span> 421<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>packet analyzer (sniffer)</span> 415<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>packet filtering</span> 420<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>personal firewall</span> 419<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>pharming</span> 441<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>phishing</span> 441<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>polymorphic virus</span> 409<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>pretexting</span> 440<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>program files</span> 436<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>quarantining</span> 411<br/>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="52" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary="rootkits">rootkit</span> 416<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>scareware</span> 442<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>script</span> 407<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>social engineering</span> 440<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spam</span> 431<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spam filter</span> 432<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spear phishing</span> 442<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spyware</span> 431<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>stealth virus</span> 409<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>surge protector</span> 443<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>time bomb</span> 407<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Trojan horse</span> 416<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virus</span> 405<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virus signature</span> 410<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>white-hat hacker (ethical hacker)</span> 414<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>whole-house surge protector</span> 444<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>worm</span> 407<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>zombie</span> 416<br/>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="53" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">making the transition to...next semester//</div>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Backup Procedures</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">You know you should have a good backup strategy in place for your key data. Consider the following:</span></li>
						<ul style="list-style-type:lower-alpha;">
							<li><span class="notStrong">How often do you back up critical data files such as homework files? What type of device do you use for backing up files? Where do you store the backups to ensure they won’t be destroyed if a major disaster (such as a fire) destroys your computer? Do you use online sites for file backups?</span></li>
							<li><span class="notStrong">List the applications (such as Microsoft Office) that are currently installed on your computer. Where is the media (DVDs) for your application software stored? For any software you purchased in an Internet download, have you burned a copy of the installation files to DVD/Blu-ray disc in case you need to reinstall the software? Why are these SFF computers appearing? What role do you see these systems fulfilling? What kind of performance and hardware would you recommend for such a system?</span></li>
							<li><span class="notStrong">Have you ever made an image backup of your entire system? If so, what software do you use for image backups? If not, research image backup software on the Internet and find an appropriate package to use. Suppose you need to purchase an additional backup device to hold your image backup. Find one that is appropriate. What is the total cost of the software and hardware you will need to implement your image backup strategy?</span></li>
						</ul>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol>
						<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Protecting Your Computer for Free</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">There are many effective, free options for protecting your computer from malware.</span></li>
						<ul style="list-style-type:lower-alpha;">
							<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Research free anti-malware programs using sources such as <em>PC Magazine</em> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://pcmag.com','_blank')">pcmag.com</span>) and <em>PC World</em> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://pcworld.com','_blank')">pcworld.com</span>). What are the highest-rated free software packages available? Are versions available for your OS? Do you have any of these tools installed on your computer already?</span></li>
							<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Many ISPs offer proprietary security software, including major brands such as Norton, free to their subscribers. Research the ISP you use or a local ISP and determine what free software it provides. When selecting an ISP, how important is it to you that it offers free security software?</span></li>
						</ul>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Botnet Awareness</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Botnets are serious computer infestations that affect large numbers of computers at one time. Still, many students are unaware of this threat even as botnets strike college campuses. Research botnets and prepare a short flyer for your classmates that explains the threats posed by botnets and the software that can be used to detect botnets.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="54" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">making the transition to...the workplace//</div>
					
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Tracking Employees</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Many corporations provide mobile devices to their employees who work outside the office. With apps such as Footprints (from Sollico Software) and GPS tracking (from LOCiMOBILE), it’s easy for employers to track the whereabouts of their employees by tracking the location of their mobile devices. Consider the following:</span></li>
						<ul style="list-style-type:lower-alpha;">
							<li><span class="notStrong">How would you feel about your boss tracking your movements during the day? Should employers have to disclose to employees that they’re being tracked? Should employers have the right to track employees to ensure they’re not slacking off during work hours?</span></li>
							<li><span class="notStrong">Should the tracking software have an option to allow employees to disable the tracking feature temporarily? Under what circumstances should it be permissible for an employee to turn off employer tracking?</span></li>
						</ul>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Computer Security Careers</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Computer security professionals are among the highest-paid employees. Using employment sites such as <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Monster.com','_blank')">Monster.com</span>, <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://computerjobs.com','_blank')">computerjobs.com</span>, and <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://dice.com','_blank')">dice.com</span>, research computer security jobs available in the state where your school is located (try searching “computer security”). Select three entry-level computer security jobs from different employers and prepare a document comparing the following: What are the educational requirements? What job skills are required? How much prior work experience are firms looking for? Are programming skills required?</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="55" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">team time//</div>
					
					<h3>Protecting Senior Citizens from Sharing Too Much Data</h3>
				<br/>	
					<h4>Problem</h4>
					<p>With the proliferation of e-commerce, electronic data capture, and electronic communication such as e-mail, individuals provide numerous companies with sensitive personal data. However, this only encourages hackers to attempt to breach computer systems in order to steal sensitive information or to use social engineering techniques to fool the unwary. Senior citizens are one group often targeted by social engineering attacks because they’re perceived to be less computer literate and more easily duped by social engineering tactics.</p>
					
					<h4>Task</h4>
					<p>The residents of a local retirement community, managed by your neighbor, have recently been the victims of e-mail phishing and phone pretexting attacks. In addition, recent examinations of residents’ computers by a computer consultant determined that many computers were infected with spyware. Your neighbor has asked you to assist in educating the retirees about the dangers of disclosing too much information or revealing information to unauthorized parties.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
					<h4>Process</h4>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Break the class into three teams. Each team will be responsible for investigating one of the following issues:</span></li>
						<ul style="list-style-type:lower-alpha;">
							<li>Phishing:<span class="notStrong"> Research popular phishing scams and find examples of phishing e-mails sent to the unwary.</span></li>
							<li>Data breaches:<span class="notStrong"> Research popular e-commerce sites or customer loyalty programs that senior citizens might use. Determine what types of data they collect and which pieces of data are not really needed to participate.</span></li>
							<li>Spyware and scareware:<span class="notStrong"> Research typical examples of these types of malware and free solutions that can be used to protect computers from these threats.</span></li>
						</ul>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Present your findings to the class and discuss methodologies for protecting individuals from cybercrime. Provide your instructor with a report of your findings and suggestions suitable for eventual presentation to the residents of the retirement community.</span></li>
					</ol>
					<h4>Conclusion</h4>
					<p>With the proliferation of electronic data, attempts by cybercrimals to collect sensitive information are inevitable. The best defense is educating individuals about the common types of scams and attacks and clearly explaining steps they can take to prevent themselves from falling prey to nefarious schemes.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="56" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">ethics project//</div>
					
					<h3>Content Control: Censorship to Protect Children</h3>
					<p class="moreSpacing">In this exercise, you’ll research and then role-play a complicated ethical situation. The role you play might or might not match your own personal beliefs; in either case, your research and use of logic will enable you to represent the view assigned. An arbitrator will watch and comment on both sides of the arguments, and together, the team will agree on an ethical solution.</p>
					
					<h4>Problem</h4>
					<p class="moreSpacing">Many parents use web-filtering software (also known as content-control software) to protect their children from objectionable content on the Internet. However, the software is also widely used in libraries, schools, and other public places where people other than parents are making decisions about what information to restrict. In 2000, the U.S. federal government began requiring libraries to use content-control software as a condition to receiving federal funds under the provisions of the Children’s Internet Protection Act (CIPA). Libraries that don’t receive federal funds don’t have to install filtering software unless their state (like Virginia) passes laws requiring them to do so to receive state funding. Upon installation of the software, it’s up to the library administrators to decide what content is restricted, as guided by the provisions of laws such as CIPA. Therefore, content restriction can vary widely from library to library.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h4>Research Areas to Consider</h4>
					<span class="psudoUlLi">U.S. Supreme Court case <em>United States v. American Library Association &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(2003)</em></span>
					<span class="psudoUlLi">Content-control software and First Amendment rights</span>
					<span class="psudoUlLi">Violation of children’s free speech rights</span>
					<span class="psudoUlLi">Children’s Internet Protection Act (CIPA)</span>
					
					<h4>Process</h4>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Divide the class into teams.</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Research the areas cited above and devise a scenario in which someone has complained about objectionable content not being blocked or about innocuous content that was inappropriately blocked.</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Team members should write a summary that provides background information for their character—for example: library patron, library administrator, or arbitrator—and that details their character’s behaviors to set the stage for the role-playing event. Then, team members should create an outline to use during the role-playing event.</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Team members should arrange a mutually convenient time to meet for the exchange, using either the collaboration feature of <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or the discussion board feature of your course management software or by meeting in person.</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Team members should present their case to the class or submit a PowerPoint presentation for review by the rest of the class, along with the summary and resolution they developed.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="57" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">ethics project//</div>
					<h4>Conclusion</h4>
					<p class="moreSpacing">As technology becomes ever more prevalent and integrated into our lives, more and more ethical dilemmas will present themselves. Being able to understand and evaluate both sides of the argument, while responding in a personally or socially ethical manner, will be an important skill.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<!--chapter 9B-->
		
		<page index="58" type="full" distinction="chapterStartB">
			<section>
				<!--new image title set up.-->
				<![CDATA[
				<section>
				
				<div class="chapterStartBox">
					<div class="chapterStartDesc" style="padding-top: 32px;">
						Careers in IT</div>	
						<div class="chapterStartNumberFocus">Technology <br/>in Focus</div>
				</div>
				<div class="loader"></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
	
		<page index="59" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="tocB">
			<section>	
				<![CDATA[
					
					<h2 class="semibold">Technology in Focus: <br/>Careers in IT</h2>
					<hr>
					
					<div class="BMargin15">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,60)">Rewards of Working in Information Technology </span>
					<span>The Altair  (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,60)">pp. 460-464</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin15">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,64)" style="display:inline;">Challenges of IT Careers </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,64)">pp. 464-465</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin15">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,65)" style="display:inline;">Choosing Your Realm of IT </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,65)">pp. 465-470</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin15">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,70)" style="display:inline;">Preparing for a Job in IT </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,70)">p. 470</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin15">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,71)" style="display:inline;">Getting Started in an IT Career </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,71)">pp. 471-472</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<img src="assets/images/figures/9B.jpg">
					
					<div class="loader"></div>
					
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="60" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				
				<div class="BMargin10 strong font_23 font_fff">

					<div class="floatRight height100"
						 style="padding:12px 17px; 
								width:208px;
								background-color:#009ecb; margin-right:11px;">
						Careers<br/>in IT</div>
					<div class="height100"
						 style="padding:12px 21px; 
						 		width:122px;
								background-color:#8dc63f;">Technology in Focus</div></div>
								
					<p>It’s hard to imagine an occupation in which computers aren’t used in some fashion. Even such previously low-tech industries as waste disposal and fast food use computers to manage inventories and order commodities. In this Technology in Focus feature, we explore various information technology (IT) career paths open to you.</p>
					<br/>			
					<div style="height:285px;
							background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/goldPot.jpg) 0px 0"></div>
							<div class="font_9 floatLeft"
								 style="margin-top:-7px;font-style: italic;">(Carol and Mike Werner/Alamy)
								 </div>			
				
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Rewards of Working in Information Technology</span>
					<p>There are many great reasons to work in the exciting, ever-changing field of IT. In this section, we’ll explore some reasons why IT fields are so attractive to graduates looking for entry-level positions.</p>
				
				<br/>	
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">IT Workers Are in Demand </h2>
					<p>If you’re investigating a career with computers, the first question you may have is, “Will I be able to get a job?” Consider the following:</p>
				
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">According to projections by the U.S. Department of Labor’s Bureau of Labor Statistics, computer-related jobs are expected to be among the fastest-growing occupations through 2020 (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(61,0)">see Figure 1</span>).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">In 2012, <em>US News and World Report</em> published a list of the best careers to consider based on growth prospects. Software developers ranked second, and 5 of the top 25 were IT careers.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">According to the National Association of Colleges and Employers (NACE) 2012 Starting Salaries for New College Graduates Survey, the average starting salary for computer science jobs increased by 4.1% in 2011.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">The number of students pursuing computer science degrees also has been increasing over the past several years, with slightly over 8,000 computer science degrees awarded in the United States in 2011. Yet, shortages of computing professionals in the United States are still projected over the next 5 to 10 years. What does all this mean? In terms of job outlook, now is a perfect time to consider an IT career.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="61" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">IT Jobs Pay Well</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">As you can see from <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(61,0)">Figure 1</span>, median salaries in IT careers are robust. But what exactly affects your salary in an IT position? Your skill set and your experience level are obvious answers, but the size of an employer and its geographic location are also factors. Large companies tend to pay more, so if you’re pursuing a high salary, set your sights on a large corporation. But remember that making a lot of money isn’t everything—be sure to consider other quality-of-life issues such as job satisfaction. Of course, choosing a computer career isn’t a guarantee you’ll get a high-paying job. Just as in any other profession, you’ll need appropriate training and on-the-job experience to earn a high salary.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">So how much can you expect to start out earning? Although starting salaries for some IT positions (computer desktop support and helpdesk analysts) are in the modest range ($41,000 to $45,000), starting salaries for students with bachelor’s degrees in IT are fairly robust. But IT salaries vary widely, depending on experience level, the geographic location of the job, and the size of the employer.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">To obtain the most accurate information, you should research salaries yourself in the geographic area where you expect to work. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Salary.com','_blank')">Salary.com</span> provides a free salary wizard to help you determine what IT professionals in your area are making compared with national averages. You can add information such as your degree and the size of the company to your search selection to fine-tune the figures further.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">High-Growth IT Jobs*</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(61,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_1.jpg) no-repeat scroll 8px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 230px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 1</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">*Excerpted from Occupational Outlook Handbook, 2012 Edition, Bureau of Labor Statistics
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(62,0)">Figure 2</span> shows that for an entry-level programming position in Chicago, you could expect to earn a salary of between $47,098 and $75,966 at a company of 500 to 1,000 employees. Hundreds of IT job titles are listed in Salary.com, so you can tailor your search to the specific job in which you’re interested.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">IT Jobs Are Not Going “Offshore”</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">In the global economy in which we now operate, job outlook includes the risk of jobs being outsourced, possibly to other countries. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Outsourcing</span> is a process whereby a business hires a third-party firm to provide business</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="62" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(62,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_2.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0px;
							    height: 145px;">
						<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:87px;"><span>Figure 2</span> <br/>The salary wizard at <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://Salary.com','_blank')">Salary.com</span> is easy to tailor to your location.
   					</figcaption></figure>
					
					<p>services (such as customer-support call centers) that were previously handled by in-house employees. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Offshoring</span> occurs when the outsourcing firm is located (or uses employees) outside the United States.</p>
					<p class="start">India, China, Romania, and other former Eastern Bloc countries are major players in providing outsourcing services for U.S. companies. The big lure of outsourcing and offshoring is cost savings: Considering that the standard of living and salaries are much lower in many countries than they are in the United States, offshoring is an attractive option for many U.S. employers.</p>
					<p class="start">However, outsourcing and offshoring don’t always deliver the cost savings that CEOs envision. Demand for personnel overseas has led to increased costs (primarily due to wage increases) for service providers in foreign markets. Furthermore, other, less tangible factors can outweigh the cost savings from outsourcing. Communications problems can arise between internal and external employees, for example, and cultural differences between the home country and the country doing the offshoring can result in software code that needs extensive rework</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>by in-house employees. Data also can be less secure in an external  environment or during the transfer between the company and an external vendor. Although outsourcing and offshoring won’t be going away, companies are approaching these staffing alternatives with more caution and are looking more to U.S. companies to provide resources.</p>
					<p class="start">So, many IT jobs are staying in the United States. According to <em>InformationWeek</em> magazine, most jobs in the following three categories (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(62,1)">see Figure 3</span>) will stay put:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Customer interaction</span><span class="innerLi notStrong">:  Jobs that require direct input from customers or that involve systems with whichcustomers interface daily</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Enablers</span><span class="innerLi notStrong">:  Jobs that involve getting key business projects accomplished, often requiring technical skills beyond the realm of IT, and good people skills</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Infrastructure jobs</span><span class="innerLi notStrong">:  Jobs that are fundamental to moving and storing the information that U.S.–based employees need to do their jobs.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Jobs That Will Likely Remain Onshore</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(62,1)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_3.jpg) no-repeat scroll 25px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 154px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 3</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="63" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">In addition, jobs that require specific knowledge of the U.S. marketplace and culture, such as social media managers, are also very likely not to be offshored.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Women Are in High Demand in IT Departments</h2>
					<p>Currently, women make up about 25% of the IT workforce (per the National Center for Women and Information Technology). This presents a huge opportunity for women who have IT skills, because many IT departments are actively seeking to diversify their workforces. In addition, although a salary gender gap (the difference between what men and women earn for performing the same job) exists in IT careers, it’s smaller than in most other professions.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">You Have a Choice of Working Location</h2>
					<p>In this case, location refers to the setting in which you work. IT jobs can be office-based, field-based, project-based, or home-based. Because not every situation is perfect for every individual, you can look for a job that suits your tastes and requirements. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(63,0)">Figure 4</span> summarizes the major job types and their locations.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">You Constantly Meet New Challenges</h2>
					<p>In IT, the playing field is always changing. New software and hardware are constantly being developed. You’ll need to work hard to keep your skills up to date. You’ll spend a lot of time in training and self-study trying to learn new systems and techniques. Many individuals thrive in this type of environment because it keeps their jobs from becoming dull or routine.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Where Do You Want to Work?</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(63,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_4.jpg) no-repeat scroll 10px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 325px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 4</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">(Mardis Coers/Fotolia; Harvepino/Fotolia; Nestor Costa/Fotolia; Paul Maguire/Fotolia)
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading TMargin10 font_16">You Work in Teams</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">When students are asked to describe their ideal jobs, many describe jobs that involve working in teams. Despite what some people think, IT professionals are not locked in lightless cubicles, basking in the glow of</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="64" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">their monitors and working alone on projects. Most IT jobs require constant interaction with other workers, usually in team settings. People skills are highly prized by IT departments. If you have good leadership and team-building skills, you’ll have the opportunity to exercise them in an IT job.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">You Don’t Need to Be a Mathematical Genius</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">Certain IT careers such as programming involve a fair bit of math. But even if you’re not mathematically inclined, you can explore many other IT careers. IT employers also value such attributes as creativity, marketing, and artistic style, especially in jobs that involve working on the Internet or with social media.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">IT Skills Are Portable</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing">Most computing skills are portable from industry to industry. A networking job in the clothing manufacturing industry uses the same primary skill set as a networking job for a supermarket chain. Therefore, if something disastrous happens to the industry you’re in, you should be able to switch to another industry without having to learn an entirely new skill set. Combining business courses with IT courses will also make you more marketable when changing jobs. For example, as an accounting major, if you minor in IT, employers may be more willing to hire you because working in accounting today means constantly interfacing with management information systems and manipulating data.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Challenges of IT Careers</span>
					<p>Although there are many positive aspects of IT careers, there can be some challenges. The discussions that follow aren’t meant to discourage you from pursuing an IT career, but merely to make you aware of exactly what challenges you might face in an IT department.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Stress</h2>
					<p>Most IT jobs are hectic (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(64,0)">see Figure 5</span>). Whereas the average American works 42 hours a week, a survey by <em>InformationWeek</em> revealed that the average IT staff person works 45 hours a week and is on call for another 24 hours. On-call time (hours an employee must be available to work in the event of a problem) has been increasing because most IT systems require 24/7 availability.</p>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(64,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_5.jpg) no-repeat 0px 10px;
							    height: 260px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 5</span> Stress comes from multiple directions in IT jobs. <br/><em>(Jenn Mackenzie/Shutterstock; Photobank.ch/Shutterstock; Stephen Coburn/Shutterstock; Wavebreakmedia ltd/Shutterstock; LWPhotography/Shutterstock)</em>
   					</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="65" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Women Are in the Minority</h2>
					<p>A majority of IT jobs are filled by men, so some women view IT departments as <em>Dilbert</em>-like microcosms of antisocial geeks and don’t feel like they would fit in. Unfortunately, some mostly male IT departments do suffer from varying degrees of gender bias. Although some women may thrive on the challenge of enlightening these male enclaves and bringing them into the twenty-first century, others might find it difficult to work in such environments.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Lifelong Learning Is Required</h2>
					<p>Although the constantly changing nature of IT can alleviate boredom, keeping up with the changes can also cause some stress. You’ll need to take training courses, do self-study, and perhaps take additional college courses, such as getting a graduate degree, to keep up with the vast shifts of technology.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Choosing Your Realm of IT</span>
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(65,0)">Figure 6</span> shows an organizational chart for a modern IT department at a large corporation that should help you understand the variety of careers available and how they interrelate. The chief information officer (CIO) has overall responsibility for the development, implementation, and maintenance of information systems and its infrastructure. Usually, the CIO reports to the chief operating officer (COO).</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">The responsibilities below the CIO are generally grouped into two units:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Development and integration (responsible for the development of systems and websites)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Technical services (responsible for the day-to-day operations of the company’s information infrastructure and network, including all hardware and software deployed)</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start BMargin10">In large organizations, responsibilities are distinct and jobs are defined more narrowly. In medium-sized organizations, there can be overlap between position responsibilities. At a small company, you might be the network administrator, database administrator, computer support technician, and social media manager all at the same time. Let’s look at the typical jobs found in each department.</p>
					
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Typical  IT Department Structure</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(65,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_6.jpg) no-repeat scroll 8px 40px #FFFFFF; height: 170px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 6</strong> Click to reveal the interactive graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="66" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(66,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Matching a Career to Your Skills
					</div>	
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Working in Development and Integration</h2>
					<p>Two distinct paths exist in this division:</p>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Web development</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Systems development</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start">Because everything involves the web today, there’s often a great deal of overlap between these paths.</p>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Web Development.</strong> When most people think of web development careers, they usually equate them with being a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>webmaster</span>. Webmasters used to be individuals who were solely responsible for all aspects of a company’s website. However, today’s webmasters usually are supervisors with responsibility for certain aspects of web development. At smaller companies, they may also be responsible for tasks that other individuals in a web development group usually do, such as the following:</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Web content creators</span> generate the words and images that appear on the web. Journalists, other writers, editors, and marketing personnel prepare an enormous amount of web content, whereas <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>video producers</span>, <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>graphic designers</span>, and <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>animators</span> create web-based multimedia. Web content creators have a thorough understanding of their own fields as well as HTML, PHP, and JavaScript.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Interface designers</span> work with graphic designers and animators to create a look and feel for the site and make it easy to navigate.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Web programmers</span> build web pages to deploy the materials that the content creators develop. They wield software tools such as Adobe Dreamweaver and Microsoft Expression to develop the web pages. They also create links to databases using products such as Oracle and SQL Server to keep information flowing between users and web pages. They must possess a solid understanding of client- and server-side web languages (HTML, XML, Java, JavaScript, ASP, PHP, Silverlight, and Perl) and of development environments such as the Microsoft.NET Framework.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Customer interaction technicians</span> provide feedback to a website’s customers. Major job responsibilities include answering e-mail, sending requested information, funneling questions to appropriate personnel (technical support, sales, and so on), and providing suggestions to web programmers for site improvements. Extensive customer service training is essential to work effectively in this area.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Social media directors</span> are responsible for directing the strategy of the company on all social media sites where the company maintains a presence. Often, supervising customer interaction technicians, social media directors make sure that customers have a quality experience while interacting with company employees and customers on sites such as Facebook, Twitter, and Yelp. Responding to comments left on such sites,</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="67" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>developing promotional strategies, and designing functionality of the company’s social media sites are common job responsibilities.</p>
					<p class="start">As you can see in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(67,0)">Figure 7</span>, many different people can work on the same website. Web programming jobs often require a four-year college degree in computer science, whereas graphic designers often are hired with two-year art degrees.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<p><strong>Systems Development.</strong> Ask most people what systems developers do and they’ll answer, “Programming.” However, programming is only one aspect of systems development. Because large projects involve many people, there are many job opportunities in systems development, most of which require four-year college degrees in computer science or management information systems:</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Systems analysts</span> gather information from end users about problems and existing information systems. They document systems and propose solutions to problems. Having good people skills is essential to success as a systems analyst. In addition, systems analysts work with programmers during the development phase to design appropriate programs to solve the problem at hand. Therefore, many organizations insist on hiring systems analysts who have solid business backgrounds and programming experience (at least at a basic level).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Programmers</span> attend meetings to document user needs, and they work closely with systems analysts during the design phase of program development. Programmers need excellent written communication </span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="noListStyle">
						<li><span class="innerLi">skills because they often generate detailed systems documentation for end-user training purposes. Because programming languages are mathematically based, it is essential for programmers to have strong math skills and an ability to think logically.</span></li>
					</ul>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Project managers</span> manage the overall systems development process: assigning staff, budgeting, reporting to management, coaching team members, and ensuring deadlines are met. Project  managers need excellent time management skills because they’re often pulled in several directions at once. They usually have prior experience as programmers or systems analysts. Many project managers obtain master’s degrees to supplement their undergraduate degrees.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">In addition to these key players, the following people are also involved in the systems development process:</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(67,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_7.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0px;
							    height: 220px;">
						<figcaption class="rightPos" style="width:125px;"><span>Figure 7</span><br/>It takes a team to create and maintain a website.<br/><em>(Studio 101/Alamy)</em>
   					</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="68" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Technical writers</span> generate systems documentation for end users and for programmers who may make modifications to the system in the future.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Network administrators</span> help the programmers and analysts design compatible systems, because many systems are required to run in certain environments (UNIX or Windows, for instance) and must work in conjunction with other programs.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Database developers</span> design and build databases to support the software systems being developed.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start BMargin10">Large development projects may have all of these team members on the project. Smaller projects may require an overlap of positions, such as a programmer also acting as a systems analyst. As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(68,0)">Figure 8</span>, team members work together to build a system.</p>
					
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Team Members in Systems Development</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(68,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_8.jpg) no-repeat scroll 90px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 210px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 8</strong> Click to reveal the interactive graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10"><span>Figure 8</span>There are many important team members in systems development. <em>(Bah69/Fotolia; Rob/Fotolia; FotoLuminate/Fotolia; HaywireMedia/Fotolia)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading font_16">Working in Technical Services</h2>
					<p>Technical services jobs are vital to keeping IT systems running. The people in these jobs install and maintain the infrastructure behind the IT systems and work with end users to make sure they can interact with the systems effectively. There are two major categories of technical services careers:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Information systems</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Support services</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start">Note that these also are the <em>least likely</em> IT jobs to be outsourced because hands-on work with equipment and users is required on a regular basis.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<p><strong>Information Systems</strong>. The information systems department keeps the networks and telecommunications up and running at all times. Within the department, you’ll find a variety of positions.</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Network administrators</span> (sometimes called <em>network engineers</em>) are involved in every stage of network planning and deployment (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(69,0)">see Figure 9</span>). They decide what equipment to buy and what media to use, they determine the network’s topology, and they help install the network (by supervising contractors or doing it themselves). Network administrators plan disaster-recovery strategies (such as what to do if a fire destroys the server room). When equipment and cables break, network administrators must fix the problem. They also obtain and install updates to network software and evaluate new equipment to determine whether the network </span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="69" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="noListStyle BMargin10">
						<li><span class="innerLi">should be upgraded. In addition, they monitor the network’s performance and often develop policies regarding network usage, security measures, and hardware and software standards.</span></li>
					</ul>	
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(69,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_9.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0px;
							    height: 465px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 9</span> At smaller companies, network administrators may be fixing a user’s computer in the morning, installing and configuring a new network operating system in the afternoon, and troubleshooting a wiring problem (shown here) in the evening. <br/><em>(ArtPix/Alamy)</em>
   					</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(69,1)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Get in the Game: Careers in Game Development
					</div>	
					
					<br/>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Database administrators (DBAs)</span> install and configure database servers and ensure that the servers provide an adequate level of access to all users.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Web server administrators</span> install, configure, and maintain web servers and ensure that the company maintains Internet connectivity at all times.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Telecommunications technicians</span> oversee the communications infrastructure, including training employees to use telecommunications equipment. They are often on call 24 hours a day.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Support Services.</strong> As a member of the support services team, you interface with users (external customers or employees) and troubleshoot their computer problems. Support service positions include the following:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Helpdesk analysts</span> staff the phones, respond to Internet live chats, or respond to e-mails and solve problems for customers or employees, either remotely or in person. Often, helpdesk personnel are called on to train users on the latest software and hardware.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Computer support technicians</span> go to a user’s location and fix software and hardware problems. They also often have to chase down and repair faults in the network infrastructure.</span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="70" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">As important as these people are, they may receive a great deal of abuse by angry users whose computers are not working. When working in support services, you need to be patient and not be overly sensitive to insults!</p>
					<p class="start">Technical services jobs often require a two-year college degree or training at a trade school or technical institute. At smaller companies, job duties tend to overlap between the helpdesk and technician jobs. These jobs are in demand and require staffing in local markets, so they are staying onshore. You can’t repair a computer’s power supply if you are located in another country!</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Preparing for a Job in IT</span>
					<p>A job in IT requires a robust skill set and formal training and preparation. Most employers today have an entry level requirement of a college degree, a technical institute diploma, appropriate professional certifications, experience in the field, or a combination of these. How can you prepare for a job in IT?</p>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Get educated.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Two- and four-year colleges and universities normally offer three degrees to prepare students for IT careers: computer science, management information systems, and information technology (although titles vary). Alternatives to colleges and universities are privately licensed technical (or trade) schools. Generally, these programs focus on building skill sets rapidly and qualifying for a job in a specific field. The main advantage of technical schools is that their programs</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="noListStyle">
						<li><span class="innerLi">usually take less time to complete than college degrees. However, to have a realistic chance of employment in IT fields other than networking or web development, you should attend a degree-granting college or university.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Investigate professional certifications.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong moreSpacing"> Certifications attempt to provide a consistent method of measuring skill levels in specific areas of IT. Hundreds of IT certifications are available, most of which you get by passing a written exam. Software and hardware vendors (such as Microsoft and Cisco) and professional organizations (such as the Computing Technology Industry Association) often establish certification standards. Visit <span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://microsoft.com','_blank')">microsoft.com</span>, <span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://cisco.com','_blank')">cisco.com</span>, <span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://comptia.org','_blank')">comptia.org</span>, and <span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://sun.com','_blank')">sun.com</span> for more information on certifications.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Get experience.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong moreSpacing"> In addition to education, employers want you to have experience, even for entry-level jobs. While you’re still completing your education, consider getting an internship or part-time job in your field of study. Many schools will help you find internships and allow you to earn credit toward your degree through internships.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Do research.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong moreSpacing"> Find out as much as you can about the company and the industry it’s in before going on an interview. Start with the company’s website, and then expand your search to business and trade publications such as <em>Business Week</em> and <em>Inc.</em> magazines.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="71" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Getting Started in an IT Career</span>
					<p>Training for a career is not useful unless you can find a job at the end of your training. Here are some tips on getting a job:</p>
					
					<ol class="strong noBMargin">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Use the career resources at your school.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Many employers recruit at schools, and most schools maintain a placement office to help students find jobs. Employees in the placement office can help you with résumé preparation and interviewing skills and can provide you with leads for internships and jobs.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Develop relationships with your instructors.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Many college instructors still work in or previously worked in the IT industry. They can often provide you with valuable advice and industry contacts.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Start networking.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Many jobs are never advertised but instead are filled by word of mouth. Seek out contacts in your field and discuss job prospects with them. Find out what skills you need, and ask them to recommend others in the industry with whom you can speak. Professional organizations such as the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) offer one way to network. These organizations often have chapters on college campuses and offer reduced membership rates for students. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(71,1)">Figure 11</span> lists major professional organizations you should consider investigating.</span></li>
					</ol>
					<ol class="noListStyle">
						<li class="start"><span class="innerLi">If you’re a woman and are thinking about pursuing an IT career, many resources and groups cater to female IT professionals and students (<span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(71,2)">see Figure 12</span>).</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(71,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Certifications: How Important Are They?
					</div>	
					
				<br/>	
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Professional Organizations</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(71,1)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_11.jpg) no-repeat scroll 63px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 180px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 11</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
				<br/>	
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Resources for Women in IT</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(71,2)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_12.jpg) no-repeat scroll 61px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 180px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 12</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="72" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="noListStyle noBMargin">
						<li><span class="innerLi">The oldest and best-known organization is the Association for Women in Computing, founded in 1978.</span></li>
					</ol>
					<ol class="strong noBMargin">
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li class="liHide"></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Check corporate websites for jobs.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Many corporate websites list current job opportunities. For example, Google provides searchable job listings by geographic  location. Check the sites of companies in which you are interested and then do a search on the sites for job openings or, if provided, click their employment links.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Visit online employment sites.</span><span class="innerLi notStrong"> Most of these sites allow you to store your résumé online, and many sites allow employers to browse résumés to find qualified employees. Begin looking at job postings on these sites early in your education, because these job postings detail the skill sets employers require. Focusing on coursework that will provide you with desirable skill sets will make you more marketable. <span class="innerLi strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(72,0)">Figure 13</span> lists employment sites as well as sites that offer other career resources.</span></li>
					</ol>
					<ol class="noListStyle">
						<li class="start"><span class="innerLi">The outlook for IT jobs should continue to be positive in the future. We wish you luck with your education and job search.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight font_21 cond">Resources for IT Employment</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(72,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig9b_13.jpg) no-repeat scroll 8px 43px #FFFFFF; height: 325px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 13</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos font_9 BMargin5 Lmargin10">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
						<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to the next Chapter:</strong>
							<span class="dot"><span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(34)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
	
		
		<page index="73" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">What working situation would you prefer?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Field-based</li>
						<li>Project-based</li>
						<li>Office-based</li>
						<li>Home-based</li>
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="74" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">Careers in IT glossary//</div>
					
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>animators</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Customer Interaction technicians</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Computer support technicians</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>database administrators (DBAs)</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>database developers</span> 468<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>game designers</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>game programmer</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>graphic designers</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>helpdesk analysts</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>interface designers</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>network administrators</span> 468<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>offshoring</span> 462<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>outsourcing</span> 461<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Play testing</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>project managers</span> 467<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>programmers</span> 467<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>social media directors</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>systems analysts</span> 467<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>technical writers</span> 468<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>telecommunications technicians</span> 469<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>video producers</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>web content creators</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>webmaster</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>web programmers</span> 466<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>web server administrators</span> 469<br/>
					

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				
					<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
					
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent semibold textBlack">
							Don't forget to use the study aids included in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or on the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://wps.prenhall.com/bp_evans_techinaction_10/','_blank')">Companion Website</span>. And don’t forget the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/index.html','_blank')">Replay Videos</span>.
						</div>
						</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>

	</chapter>
</ebook>	