<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ebook book="compTia">
<chapter index="5" title="" glossary="43" secondGlossary="76">

<page index="0" type="full" distinction="chapterStart">
			<section>
				<!--new image title set up.-->
				<![CDATA[
				<section>
				
				<div class="chapterStartBox">
					<div class="chapterStartDesc topPadding10">
						System Software:<br/>
						The Operating System,<br/>
						Utility Programs, and<br/>
						File Management</div>	
				<div class="chapterStartNumber">5</div>
				</div>
				<div class="loader"></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
	<page index="1" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="toc">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[

					<span class="largeGreenHeading"  onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">Understanding System Software</span>
					<img src="assets/images/pics/Operating.jpg" style="margin-top:-27px;margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading"  onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">Operating System Fundamentals</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objectives</span>
					<ul>
						<li class="shiftRight55"><span class="ul1DigNumber">1.</span> What software is included in system software? <br/><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">(p. 174)</span></li>
						<li style="width:350px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">2.</span> What are the different kinds of operating systems? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,3)">(pp. 174-177)</span></li>
						<li style="width:350px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">3.</span> What are the most common operating systems? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,6)">(pp. 177-180)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/customizing_windows/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Customizing Windows
					</div>
					
					<hr class="clearRight" style="margin-top:2px;">
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/orgastra.jpg" style="margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading"  onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,10)">What the Operating System Does</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objectives</span>
					<ul>
						<li class="shiftRight55"><span class="ul1DigNumber">4.</span> How does the operating system provide a means for users to interact with the  computer? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,10)">(p. 181)</span></li>
						<li class="shiftRight55"><span class="ul1DigNumber">5.</span> How does the operating system help manage resources such as the processor, memory, storage, hardware, and peripheral devices? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,11)">(pp. 182–185)</span></li>
						<li style="margin-right:-90px;"><span class="ul1DigNumber">6.</span> How does the operating system interact with application software? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,15)">(p. 186)</span></li>
					</ul>
						
					
					<hr class="clearRight" style="margin-top:2px;">
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/boots.jpg" style="margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,16)">The Boot Process: Starting Your Computer</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li class="shiftRight55"><span class="ul1DigNumber">7.</span> How does the operating system help the computer start up? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,16)">(pp. 187–190)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="activeHelpdesk" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_12.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
						<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
						Starting the Computer: The Boot Process
					</div>
					
					<img src="assets/images/layout/playTechTown.png" class="techTown" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techtown','_blank')"/>

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<span class="largeGreenHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,22)">Using System Software</span>
					<img src="assets/images/pics/windows.jpg" style="margin-top:-27px;margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,22)">The Windows Interface</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li><span class="ul1DigNumber lessSpacing">8.</span> What are the main features of the Windows interface? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,22)">(pp. 193–197)</span>
						</li>
					</ul>
					
					
					<hr style="margin-top:0px;margin-bottom:3px;">
					
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/stack.jpg" style="margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,27)">Organizing Your Computer: File Management</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li class="shiftRight55"><span class="ul1DigNumber lessSpacing">9.</span> How does the operating system help me keep my computer organized? <br/><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,27)">(pp. 198-203)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/file_management/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						File Management
					</div>
					
					<div class="activeHelpdesk"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_13.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
						<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
						Organizing Your Computer: File Management
					</div>
					
					<hr style="margin-top:0px;margin-bottom:3px;">
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/workman.jpg" style="margin-right:0px;margin-bottom:8px;"/>
					<span class="orangeHeading noBMargin" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,32)">Utility Programs</span>
					<span class="semiBoldGrey">Objective</span>
					<ul>
						<li><span class="ul1DigNumber lessSpacing">10.</span> What utility programs are included in  system software and what do they do? <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,32)">(pp. 203–209)</span>
						</li>
					</ul>
					
					<div class="activeHelpdesk"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_14.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
						<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
						Using Utility Programs
					</div>
					
					<div class="soundByte"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/file_compression/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						File Compression
					</div>
					
					
					<div class="soundByte floatRight" style="width:180px;"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/letting_your_computer_clean_up_after_itself/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Letting Your Computer Clean Up After Itself
					</div>
					
					<div class="soundByte" 
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/hard_disk_anatomy_interactive/index.html','_blank')">
						<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
						<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
						Hard Disk Anatomy
					</div>
					
					
					
					

					<span class="bottomMediaText">
   						For all media in this chapter go to <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techinaction','_blank')">pearsonhighered.com/techinaction</span> or <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span>.
   					</span>

					<span class="verticalRightCreds" style="margin-right:-46px;margin-bottom:50px;">
							(Mary Anne Poatsy; Ferenc Szelepcsenyi/Shutterstock; Ivancovlad/Shutterstock; StanislavPopov/Shutterstock; reji/Fotolia)
					</span>
					<div class="loader"></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="2" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="whiteOnBlack">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[


					
					<div style="width:110%;height:100%;
							background:no-repeat url(assets/images/figures/GraphWave.jpg) -10px 0"></div></div>
							<div class="font_9 floatLeft"
								 style="margin-top:-7px;font-style: italic;">
								 </div>




				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="thinGreenHeading">How Cool Is This?</span>
					<p class="moreSpacing">Have you ever been expecting a <strong>critical phone call</strong> but been in a situation where you absolutely need to <strong>silence your phone</strong>? iPhone’s iOS 5 lets you create <strong>custom vibration patterns</strong> that you can assign to individual contacts. This lets you <strong>easily identify callers</strong> in a near <strong>stealth mode setting</strong>. To try it out, first make sure custom vibrations are enabled in Settings. Then go to Contacts, choose a contact, and select Edit. Locate the Vibration > Create New Vibration option, and select it. You’ll be presented with a screen on which you can tap out your own vibration rhythm. After saving, just listen for the appropriate “<strong>buzz</strong>” <strong>pattern</strong> you defined and you’ll know who is calling <strong>without drawing attention</strong> to yourself or your phone.</p>
					
					<div class="scanThis"
						 style="background-image: url('assets/images/pics/Chap5ArrSchip_computer.png')" onclick="window.open('http://www.apple.com/iphone/','_blank')">
						Scan here for more info 
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>

		</page>
		
		<page index="3" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingGreenBackDiagDashes">Understanding System Software</div>
					<p class="digCompP">As discussed in the previous chapter, your computer uses two basic types of software: application software and system software. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Application software</span> is the software you use to do everyday tasks at home and at work. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>System software</span> is the set of programs that helps run the computer and coordinates instructions between application software and the computer’s hardware devices. From the moment you turn on your computer to the time you shut it down, you’re interacting with system software.</p>
					<div class="greenHeadingLineDashed"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/OperatingThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">operating system</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:102px;">Fundamentals</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>System software consists of two primary types of programs: the <em>operating system</em> and <em>utility programs</em>. The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>operating system (OS)</span> is a group of programs that controls how your computer functions. The OS:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Manages the computer’s hardware, including the processor, memory, and storage devices, as well as peripheral devices such as the printer;</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Provides a consistent means for application software to work with the central processing unit (CPU); and</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Is responsible for the management, scheduling, and coordination of tasks</span></li>
					</ul>
					<p class="start">You interact with your OS through the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>user interface</span>—the <em>desktop, icons,</em> and <em>menus</em> that let you communicate with your computer.</p>
					<p class="start">A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>utility program</span> is a small program that performs many of the general housekeeping tasks for your computer, such as system maintenance and file compression. A set of utility programs is bundled with each OS, but </p>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>you can also buy standalone utility programs that often provide more features.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Do all computers have operating systems?</strong> Every computer, from the smallest laptop to the largest supercomputer, has an OS. Even cell phones, game consoles, cars, and some appliances have operating systems. The role of the OS is critical;  the computer can’t operate without it.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Are all operating systems alike?</strong> You’re probably familiar with Microsoft Windows, Apple OS X, and perhaps the iPhone’s iOS operating system, but many other operating systems exist. Laptops, tablet computers, and smartphones all need specific operating systems designed to take advantage of their unique characteristics. However, as devices begin to converge in terms of functionality, and operating systems continue to become more powerful, developers such as Microsoft and Apple are making operating  systems that have similar functionality (such as OS X and iOS) or are making single operating systems (such as Windows 8) that can run on multiple devices. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(4,0)">Figure 5.1</span> lists a number of common operating systems.</p>
					<p class="start">When operating systems were originally developed, they were designed for a single user performing one task at a time (that is, they were <em>single-user, single-task operating systems</em>). However, modern operating systems allow a single user to <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>multitask</span>—to perform more than one process at a time. And operating systems such as Windows and OS X provide networking capabilities as well, essentially making them <em>multiuser, multitasking operating systems</em>.</p>
					
					]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="4" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight">Common Operating Systems</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(4,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.1.jpg) no-repeat scroll 15px 35px #FFFFFF; height: 255px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 5.1</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos">
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					
					<p class="start TMargin10">Operating systems can be categorized by the type of device in which they’re installed, such as robots and specialized equipment with built-in computers, mainframes and network computers, mobile devices, and personal computers. Next, we’ll look at these different types of operating systems. </p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Real-Time Operating Systems</h2>
					<p><strong>Why do machines with built-in computers need an OS?</strong> Machinery that performs a repetitive series of specific tasks in an exact amount of  time requires a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>real-time operating system (RTOS)</span>. Also referred to as <em>embedded systems</em>, RTOSs require minimal user interaction. This type of</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>OS is a program with a specific purpose, and it must guarantee certain response times for particular computing tasks; otherwise, the machine is useless. The programs are written specifically for the needs of the devices and their functions. Therefore, there are no commercially available standard RTOS software programs. Devices that must perform regimented tasks or record precise results—such as measurement instruments found in the</p>
				
				<p>scientific, defense, and aerospace industries—require RTOSs. Examples include digital storage oscilloscopes and the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Where else are RTOSs used today?</strong> You also encounter RTOSs every day in devices such as fuel-injection systems in car engines, automobile “infotainment” systems, and some common appliances. RTOSs are also found in many types of robotic equipment. Television stations use robotic cameras with RTOSs that glide across a suspended cable system to record sports events from many angles (<span class="strongDBlue"  onclick="compTia.togglePopup(4,1)">see Figure 5.2</span>).</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Operating Systems for Networks,Servers, and Mainframes</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What kind of operating systems do networks use?</strong> A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="multiuser operating system (network operating system)">multiuser operating system</span> (also known as a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="multiuser operating system (network operating system)">network operating system</span>) lets more than one user access the computer system at a time by handling and prioritizing requests from multiple users. Networks (groups of computers connected to each other so that they can communicate and share resources) need a multiuser OS be cause many users simultaneously access the server (the computer that manages network resources such as printers).</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="5" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(4,1)"
						style="height: 375px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.2.jpg) no-repeat scroll 50px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.2</span> Devices such as TV sky cameras, cars, and medical equipment use RTOSs. <em>(John Pyle/Cal Sport Media/Newscom; The Washington Post/GettyImages; Elfstrom/DavidElfstrom/iStockphoto)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
					
					 <p class="TMargin10 moreSpacing">The latest versions of Windows and OS X can be considered network operating systems: They enable users to set up basic networks in their homes and small businesses.</p>
					
					<p class="start moreSpacing">In larger networks, a more robust network OS is installed on servers and manages all user requests. For example, on a network where users share a printer, the network OS ensures that the printer prints only one </p>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">document at a time in the order the requests were made. Examples of network operating systems include Windows Server, Linux, and UNIX.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What is UNIX?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>UNIX</span> is a multiuser, multitasking OS that is used as a network OS, primarily with mainframes, although it’s also often found on PCs.</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(5,0)" class="readMore"></a>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Operating Systems for Mobile Devices</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What kind of OS does a smartphone use?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue"  onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,0)">Figure 5.3</span> shows the most common operating systems found on smartphones such as the iPhone. Most smartphones have at least modest multitasking capabilities, such as letting you check e-mail while you’re on a phone call. More advanced smartphones  provide greater multitasking, such as letting you talk and use apps at the same time.</p>
					
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What OS do tablets use?</strong> Popular tablet operating systems include iOS, Android, and Windows (<span class="strongDBlue"  onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,1)">see Figure 5.4</span>). iPads use iOS, whereas a number of different tablets (such as the Samsung Galaxy Tab and the Motorola Xoom) use versions of Android. The Kindle Fire also runs a customized version of Android. Until the release of Windows 8 in 2012, Microsoft didn’t have a popular tablet OS, but the company is hoping to reverse this trend with Windows 8, which is optimized for tablet devices.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="6" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13 font_16">Popular Smartphone Operating Systems</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,0)" style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.3.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 40px #FFFFFF; height: 222px; overflow: hidden;">
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 5.3</strong> Click to test your knowledge</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="padding:5px 10px;">
								<span>Figure 5.3</span> Popular Smartphone Operating Systems (Based on U.S. Market Share, February 2012, per comScore)
						</figcaption></figure>
						</div>
					<br/>	
						<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13 font_16">Popular Tablet Operating Systems</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(6,1)" style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.4.jpg) no-repeat scroll 55px 40px #FFFFFF; height: 222px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 5.4</strong> Click to test your knowledge</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="padding:5px 10px;"><span>Figure 5.4</span> Popular Tablet Operating Systems (Based on Market Share, Fourth Quarter 2011, per Strategy Analytics)
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Do gaming consoles and iPods use an OS?</strong> Gaming systems such as Microsoft’s Xbox 360, the Nintendo Wii, and the Sony PlayStation, as well as personal media players such as the iPod all require system software developed specifically for the particular device. The system software controls the physical aspects of the device (such as game controllers) as well as other application programs that come with the device. For example, the operating systems on gaming consoles control web browsing and file storage of media and photos as well as playing of DVDs and games.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Operating Systems for Personal Computers</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are the most popular operating systems for personal computers?</strong>  Microsoft Windows, OS X, and Linux (an open source OS) are the top three operating systems for personal computers. Although they share similar features, each is unique.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What’s special about Windows?</strong> Microsoft <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="windows">Windows</span> is an operating environment that incorporates a user-friendly, visual interface like the one that was first introduced with Apple’s OS. Over time, Improvements in Windows have concentrated on increasing user functionality and friendliness, improving Internet capabilities, supporting home networks, and enhancing file privacy and security. The newest release of Microsoft’s OS, <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8</span>, provides a new interface optimized for touch-screen devices.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What’s the difference between the various editions of Windows 8 operating systems?</strong> Windows 8 simplifies consumer choices </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="7" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>because it’s offered in only two versions:  Windows 8 and Windows 8 Pro. For most users, Windows 8 is sufficient, as it now includes many features (such as remote access) that weren’t included in Windows 7 Home Premium. However, Windows 8 doesn’t include Media Center, which you may be used to seeing in previous versions of Windows. Media Center is now available  only as an add-on package for Windows 8 Pro.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What’s special about the Mac OS?</strong> In 1984, <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Mac OS</span> became the first commercially available OS to incorporate a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="graphical user interface (gui)">graphical user interface</span>, or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="graphical user interface (gui)">GUI</span>, with user-friendly point-and-click technology. Many Mac users have switched from Windows because of the “coolness” of the Mac OS, OS X. The latest version, Mountain Lion, adds many of the popular and innovative features loved by iOS users, such as messages, reminders, notes, and a notification center. If you’ve been using Windows for a while, you shouldn’t have any problems making the transition to OS X. You’ll notice immediately that OS X uses the same desktop metaphors as Windows, including icons for folders and a Trash Can (similar to a Recycle Bin) for deleted documents. OS X also includes a window-based interface like the one in Windows.</p>
					<p class="start">OS X is based on the UNIX operating system, which is exceptionally stable and reliable. However, just as with  any other OS, you still need to install updates as they become available and protect yourself from viruses, spyware, and other malicious software.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What is Linux?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Linux</span> is an open source OS designed for use on personal computers and as a network OS. Open source software is freely available for anyone to use or modify as he or she wishes.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(7,0)" class="readMore BMargin10"></a>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>What computers use Linux?</strong> Linux is gaining popularity among computer manufacturers, which have begun to ship it with some of their latest PCs. Android, the tablet and phone OS, is Linux based. Because the overall size of Android is much smaller than that of Windows, many netbook users choose to use it in place of the factory-installed Windows OS (<span class="strongDBlue"  onclick="compTia.togglePopup(7,1)">see Figure 5.5</span>). Some Linux-based operating systems have been modified to run on iPods and gaming systems.</p>
				<br/>	
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(7,1)"
						style="height: 290px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.5.jpg) no-repeat scroll 10px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.5</span> Developed by Google, the Android OS is based on Linux and runs easily on netbooks and tablets. <em>(Oleksiy Maksymenko Photography/Alamy)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="8" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>Where can I get Linux?</strong> Linux is available for download in various packages known as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="distributions (distros)">distributions</span>, or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="distributions (distros)">distros</span>. Distros include the underlying Linux kernel (the code that provides Linux’s basic functionality) and special modifications to the OS, and may also include additional open source software (such as OpenOffice). A good place to start researching distros is <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://distrowatch.com','_blank')">distrowatch.com</span>. This site tracks Linux distros and provides helpful tips for beginners on choosing one.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Does it matter what OS is on my computer?</strong> An OS is designed to run on specific CPUs. CPUs have different designs, which can require modifying the OS software to allow it to communicate properly with each CPU. The combination of an OS and a specific processor is referred to as a computer’s <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>platform</span>.</p>
					<p class="start">For user convenience, computers and other devices usually come with an OS already installed. However, with some PCs, you can specify which OS you’d like installed when you order your device. For example, Windows and Linux can run on most of the hardware being sold today. Your decision of an OS in this case is mostly a matter of price and personal preference. However, Apple equipment—computers, iPhones, iPads, and iPod Touches—comes with Apple operating systems preinstalled.</p>
					<p class="start">Note that most <em>application software</em> is OS dependent. You need to make sure you get the correct version of the application software for  your OS, such as Microsoft Office 2013 for Windows and Microsoft Office 2011 for OS X.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/customizing_windows/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Customizing Windows
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll find out how to customize your desktop. You’ll learn how to configure the desktop, set up a screen saver, change pointer options, customize the Start screen, and manage user accounts.
					</div></div>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>Can I have more than one OS on my computer?</strong> Many people run more than one OS on their computers because different operating systems offer different features. For example, Windows and Linux both run well on Apple computers. A standard utility included in OS X called Boot Camp lets you boot into either Windows or OS X. And if you want to run both OS X and Windows OS at the same time, you can create “virtual drives” using virtualization software such as Parallels or VMware Fusion.</p>
					<p class="start">In Windows, you can create a separate section of your hard drive (called a <em>partition</em>) and install another OS on it while leaving your original Windows installation untouched. After installing the second OS, when your computer starts, you’re offered a choice of which OS to use.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do operating systems use the“cloud”?</strong> Now that broadband Internet access and providing computer resources via the Internet (so-called <em>cloud computing</em>) are becoming more commonplace, operating systems have features that are tied to cloud computing.</p>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(8,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						Upgrading Your Operating System
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="9" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>Here are a few examples:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Windows 8 features tighter integration with the cloud. Using your <em>Microsoft account</em>, Windows 8 stores your settings and keeps track of applications you’ve purchased from the Windows store online. You can easily access and store files online in your <em>Sky Drive account</em>. You can also log on to any Windows 8 machine and be able to see your familiar desktop and applications.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Similarly, OS X Mountain Lion allows you to sign in with your <em>Apple ID</em>, which provides access to Apple’s <em>iCloud</em> system. iCloud stores your content online and automatically pushes it out to all your Apple devices.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Google has launched the <em>Google Chrome OS</em> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(9,0)">see Figure 5.6</span>), which is a web-based OS. With the Chrome OS, virtually no files are installed on your computing device. Rather, the main functionality of the OS is provided by accessing the web through a web browser. Chrome OS is only available on certain hardware from Google’s manufacturing partners, and these devices are called <em>Chromebooks</em>.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">Another pioneer in accessing cloud-based storage and applications with a browser is the open source product eyeOS (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://eyeos.org','_blank')">eyeos.org</span>). eyeOS allows companies to set up private clouds containing data and applications that can be accessed by their employees, partners, or customers. Using almost any computing device with a browser, users can access their data and applications through an Internet connection.</p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(9,0)"
						style="height: 268px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.6.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.6</span> The Google Chrome OS has a very minimalist look.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
			
			<br/>
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(9,1)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue TMargin5">
						<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
						OS Market Share Battle: It’s Still a Windows World
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="10" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashedEnd"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingBO" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/orgastraThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="dblue">what the operating</div>
						<div class="orange" style="margin-left:150px;">SYSTEM DOES</div>
					</div>
					
					<p class="lessSpacing">As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(10,0)">Figure 5.7</span>, the OS is like an orchestra’s conductor. It coordinates and directs the flow of data and information through the computer system. In this section, we explore the operations of the OS in detail.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">The User Interface</h2>
					<p class="lessSpacing"><strong>How does the OS control how I interact with my computer?</strong> The OS provides a user interface that lets you interact with the computer. The first personal computers used <em>Microsoft Disk Operating System</em> (<em>MS-DOS</em>, or just <em>DOS</em>), which had a command-driven interface, as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(11,0)">Figure 5.8a</span>. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>command-driven interface</span> is one in which you enter commands to communicate with the computer system. The DOS commands were not always easy to understand; as a result, the interface proved to be too complicated for the average user. Therefore, PCs were used primarily in business and by professional computer operators.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing">The command-driven interface was later improved by incorporating a menu-driven interface, as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(11,0)">Figure 5.8b</span>. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>menu-driven interface</span> is one in which you choose commands from menus displayed on the screen. Menu-driven interfaces eliminated the need for users to know every command because they could select most of the commonly used commands from a menu. However, they were still not easy enough for most people to use.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>What kind of interface do operating systems use today? </strong>Current personal computer operating systems such as Microsoft Windows and OS X use a graphical user interface, or GUI (pronounced “gooey”). Unlike command-and menu-driven interfaces, GUIs display graphics and use the point-and-click technology of the mouse and cursor, making them much more user-friendly.</p>
					
					<p class="start">Linux-based operating systems do not have a single default GUI interface. Instead, users are free to choose among many commercially available and free interfaces, such as GNOME and KDE, each of which provides a different look and feel.</p>
				
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes tallerOrangeHead TMargin5 font_18">The OS</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(10,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.7.jpg) no-repeat scroll 143px 34px #FFFFFF; height: 268px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong>Figure 5.7</strong> Click to reveal active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="leftPos TMargin10" style="padding:5px 10px;width:114px;"><span>Figure 5.7</span> The OS is the orchestra conductor of your computer, coordinating its many activities and devices. <em>(Lusoimages/Shutterstock; ra2 studio/Shutterstock;Yuri Arcurs/Shutterstock;aPERFECT <br/>/Shutterstock; Roman Shcherbakov/Shutterstock; Ragnarock/Shutterstock; Arno van Dulmen/Shutterstock)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="11" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(11,0)"
						style="height: 530px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.8.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.8</span> (a) A command driven interface. (b) A menu driven interface.</figcaption>
   			</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Processor Management</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Why does the OS need to manage the processor?</strong> When you use your computer, you’re usually asking the processor (also called the CPU) to perform several tasks at once. For example, you might be printing a Word document, chatting with your friends on Facebook, and watching a movie using the Blu-ray drive—all at the same time, or at least what appears to be at the same time. Although the CPU is powerful, it still needs the OS to arrange the execution of all these activities in a systematic way.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">To do so, the OS assigns a slice of its time to each activity that requires the processor’s attention. The OS must then switch among different processes millions of times a second to make it appear that everything is happening seamlessly. Otherwise, you wouldn’t be able to watch a movie and print at the same time without experiencing delays in the process.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How exactly does the OS coordinate all the activities?</strong> When you create and print a document in Word while also watching a Blu-ray movie, for example, many different devices in the computer are involved, including your keyboard, mouse, Blu-ray drive, and printer. Every keystroke, every mouse click, and each signal to the printer and from the Blu-ray drive creates an action, or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>event</span>, in the respective device (keyboard, mouse, Blu-ray drive, or printer) to which the OS responds.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Sometimes these events occur sequentially (such as when you type characters one at a time), but other events involve two or more devices </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="12" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">working concurrently (such as the printer printing while you type and watch a movie). Although it looks as though all the devices are working at the same time, the OS in fact switches back and forth among processes, controlling the timing of events on which the processor works.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">For example, assume you’re typing and want to print a document. When you tell your computer to print your document, the printer generates a unique signal called an <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>interrupt</span> that tells the OS that it’s in need of immediate attention. Every device has its own type of interrupt, which is associated with an <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>interrupt handler</span>, a special numerical code that prioritizes the requests. These requests are placed in the interrupt table in the computer’s primary memory (RAM). The OS processes the task assigned a higher priority before processing a task assigned a lower priority. This is called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>preemptive multitasking</span>.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">In our example, when the OS receives the interrupt from the printer, it suspends the CPU’s typing activity and Blu-ray activity, and puts a “memo” in a special location in RAM called a <em>stack</em>. The memo is a reminder of what the CPU was doing before it started to work on the printer request. The CPU then retrieves the printer request from the interrupt table and begins to process it. On completion of the printer request, the CPU goes back to the stack, retrieves the memo it placed about the keystroke or Blu-ray activity, and returns to that task until it is interrupted again, in a very quick and seamless fashion, as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(12,0)">Figure 5.9</span>.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight">How Preemptive Multitasking Works</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(12,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.9.jpg) no-repeat scroll 31px 34px #FFFFFF; height: 275px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 5.9</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="padding:5px 10px;"><span></span>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
				<br/>	
				
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>What happens if more than one document is waiting to be printed?</strong> The OS also coordinates multiple activities for peripheral devices such as printers. When the processor receives a request to send information to the printer, it first checks with the OS to ensure that the printer is not already in use. If it is, the OS puts the request in another temporary storage area in RAM, called the <em>buffer</em>. The request then waits in the buffer until the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spooler</span>, a program that helps coordinate all print jobs currently being sent to the printer, indicates the printer is available. If more than one print job is waiting, a line (or <em>queue</em>) is formed so that the printer can process the requests in order.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="13" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Memory and Storage Management</h2>
					<p><strong>Why does the OS have to manage the computer’s memory?</strong> As the OS coordinates the activities of the processor, it uses RAM as a temporary storage area for instructions and data the processor needs. The processor then accesses these instructions and data from RAM when it’s ready to process them. The OS is therefore responsible for coordinating the space allocations in RAM to ensure there’s enough space for all the pending instructions and data. The OS then clears the items from RAM when the processor no longer needs them.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Can my OS ever run out of RAM?</strong> RAM has limited capacity. Like most users, you’ll add new software and peripherals to your computer over time. Most computers sold for home use have between 4 and 16 GB of RAM. If you have an older computer system with less RAM, it might be time to consider buying a new computer or adding more RAM. As you add and upgrade software and increase your usage of the computer system, you might find that the amount of RAM you have is no longer sufficient for your needs.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What happens if my computer runs out of RAM?</strong> When there isn’t enough RAM for the OS to store the required data and instructions, the OS borrows from the more spacious hard drive. This process of optimizing RAM storage by borrowing hard drive space is called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virtual memory</span>. As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(13,0)">Figure 5.10</span>, when more RAM is needed, the OS swaps out from RAM the data or instructions that haven’t recently been used and moves them to a temporary storage area on the hard drive called the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="swap file (page file)">swap file (or page </span></p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p><span class="strongDBlue" glossary="swap file (page file)">file)</span>. If the data or instructions in the swapfile are needed later, the OS swaps them back into active RAM and  replaces them in the hard drive’s swap file with less active data or instructions. This process of swapping is known as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>paging</span>.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Can I ever run out of virtual memory?</strong> Only a portion of the hard drive is allocated to virtual memory. You can manually change this setting to increase the amount of hard drive space allocated, but eventually your computer will become sluggish as it is forced to page more often. This condition of excessive paging is called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>thrashing</span>. The solution to this problem is to increase the amount of RAM in your computer so that it won’t be necessary for it to send data and instructions to virtual memory.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(13,0)"
						style="height: 200px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.10.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.10</span> Virtual memory borrows excess storage capacity from the hard drive when there isn’t enough capacity in RAM. <em>(brontazavra/ Shutterstock; aPERFECT/Fotolia; Tim Dobbs/Shutterstock)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
			
			
				<div class="orangeHorzButton" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(13,1)">
					<span class="largeBoldWhite">ethics</span>
					<span class="medBoldGrey">in IT</span>
					<strong style="font-size:14px;">Sugar: The Sweet OS for Every Child</strong>
				</div>		
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="14" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How does the OS manage storage?</strong> If it weren’t for the OS, the files and applications you save to the hard drive and other storage locations would be an unorganized mess. Fortunately, the OS has a file-management system that keeps track of the name and location of each file you save and the programs you install. We’ll talk more about file management later in this chapter.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Hardware and Peripheral Device Management</h2>
					<p><strong>How does the OS manage the hardware and peripheral devices?</strong> Each device attached to your computer comes with a special program called a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>device driver</span> that facilitates communication between the device and the OS. Because the OS must be able to communicate with every device in the computer system, the device driver translates the device’s specialized commands into commands the OS can understand, and vice versa. Devices wouldn’t function without the proper device drivers because the OS wouldn’t know how to communicate with them.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Do I always need to install drivers?</strong> Today, most devices, such as flash drives, mice, keyboards, and digital cameras, come with the driver already installed in Windows. The devices whose drivers are included in Windows are called Plug and Play devices. <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Plug and Play (PnP)</span> is a software and hardware standard designed to facilitate the installation of new hardware in PCs by including in the OS the drivers these devices  need in order to run. Because the OS includes this software, incorporating a new device into your computer system seems automatic. PnP lets you plug a </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>new device into your computer, turn it on, and immediately play (use) the device (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(14,1)">see Figure 5.13</span>).</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(14,0)" class="readMore"></a>
				<br/>	
					
					<p class="start"><strong>Can I damage my system by installing a device driver?</strong> Occasionally, when you install a driver your system may become unstable (that is, programs may stop responding, certain actions may cause a crash, or the device or the entire system may stop working). Although this is uncommon, it can happen. Fortunately, to remedy the problem, Windows has a Roll Back Driver feature that removes a newly installed driver and replaces it with the last one that worked (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(15,0)">see Figure 5.14</span>).</p>
				<br/>
				
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(14,1)"
						style="height: 215px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.13.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.13</span> A Windows message showing a successful driver install the first time an external hard drive was connected to the computer.</figcaption>
   			</figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="15" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:296px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.14.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(15,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_14.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;bottom:22px;">
						<span>Figure 5.14</span> The Roll Back Driver feature in Windows removes a newly installed driver and replaces it with the last one that worked.
						</figcaption></figure>
					
					<p class="smaller"><em>>To access the Device Manager window, navigate to the desktop, display Control Panel, and click the <strong>Hardware and Sound</strong> group. Then, in the <strong>Devices and Printers</strong> group, click the <strong>Device Manager</strong> link. To display the Properties dialog box, double-click on a device. Click the <strong>Driver</strong> tab.</em></p>
					
				<br/>	
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain noTMargin">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_11.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Managing Hardware and Peripheral Devices: The OS
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about how the OS manages memory, storage, hardware, and peripheral device.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Software Application Coordination</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>How does the OS help application software run on the computer?</strong> Every computer program, no matter what its type or manufacturer, needs to interact with the CPU using computer code. For programs to work with the CPU, they must contain code the CPU recognizes. Rather than having the same blocks of code for similar procedures in each program, the OS includes the blocks of code—each called an <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>application programming interface (API)</span>—that application software needs in order to interact with the CPU. Microsoft DirectX, for example, is a group of multimedia APIs built into the Windows OS that improves graphics and sounds when you’re playing games or watching videos on your PC.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What are the advantages of using APIs?</strong> To create applications that can communicate with the OS, software programmers need only refer to the API code blocks when they write an application. They don’t need to include the entire code sequence. APIs not only prevent redundancies in software code, they make it easier for software developers to respond to changes in the OS. Software companies also take advantage of APIs to make applications in software suites (such as Microsoft Office) that have a similar interface and functionality. And since these applications share common APIs, data exchange is facilitated between two programs, such as inserting a chart from Excel into a Word document.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="16" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashed"></div>
				
					<div class="fancyHeadingOB"
						 style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/bootsThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">the boot process: starting</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left: 105px;">Your Computer</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>Many things happen quickly between the time you turn on your computer and the time it’s ready for you to start using it. As we discussed earlier, all data and instructions (including the OS) are stored in RAM while your computer is on. When you turn off your computer, RAM is wiped clean of all its data (including the OS). How does the computer know what to do when you turn it on if there is nothing in RAM? It runs through a special boot process (or start-up process) to load the OS into RAM. The term <em>boot</em>, from <em>bootstrap loader</em> (a small program used to start a larger program), alludes to the straps of leather, called <em>bootstraps</em>, that people used to use to help them pull on their boots. This is the source of the expression “pull yourself up by your bootstraps.”</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What are the steps involved in the boot process?</strong> As illustrated in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(16,0)">Figure 5.15</span>, the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>boot process</span> consists of four basic steps. Let’s look at each step in detail.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Step 1: Activating BIOS</h2>
					<p><strong>What’s the first thing that happens after I turn on my computer?</strong> In the first step of the boot process, the CPU activates the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>basic input/output system (BIOS)</span>. BIOS is a program that manages the exchange of data between the OS and all the input and and output devices attached to the </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">The Boot Process</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(16,0)" style="    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.15.jpg) no-repeat scroll 31px 38px #FFFFFF; height: 290px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading"><strong style="padding-left:6px">Figure 5.15</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="padding:5px 10px;"><span>Figure 5.15</span> The Boot Process <em>(Arno van Dulmen/Shutterstock; Ragnarock/Shutterstock)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
				<br/>	
					<p>system. BIOS is also responsible for loading the OS into RAM from its permanent location on the hard drive. BIOS itself is stored on a read-only memory (ROM) chip on the motherboard. Unlike data stored in RAM, data stored in ROM is permanent and is not erased when the power is turned off.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Step 2: Performing the Power-On Self-Test</h2>
					<p><strong>How does the computer determine whether the hardware is working properly?</strong> The first job BIOS performs is to ensure that essential peripheral </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="17" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>devices are attached and operational—a process called the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="power-on self-test (post)">power-on self-test, or POST</span>. The BIOS compares the results of the POST with the various hardware configurations permanently stored in CMOS (pronounced “see-moss”). CMOS, which stands for <em>complementary metal-oxide semiconductor</em>, is a special kind of memory that uses almost no power. A little battery provides enough power so that the CMOS contents won’t be lost after the computer is turned off. CMOS contains information about the system’s memory, types of disk drives, and other essential input and output hardware components. If the results of the POST compare favorably with the hardware configurations stored in CMOS, the boot process continues.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Step 3: Loading the OS</h2>
					<p><strong>How does the OS get loaded into RAM?</strong> Next, BIOS goes through a preconfigured list of devices in its search for the drive that contains the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>system files</span>, the main files of the OS. When it is located, the OS loads into RAM from its permanent storage location on the hard drive.</p>
					<p class="start">Once the system files are loaded into RAM, the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="kernel (supervisor program)">kernel (or supervisor program)</span> is loaded. The kernel is the essential component of the OS. It’s responsible for managing the processor and all other components of the computer system. Because it stays in RAM the entire time your computer is powered on, the kernel is said to be <em>memory resident</em>. Other, less critical, parts of the OS stay on the hard drive and are copied over to RAM on an as-needed basis so that RAM is managed more efficiently. These programs are referred to as <em>non-resident</em>. Once the kernel is loaded, the OS takes over control of the computer’s functions.</p>
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Step 4: Checking Further Configurations and Customizations</h2>
					<p><strong>Is that it?</strong> Finally, the OS checks the registry for the configuration of other system components. The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>registry</span> contains all the different configurations (settings) used by the OS and by other applications. It contains the customized settings you put into place, such as mouse speed, as well as instructions as to which programs should be loaded first.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Why do I sometimes need to enter a login name and password at the end of the boot process?</strong> The verification of your login name and password is called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>authentication</span>. The authentication process blocks unauthorized users from entering the system. You may have your home computer set up for authentication, especially if you have multiple users accessing it. All large networked environments, like your college, require user authentication for access.</p>
					<p class="start">On a Windows 8 computer, the default setting is to input a password to log in to your <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Microsoft account</span> after your computer has completely booted up. Because configuration settings are stored online and associated </p>
					
				<br/>	
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain noTMargin">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_12.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Starting the Computer: The Boot Process
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about how the operating system helps the computer start up.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="18" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing">with a particular Microsoft account, this makes it easy for multiple people to share any Windows 8 computer while maintaining access to their individual settings and preferences.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>How do I know if the boot process is successful?</strong> The entire boot process takes only a few minutes to complete. If the entire system is checked out and loaded properly, the process completes by displaying the Start screen. The computer system is now ready to accept your first command.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Handling Errors in the Boot Process</h2>
					<p class="lessSpacing"><strong>What should I do if my computer doesn’t boot properly?</strong> Sometimes problems occur during the boot process. Here are some suggestions for solving a boot problem:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">If you’ve recently installed new software or hardware, try uninstalling it. (Make sure you use the Uninstall a program feature in the Control Panel to remove the software.) If the problem no longer occurs when rebooting, you can reinstall the device or software.</li></span>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Try accessing the Windows Advanced Options Menu (accessible by pressing the F8 key during the boot process). If Windows detects a problem in the boot process, it will add Last Known Good Configuration to the Windows Advanced Options Menu. Every time your computer boots successfully, a configuration of the boot process is saved. When you choose to boot with the Last Known Good Configuration, the OS starts your computer by using the registry information that was saved during the last shut down.</li></span>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
						
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Try refreshing your computer (new in Windows 8).</span></li>
					</ul>	
					
					<p class="start"><strong>What happens when a PC is “refreshed”?</strong> Sometimes Windows does not boot properly or the system does not respond properly.You may even see messages related to “fatal exceptions.” <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Refresh your PC</span> is a new utility program in Windows 8 that attempts to diagnose and fix errors in your Windows system files that are causing your computer to behave improperly (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(18,0)">see Figure 5.16</span>).</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:206px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.16.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(18,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_16.html','_blank')"
						></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 5.16</span> The PC settings screen in Windows 8 provides access to the Refresh your PC option.
						</figcaption></figure>
					
					<p class="smaller"><em>>To access the PC Settings screen, display the Charms bar on the Start screen (swipe from right, or point cursor to upper-right corner of screen), click <strong>Settings</strong>, then click <strong>More PC Settings</strong>. On the PC Settings screen, click <strong>General</strong>, and scroll down.</em></p>
					
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="19" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>When a PC is refreshed, the following occurs:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Your data files (documents, music, videos, etc.) and personalization settings are not removed or changed.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Apps that you have downloaded from the Windows Store are kept intact.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Apps that you have downloaded from the Internet or installed from DVDs will be removed from your PC. Therefore, you’ll need to reinstall them after the refresh.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">It’s recommended that you back up your PC prior to refreshing it as a precautionary measure. Finally, if all other attempts to fix your computer fail, try a System Restore to roll back to a past configuration. System Restore is covered in more detail later in this chapter.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What should I do if my keyboard or another device doesn’t work after I boot my computer?</strong> Sometimes during the boot process, BIOS skips a device (such as a keyboard) or improperly identifies it. Your only indication that this problem has occurred is that the device won’t respond after the system has been booted. When that happens, try rebooting. If the problem persists, check the OS’s website for any patches (or software fixes) that may resolve the issue. If there are no patches or the problem persists, you may want to get technical assistance.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to Part 2:</strong>
							<span class="dot">Watch <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/Chapter_5_Part_1/Chapter_5_Part_1.html','_blank')" >Replay Video 5.1</span>.</span>
							<span class="dot">Then <span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(16)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="20" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">Which OS do you have on your smartphone?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Android</li>
						<li>iOS</li>
						<li>BlackBerry</li>
						<li>Microsoft Phone</li>
						<li>Other</li>
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="21" type="Full" distinction=""
				customscript="compTia.modules.toggleModule(17)" closescript="compTia.modules.toggleModule(0)">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="22" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes font_19">Using System Software</div>
					<p class="digCompP">Now that you know how system software works, let’s explore how specific operating systems and their tools function.</p>
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeMidDiagDashes"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingBO bgPosition00" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/windowsThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="dblue" style="margin-left:59px; color:#166beb">the windows</div>
						<div class="orange" style="margin-left: 133px">Interface</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>As we mentioned earlier, Windows 8 is a departure from previous versions of Windows because it’s designed for a variety of devices, including laptops, desktops, and tablet PCs. To enable Windows 8 to function on all types of devices, there are often three different ways to accomplish tasks in Windows 8:</p>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Using a mouse</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Touching the screen (on touch-enabled devices)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Using keystrokes</span></li>
					</ol>
					<p>Which method you use depends on the type of device you’re using and, to a large extent, on your personal preferences.</p>
					<p class="start">The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Start screen</span> is the first interaction you have with the OS and the first image you see on your display. As its name implies, the Start screen is the place where you begin all of your computing activities. The Windows 8 Start screen provides you with access to your most used applications in one convenient screen.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>How do Windows 8 “optimized” programs differ from older Windows apps?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8 apps</span> are applications specifically designed</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>to run in the interface of Windows 8. The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8 interface</span> features large type with clean, readable block images inspired by metropolitan service signs such as those found on bus stations and subways.</p>
					<p class="start">Windows 8 apps either are preinstalled with Windows 8 (such as Photos, Messaging, and Calendar) or are available for download from the Windows Store (Microsoft’s apps marketplace). You can launch Windows 8 apps by clicking or tapping on their icons on the Startscreen.</p>

					<p class="start">Windows 8 apps are displayed full screen, without the distractions of borders or controls (such as scrollbars or menus). For example, <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)">Figure 5.17</span> shows Internet Explorer 10, which is a Windows 8 app. Notice that unlike older versions of Internet Explorer, there are no window borders or menus visible (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)">see Figure 5.17a</span>), as the application fills the entire screen. Controls and settings are contained on <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>app bars</span>, such as the Tabs bar and Address bar (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)">Figure 5.17b</span>), that float on screen above the app when you summon them or you need them. Right-clicking on a Windows 8 app screen usually displays the app bars.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>What are the main features of the Windows 8 Start screen?</strong> The Start screen is based on the interface for Windows smartphones. The most useful feature of the Start screen is that it lets you customize it to meet your needs. As such, the Start screen on your computer may be different from the Start screen on your friend’s computer. And because your Windows 8 settings and preferences are saved in your Microsoft account, when you log on to any Windows 8 computer, you’ll see your own personal settings, preferences, and applications reflected on the Start screen (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,0)">see Figure 5.18</span>).</p>
					
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="23" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:535px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.17.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(23,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_17.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;bottom:8px;">
						<span>Figure 5.17</span> (a) Internet Explorer 10, a Windows 8 app, displays full screen. (b) Right-clicking on the Internet Explorer 10 screen displays the open Tabs bar (top) and the Address bar (bottom).
						</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start lessSpacing">For performing common tasks, such as searching or sharing information, Windows 8 has created special shortcuts called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>charms</span>. Charms are located on the <em>Charms bar</em> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,0)">see Figure 5.18</span>), which you access by moving your cursor to the upper-right corner of the screen, swiping in from the right edge of the screen, or pressing the Windows key+C.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>Why can’t I see icons for certain applications on my Start screen?</strong> Not all the Windows 8 apps and programs installed on your computer are visible on the Start screen. You can choose which applications are visible on the Start screen through a process called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>pinning</span>. Usually, when you install a Windows 8 app or any other program on your computer, it pins the program (displays it) on the Star screen by default. (For more on pinning apps, <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(1,21)">see the Try This feature</span>.) If there is an icon on the Start screen you don’t need, just right-click on it (or touch and hold) and select the Unpin from Start option that appears on the app bar at the bottom of the screen. If you want to see all the applications installed on your computer, not just the ones pinned to your Start screen, right-click on a blank area of the Start screen and select the All apps option that app bars at the bottom of the screen. This displays the Apps screen (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,1)">see Figure 5.19</span>), which shows all Windows 8 apps and other programs installed on your computer.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>What happened to the Start button from Windows 7?</strong> When using Windows 8 for the first time, you might be looking for the Start button, which has been removed.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>



<!-- START FROM HERE!!! -->

		<page index="24" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:248px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.18.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_18.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px; bottom:4px">
						<span>Figure 5.18</span> The Windows 8 Start screen puts the most commonly used features of the OS at your fingertips. You can easily customize it to meet your needs.
						</figcaption></figure>
	
					<figure class="TMargin10" style="height: 238px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.19.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(24,1)" />

					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_19.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;bottom:17px">
						<span>Figure 5.19</span> The Windows 8 Apps screen shows all Windows 8 apps and other programs installed on your computer.
						</figcaption></figure>	
						
					<div class="itSimContain TMargin10"
							onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_mylabs/simulations/2012/IT/system_software','_blank')">
							<div class="itSimContent">
								<span>IT</span>
								<span>Simulation - System Software</span>
							</div>
						</div>		
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>There are several ways to return to the Start screen in Windows 8:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Press the Windows key.</li></span>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Display the Charms bar and click (or touch) Start.</li></span>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Move your cursor to the lower-left corner of your screen (roughly where the Start button used to be) to display a Start screen icon. Click it to display the Start screen.</li></span>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I quickly access useful programs and tools that were available from the Windows 7 Start button?</strong> Although the Start button is gone, right-clicking on your screen in the lower-left corner displays a menu of quick links to common administrative tasks and programs, such as Control Panel and File Explorer.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Where is the Windows desktop?</strong> If you’ve been using versions of Windows prior to Windows 8, you’re used to the desktop being the first screen you see on your computer. The desktop from Windows 7 still exists, just in a slightly modified version. You can access the Windows 8 desktop via the Desktop icon on the Start screen or by pressing the Windows key+D. Programs that have not been designed to run in the Windows 8 interface (like Microsoft Office 2010) will run on the Windows 8 desktop.</p>
					<p class="start">The desktop still has features like the taskbar. The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>taskbar</span> displays open and favorite applications for easy access. You can point to an icon to preview windows of open files or programs, or move your mouse over a thumbnail to preview a full-screen image. Or, you can right-click an icon to view a Jump List—the most recently or commonly used files or commands for that application.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		
		<page index="25" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I switch between apps in Windows 8?</strong> If you want to go back to the last program you were using, just point your cursor to the upper-left corner of the screen and drag (or swipe) from the left. Drag the thumbnail image of your previous program to the middle of your screen and it will be available. Repeatedly swiping from the left will scroll backward through all your open programs.</p>
					<p class="start">For a list of open programs—so you can jump right to the correct one—position your cursor in the upperleft corner until the thumbnail appears, then move the cursor down (or swipe in from the left, and before you let go, swipe out again) to display a list of thumbnails of previous programs called a <em>switch list</em> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(25,0)">see Figure 5.20</span>). Alternatively, pressing the Alt and Tab keys simultaneously also allows you to scroll through open apps.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I see more than one Windows 8 app on my screen at a time?</strong> Windows 8 apps can snap into place on either the left or right side of the screen, so you can easily display two apps at the same time. Just display the thumbnail list of running apps and click and drag the thumbnail of the second app you want to display to the left or right side of the screen. The app will snap into place while still leaving the other app you had running visible.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I close a Windows 8 app?</strong> When Windows 8 apps aren’t displayed on the screen, Windows will suspend them temporarily so they don’t use much memory or power. Therefore, theoretically, you don’t ever need to shut down Windows 8 apps. However, most people prefer not to have endless apps running, and it may be inconvenient to scroll through a </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:533px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.20.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(25,0)" style="margin-left:60px"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_20.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 5.20</span> The thumbnails of open programs allow you to switch quickly between them. <em>(Alan Evans)</em>
						</figcaption></figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="26" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">huge list of running apps to find the one you want. To close a Windows 8 app from within the app, press Alt+F4. Alternatively, you can move your cursor to the top of the screen until it turns into a hand, then left-click and drag down. The app will shrink to a small window. Drag it down to the bottom of the screen and release the mouse button to close the app. Right-clicking on a thumbnail of the app on the switch list also allows you to close an app.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How does the Mac user interface compare with Windows 8?</strong> Although the OS X and the Windows operating systems aren’t compatible, they’re extremely similar in terms of functionality. For example, as is the case with Windows, OS X programs appear in resizable windows and use menus and icons. However, instead of the Start screen, OS X features a Dock with icons on the bottom for your most popular programs (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,1)">see Figure 5.21</span>). Mountain Lion, the latest version of OS X, adds many applications that have become so popular in iOS.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Is a Linux user interface similar to OS X and Windows?</strong> Different distros of Linux feature different user interfaces. But most of them, like Ubuntu (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,2)">see Figure 5.22</span>), are based on familiar Windows and OS X paradigms such as using icons to launch programs and having apps run in a window environment.</p>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue" style="font-size:12px;">
							<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
							Touch Language for Windows 8
						</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,1)"
						style="height: 222px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.21.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.21</span> <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.apple.com/osx/','_blank')">OS X Mountain Lion</span> adds many of apps that have become so popular in iOS.</figcaption>
   			</figure>	
				
			<br/>	
				<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,2)"
						style="height: 227px;background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.22.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 0 transparent;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				<span>Figure 5.22</span> The <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.ubuntu.com','_blank')">Ubuntu</span> Linux user interface resembles the Windows desktop. <em>(Masterfile)</em></figcaption>
   			</figure>
			
			<br/>
				<img onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,3)" src="assets/images/layout/TrendsinItChapter5.0.jpg" />	
			]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="27" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="greenHeadingLineDashed"></div>
		
							<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/stackThumbnail.jpg)">
								<div class="orange">organizing your computer: file</div>
								<div class="blue" style="margin-left:122px;">MANAGEMENT</div>
							</div>
							
					<p>So far we’ve discussed how the OS manages the processor, memory, storage, and devices, and that it provides a way for applications and users to interact with the computer. An additional function of the OS is to enable <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file management</span>, which provides an organizational structure to your computer’s contents. In this section, we discuss how you can use this organizational structure to make your computer more organized and efficient.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Organizing Your Files</h2>
					<p><strong>How does the OS organize files?</strong> Windows organizes the contents of your computer in a hierarchical <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>directory</span> structure composed of <em>drives, libraries, folders, subfolders,</em> and <em>files</em>. The hard drive, represented as the C: drive, is where you permanently store most of your files. Each additional storage drive (optical drive, flash drive, or external hard drive) is given a unique letter (<em>D, E, F</em>, and so on). The C: drive is like a large filing cabinet in which all files are stored. As such, the C: drive is the top of the filing structure of your computer and is referred to as the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>root directory</span>. All other folders and files are organized within the root directory. There are areas in the root directory that the OS has filled with files and folders holding special OS files. The programs within these files help run the computer and generally shouldn’t be accessed.</p>		
							
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>What exactly are files and folders?</strong> In an OS, a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file</span> is a collection of program instructions or data that is stored and treated as a single unit. Files can be generated from an application such as a Word document or an Excel workbook. In addition, files can represent an entire application, a web page, a set of sounds, or an image. Files can be stored on the hard drive, a flash drive, online, or on any other permanent storage medium. As the number of files you save increases, it becomes more important to keep them organized in folders and libraries. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>folder</span> is a collection of files.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How does the library work?</strong> In Windows, a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>library</span> gathers categories of files from different locations and displays them as if they were all saved in a single folder, regardless of where they are physically stored. For example, you might have pictures stored all over your computer, including your external hard drive. Rather than looking through each separate location to view your pictures, you can access all of them more easily by looking in the Pictures library. There are four default libraries: Documents, Music, Pictures, and Videos.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I easily locate and see the contents of my computer?</strong> In Windows, <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>File Explorer</span> (previously called Windows Explorer) is the main tool for finding, viewing, and managing the contents of your computer. It shows the location and contents of every drive, folder, and file. As illustrated </p>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(27,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue" style="font-size:12px;">
							<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
							How to Get the Most from Windows Libraries
						</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="28" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(28,0)">Figure 5.24</span>, File Explorer is divided into two panes, or sections:</p>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi">The <em>navigation pane</em> on the left shows the contents of your computer. It displays commonly accessed areas, organized by Favorites and Libraries (Documents, Music, Pictures, and Videos).</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">When you select a Favorite, Library, drive, or network, the files and folders of that particular area are displayed in the <em>details pane</em></span> on the right.</li>
					</ol>
					
					<p><strong>What are some tips on how best to organize my files?</strong> Creating folders is the key to organizing files because folders keep related documents together. For example, you might create one folder called “Classes” to hold </p>
					
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:238px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.24.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(28,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_24.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;bottom:33px;">
						<span>Figure 5.24</span> File Explorer lets you see the contents of your computer.
						</figcaption></figure>
						
					<p><em>>Right-click the lower-left corner of the screen to display the menu, and then select <strong>File Explorer</strong>.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>your class work. Inside the “Classes” folder, you could create subfolders for each of your classes (such as CIS 110 and BUS 336). Inside each of those subfolders, you could create further subfolders for each class’s assignments, homework, and so on.</p>
					<p class="start">Grouping related files into folders makes it easier for you to identify and find files. Which would be easier—going to the CIS 110 folder to find a file or searching through the hundreds of individual files in the Documents library hoping to find the right one? Grouping files in a folder also allows you to move files more efficiently, so you can quickly transfer critical files needing frequent backup, for instance.</p>
					
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/file_management/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							File Management
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll examine the features of file management and maintenance. You’ll learn the various methods of creating folders, how to turn a group of unorganized files into an organized system of folders with related files, and how to maintain your file system.
					</div></div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Viewing and Sorting Files and Folders</h2>
					<p><strong>Are there different ways I can view and sort my files and folders?</strong> When you open any folder in File Explorer, the ribbon at the top displays a View tab. Clicking on the View tab offers you different ways to view the folders and files. In some views, the folders are displayed as <em>Live Icons</em>. Live Icons allows you to preview the actual contents of a specific file or folder without actually opening the file. Live Icons can be displayed in a variety of views.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="29" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
						<p class="lessSpacing">Here are the two most useful views for students:</p>
						<ol>
							<li><span class="innerLi lessSpacing"><strong>Details view:</strong> This is the most interactive view. As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(28,0)">Figure 5.24</span>, files and folders are displayed in list form, and the additional file information is displayed in columns alongside the name of the file. You can sort and display the contents of the folder by any of the column headings, so you can sort the contents alphabetically by name or type, or hierarchically by date last modified or file size. Right-click the column heading area to modify the display of columns.</span></li>
							<li><span class="innerLi lessSpacing"><strong>Large Icons view:</strong> As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(29,0)">Figure 5.25</span>, Large Icons view shows the contents of folders as small images. Large Icons view is the best view to use if your folder contains picture files because you can see a  few images</span></li>
						</ol>	
					
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 5px;height:233px">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.25.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(29,0)" />
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_25.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;bottom:10px;">
						<span>Figure 5.25</span> The Large Icons view is a good way to display the contents of files and folders. The preview pane on the right lets you see the first page of your document without first opening it.
						</figcaption></figure>
						
					<p class="lessSpacing"><em>>To access Large Icons <strong>view</strong>, click the View option from the ribbon in File Explorer, and then select <strong>Large Icons</strong> view. To access the Preview pane, click that icon on the View tab of the ribbon.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p style="margin-left:10px;">peeking out of the folder. It’s also good to use if your folder contains PowerPoint presentations because the title slide of the presentation will display, making it easier for you to distinguish among presentations. Additionally, a preview pane is available in this view. The preview pane lets you view the first page of the selected document without having to open it.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What’s the best way to search for a file?</strong> In Windows 8, the Search app is the best way to search for files and the contents of folders. The Search app searches through your hard drive or other storage devices (DVD or flash drive) to locate files and folders that match the criteria you provide. Your search can be based on part of the name of file or folder or just a word or phrase in it. You can also search for a file type by representing the file name as an asterisk (called a wildcard character) and typing the file extension (such as “*.xlsx” to search for Excel files). You access the Search app from the Charms bar or from File Explorer. OS X has a similar feature called Spotlight.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Naming Files</h2>
					<p><strong>Are there special rules I have to follow when I name files?</strong> The first part of a file, or the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file name</span>, is generally the name you assign to the file when you save it. For example, “bioreport” may be the name you assign a report you have completed for a biology class.</p>
					<p class="start">In a Windows application, an <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="extension (file type)">extension, or file type</span>, follows the file name and a period or dot (.). Like a last name, this extension identifies what kind of family of files the file belongs to, or which application should be </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>		
		
		<page index="30" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing">used to read the file. For example, if “bioreport” is a spreadsheet created in Microsoft Excel 2010, it has an .xlsx extension,  and its name is “bioreport.xlsx.” <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(30,1)">Figure 5.26</span> lists some common file extensions and the types of documents they indicate.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>Why is it important to know the file extension?</strong> When you save a file created in most applications running under the Windows OS, you don’t need to add the extension to the file name; it is added automatically for you. Mac and Linux operating systems don’t require file extensions. This is because the information as to the type of application the computer should use to open the file is stored inside the file itself. However, if you’re using the Mac or Linux OS and will be sending files to Windows users, you should add an extension to your file name so that Windows can more easily open your files. </p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(30,0)" class="readMore"></a>
					
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>Are there things I shouldn’t do when naming my files?</strong> Each OS has its own naming conventions, or rules, which are listed in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,0)">Figure 5.27</span>. Beyond those conventions, it’s important that you name your files so that you can easily identify them. Files names can have as many as 255 characters, so don’t be afraid to use as many characters as you need. A file name such as “BIO 101 Research Paper First Draft.docx” makes it very clear what that file contains.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing">Keep in mind, however, that all files must be uniquely identified, unless you save them in different folders or in different locations. Therefore, although files may share the same file name (such as “bioreport.docx” </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing">or “bioreport.xlsx”) or share the same extension (“bioreport.xlsx” or “budget.xlsx”), no two files stored on the same device and folder can share <em>both</em> the same file name and the same extension.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing"><strong>How can I tell where my files are saved?</strong> When you save a file for the first time, you give the file a name and designate where you want to save it. For easy reference, the OS includes libraries where files are saved unless you </p>
					
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain TMargin5">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_13.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Organizing Your Computer: File Management
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about the desktop, window features, and how the OS helps keep the computer organized.
					</div></div>
					
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13">Common File Name Extensions</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(30,1)" style="
						background: url('assets/images/figures/fig5.26.jpg') no-repeat scroll 15px 24px #FFFFFF;
						height: 225px; overflow: hidden;">
						<span class="strongDHeading font_dBlu font_15 TMargin5"><strong>Figure 5.26</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>

						</figure></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="31" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13">File-Naming Conventions</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,0)" style="
						background: url('assets/images/figures/fig5.27.jpg') no-repeat scroll 12px 28px #FFFFFF;
						height: 174px; overflow: hidden;">
						<span class="strongDHeading font_15 TMargin5"><strong>Figure 5.27</strong> Click to enlarge the table</span>

						</figure></div>
					<br/>	
					
					<p>specify otherwise. In Windows, the default libraries are Documents for files, Music for audio files, Pictures for graphics files, and Videos for video files.</p>
					<p class="start">You can determine the location of a file by its <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file path</span>. The file path starts with the drive in which the file is located and includes all folders, subfolders (if any), the file name, and the extension. For example, if you were saving a picture of Andrew Carnegie for a term paper for a U.S. History course, the file path might be C:\Documents\HIS182\Term Paper\Illustrations\ACarnegie.jpg.</p>
					<p class="start">As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,1)">Figure 5.28</span>, “C:” is the drive on which the file is stored (in this case, the hard drive), and “Documents” is the file’s  primary folder. “HIS182,” “Term Paper,” and “Illustrations” are successive subfolders within the “Documents” main folder. Last comes the file name, “ACarnegie,” separated from the file extension (in this case, “jpg”) by a period. </p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13">Understanding File Paths</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(31,1)" style="
						background: url('assets/images/figures/fig5.28.jpg') no-repeat scroll 5px 40px #FFFFFF;
						height: 142px; overflow: hidden;">
						<span class="strongDHeading font_15 TMargin5"><strong>Figure 5.28</strong> Click to reveal the active graphic</span>

						</figure></div>
					<br/>	
					
					<p>The backslash characters (\), used by Windows, are referred to as <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="path separator">path separators</span>. OS X files use a colon (:), whereas UNIX and Linux files use the forward slash (/) as the path separator.</p>	
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Working with Files</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I move and copy files?</strong> Once you’ve located your file with File Explorer, you can perform many other file-management actions such as opening, copying, moving, renaming, and deleting files. You open a file by double-clicking the file from its storage location. You can copy a file to another location using the Copy command. To move a file from one location to another, use the Cut command. You can access both of these commands easily by right-clicking on a file’s name, which displays a shortcut menu.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Where do deleted files go?</strong> The <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Recycle Bin</span> is a folder on the desktop, represented by an icon that looks like a recycling bin, where files deleted from the hard drive reside until you permanently purge them from </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="32" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>your system. Unfortunately, files deleted from other drives don’t go to the Recycle Bin but are deleted from the system immediately. In addition, files stored in the cloud are not cycled through the Recycle Bin. When you delete a file from a Dropbox or SkyDrive folder, consider it gone forever!</p>
					<p class="start">Mac systems have something similar to the Recycle Bin, called Trash, which is represented by a waste basket icon. To delete files on a Mac, drag the files to the Trash icon.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I permanently delete files from my system?</strong> Files placed in the Recycle Bin or the Trash remain in the system until they’re permanently deleted. To delete files from the Recycle Bin permanently, select Empty Recycle Bin after right-clicking the desktop icon. On Macs, select Empty Trash from the Finder menu in OS X.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>What happens if I need to recover a deleted file?</strong> Getting a file back after the Trash has been emptied still may be possible. When the Trash is emptied, only the reference to the file is deleted permanently, so the OS has no easy way to find the file. The file data actually remains on the hard drive until it’s written over by another file. You may be able to use a program such as FarStone’s RestoreIT! or Norton Ghost to try to retrieve files you think you’ve permanently deleted. These programs reveal files that are still intact on the hard drive and help you recover them. This is how they do it on CSI!</p>
					
					<div onclick="compTia.togglePopup(32,0)" class="bitsAndBytesBlue noTMargin">
					<span class="bits">Bits</span><span class="and">&</span><span class="bytes">bytes</span><br>
					A File Type for Everyone
				</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="blueHeadingLineDashedEnd"></div>

					<div class="fancyHeadingOB" style="background-image:url(assets/images/pics/workmanThumbnail.jpg)">
						<div class="orange">utility</div>
						<div class="blue" style="margin-left:89px;">Programs</div>
					</div>
					
					<p>The main component of system software is the OS. However, <em>utility programs</em>—small applications that perform special functions on the computer—are also an essential part of system software. Utility programs come in three flavors:</p>
					<ol class="noBMargin">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Those that are included with the OS (such as System Restore)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Those sold as stand-alone programs (such as antivirus software)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Those offered as freeware (such as anti-malware software like Ad-Aware from Lavasoft)</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start"><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(33,0)">Figure 5.30</span> lists some of the various types of utility programs available within the Windows OS as well as some alternatives available as stand-alone programs. In general, the basic utilities designed to manage and tune your computer hardware are incorporated into the OS. The stand-alone utility programs typically offer more features or an easier user interface for backup, security, diagnostic, or recovery functions. For some Windows programs, like Task Manager and Resource Monitor, no good stand-alone alternatives exist.</p>	
					
					<div class="activeHelpdeskContain noTMargin">
						<div class="activeHelpdeskContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_tiahelpdesk_9/AHDC_9e/AHDC_hd_14.html','_blank')">
						<div class="activeHelpdesk">
							<span class="icon blueCallPerson"> </span>
							<span class="title">Active Helpdesk</span>
							Using Utility Programs
						</div>
						In this Active Helpdesk call, you’ll play the role of a helpdesk staffer, fielding calls about the utility programs included in system software and what these programs do.
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="33" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Utility Programs</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(33,0)" style="
						background: url('assets/images/figures/fig5.30.jpg') no-repeat scroll 13px 29px #FFFFFF;
						height: 245px; overflow: hidden;">
						<span class="strongDHeading font_dBlu font_15 TMargin5"><strong>Figure 5.30</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>

						</figure></div>
					<br/>	
					<p class="start">In this section, we explore many of the utility programs you’ll find installed on a Windows 8 OS. Unless otherwise noted, you can find Windows utilities in the Control Panel. We’ll discuss antivirus and personal fire wall utility programs in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.generatePages(9)">Chapter 9</span>.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Display Utilities</h2>
					<p><strong>How can I change the appearance of my Start screen and desktop?</strong>You can personalize the Start screen and the lock screen (the screen that forces you to enter a password to resume using your computer) to suit your tastes. To do so, display the Charms bar, select Settings, choose More PC settings, and then the Personalize option. This provides you with </p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="moreSpacing">access to personalization options such as changing pictures, colors, and backgrounds. This also provides you with access to all the features you need to change the appearance of your desktop.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">The Programs and Features Utility</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What’s the correct way to add new programs to my system?</strong> When you download Windows 8 apps from the Windows Store, they automatically install on your computer. If you install non-Windows 8 programs, the program usually automatically runs a <em>wizard</em> that walks you through the installation process. If a wizard doesn’t start automatically, open the Control Panel, click Programs, then click Programs and Features. This prompts the OS to look for the setup  program of the new software, and it starts the installation wizard.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What’s the correct way to remove unwanted programs from my system?</strong> You can quickly uninstall Windows 8 apps by right-clicking their icon on the Start screen (or touching and holding) and selecting the Uninstall option from the app bar. For non-Windows 8 programs, you should use the Windows uninstaller utility found in Programs in the Control Panel. Using either of these methods ensures that you delete not only the main program files but also all supporting files and most registry entries.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">File Compression Utilities</h2>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>Why would I want to use a file compression utility?</strong> File compression makes a large file more compact, making it easier and faster for you to send </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="34" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>large attachments by e-mail, upload them to the web, or save them onto a disc. As shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(34,0)">Figure 5.31</span>, Windows has a built-in <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file compression utility</span> that takes out redundancies in a file (zips it) to reduce the file size. You can also obtain several stand-alone freeware and shareware programs, such as WinZip (for Windows) and StuffIt (for Windows or Mac), to compress your files.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How does file compression work?</strong> Most compression programs look for repeated patterns of letters and replace these patterns with a shorter placeholder. The repeated patterns and the associated placeholder are cataloged and stored temporarily in a separate file called the <em>dictionary</em>. For example, in the following sentence, you can easily see the repeated patterns of letters.</p>
					<br/>
					<p style="color:red; font-size:18px"><strong><span style="color:#166beb;">The</span> r<span style="color:#71ba12;">ain</span> in Sp<span style="color:#71ba12;">ain</span> falls m<span style="color:#71ba12;">ain</span>ly on <span style="color:#166beb;">the</span> pl<span style="color:#71ba12;">ain.</span></strong></p>
					<br/>
					<p>Although this example contains obvious repeated patterns (<span style="color:#71ba12;">ain</span> and <span style="color:#166beb;">the</span>), in a large document, the repeated patterns may be more complex. The compression program’s algorithm (a set of instructions designed to complete a solution in a step-by-step manner) therefore runs through the file several times to determine the optimal repeated patterns needed to obtain the greatest compression.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How effective are file compression programs?</strong> Current compression programs can reduce text files by 50% or more, depending on the file. However, some files, such as PDF files, already contain a form of compression, so they don’t need to be compressed further. Image files such </p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/file_compression/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							File Compression
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn about the advantages of file compression and how to use Windows to compress and decompress files. This Sound Byte also teaches you how to find and install file compression shareware programs.
					</div></div>
					
				
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:336px;width:428px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.31.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(34,0)"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_31.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 5.31</span> (a) File compression is a built-in utility of the Windows OS. (b) Compressing the Word document reduces the file size from 19,034 KB to 18,457 KB
						</figcaption></figure>	
						
					<p class="lessSpacing"><em>>To access the Windows file compression utility, right-click the file or folder that you want to compress, select <strong>Send to</strong> from the shortcut menu, and then select <strong>Compressed (zipped) folder.</strong></em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="35" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>as JPEG, GIF, and PNG files discard small variations in color that the human eye might not pick up. Likewise, MP3 files permanently discard sounds that the human ear can’t hear. These graphic and audio files don’t need further compression.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How do I decompress a file I’ve compressed?</strong> When you want to restore the file to its original state, you need to <em>decompress</em> the file. Generally, the program you used to compress the file can decompress the program you used to compress the file can decompress the file as well (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,0)">see Figure 5.32</span>).</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">System Maintenance Utilities</h2>
					<p><strong>What utilities can make my system work faster?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Disk Cleanup</span> is a Windows utility that removes unnecessary files from your hard drive. These include files that have accumulated in the Recycle Bin as well as temporary files—files created by Windows to store data temporarily while a program is running. Windows usually deletes these temporary files when you exit the program, but sometimes it forgets to do this or doesn’t have time because your system freezes or incurs a problem that prevents you from properly exiting a program.</p>
					<p class="start">Disk Cleanup also removes temporary Internet files (web pages stored on your hard drive for quick viewing) as well as offline web pages (pages stored on your computer so you can view them without being connected to the Internet). If not deleted periodically, these unnecessary files can slow down your computer.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:327px;width:418px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.32.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(35,0)"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_32.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px;">
						<span>Figure 5.32</span> The Extraction Wizard in Windows makes unzipping compressed folders and files easy.
						</figcaption></figure>

					<br/>	
						
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I control which files Disk Cleanup deletes?</strong> When you run Disk Cleanup, the program scans your hard drive to determine which folders have files that can be deleted and calculates the amount of hard drive space that will be freed up by doing so. You check off which type of files you would like to delete, as shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(36,0)">Figure 5.33</span>.</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I diagnose potential errors or damage on my hard drive?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="error-checking">Error-checking</span> is a Windows utility that checks for lost files and fragments as well as physical errors on your hard drive. Lost files and</p>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="36" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing">fragments of files occur as you save, resave, move, delete, and copy files on your hard drive. Sometimes the system becomes confused, leaving references on the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="file allocation table (fat)">file allocation table, or FAT</span> (an index of all sector numbers in a table), to files that no longer exist or have been moved. Physical errors on the hard drive occur when the mechanism that reads the hard drive’s data (which is stored as <em>1s</em> or <em>0s</em>) can no longer determine whether the area holds a <em>1</em> or a <em>0</em>. These areas are called <em>bad sectors</em>.</p>
					
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:319px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.33.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(36,0)" style="margin-left:55px;"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_33.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px; bottom:33px;">
						<span>Figure 5.33</span>  Using Disk Cleanup will help free space on your hard drive.
						</figcaption></figure>
						
					<p class="lessSpacing"><em>>Disk Cleanup is accessed by displaying File Explorer, right-clicking on the disk you wish to clean, selecting <strong>Properties</strong> from the shortcut menu, and then clicking the <strong>Disk Cleanup</strong> button on the General tab.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>Sometimes Error-checking can recover the lost data, but more often, it deletes the files that are taking up space.</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(36,1)" class="readMore"></a>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>How can I check on a program that’s stopped running?</strong> If a program has stopped working, you can use the Windows <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Task Manager</span> utility (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,0)">see Figure 5.34</span>) to check on the program or to exit the nonresponsive program. In Windows 8, the Processes tab of Task Manager lists all the programs you’re using and indicates their status. “Not responding” will be shown next to a program that stopped improperly. If the status section is blank (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,0)">Figure 5.34</span>), then the program is working normally. You can terminate programs that aren’t responding by right-clicking the app name and selecting End Task from the shortcut menu.</p>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">System Restore and Backup Utilities</h2>
					<p><strong>Is there an undo command for the system?</strong> Suppose you’ve just installed a new software program and your computer freezes. After rebooting the computer, when you try to start the application, the system freezes once again. You uninstall the new program, but your computer continues to freeze after rebooting. What can you do now?</p>
					<p class="start">Windows has a utility called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>System Restore</span> that lets you roll your system settings back to a specific date when everything was working properly. A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>system restore point</span>, which is a snapshot of your entire system’s settings, is generated prior to certain events, such as installing or </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="37" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/hard_disk_anatomy_interactive/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Hard Disk Anatomy
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll watch a series of animations that show various aspects of a hard drive, including the anatomy of a hard drive, how a computer reads and writes data to a hard drive, and the fragmenting and defragmenting of a hard drive.
					</div></div>
				
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:302px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.34.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,0)" style="margin-left:60px;"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_34.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px; bottom:24px;">
						<span>Figure 5.34</span>  You can use Windows 8 Task Manager to close nonresponsive programs.
						</figcaption></figure>
						
					<p><em>>Task Manager is accessed by holding down <strong>Ctrl, Alt,</strong> and <strong>Del</strong> or by right-clicking on the taskbar at the bottom of the desktop.</em></p>	
						
					<div class="greenHorzButton" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,1)" style="margin-top:10px;">
						<span class="largeBoldWhite">DIG DEEPER</span>
						<strong style="font-size:13px;margin-right:6px;">How Disk Defragmenter Utilities Work</strong>
					</div>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing">updating software, or automatically once a week if no other restore points were created in that time. You also can create a restore point manually at any time.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing">Should problems occur, if the computer was running just fine before you installed new software or a hardware device, you could restore your computer to the settings that were in effect before the software or hardware installation (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,2)">see Figure 5.37</span>). System Restore doesn’t affect your personal data files (such as Word documents or e-mail), so you won’t lose changes made to these files.</p>
				
					<figure style="margin-bottom: 10px;height:244px;">
						<img src="assets/images/figures/fig5.37.jpg" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(37,2)" style="margin-left:60px;"/>
					<div class="playIcon bottomPos"
						onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/streaming/bp/2014/it/evans/figure/Figure_5_37.html','_blank')"></div>
					
					<figcaption style="margin-left:60px; bottom:0px;">
						<span>Figure 5.37</span>  This System Restore Wizard shows a restore point set manually by a user and automatically by Windows before a backup was run. Setting a restore point is good practice before installing any hardware or software.
						</figcaption></figure>
						
					<p class="lessSpacing"><em>>The System Restore Wizard is found by accessing the Control Panel, choosing <strong>System and Security</strong>, clicking the <strong>System</strong> link, selecting <strong>System Protection</strong>, and then clicking the System Restore button. The System Restore Wizard appears, with the restore points shown on the second page of the Wizard.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="38" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="lessSpacing"><strong>How can I protect my data in the event something malfunctions in my system?</strong> When you use the Windows 8 <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>File History</span> utility (found in the Control Panel under System and Security), you can have Windows automatically create a duplicate of your libraries, desktop, contacts, and favorites and copy it to another storage device, such as an external hard drive. A backup copy protects your data in the event your hard drive fails or files are accidentally erased.</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,0)" class="readMore TMargin5"></a>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Accessibility Utilities</h2>
					<p class="lessSpacing"><strong>What utilities are designed for users with special needs?</strong> Microsoft Windows includes an Ease of Access Center, which is a centralized location for assistive technology and tools to adjust accessibility settings. In the Ease of Access Center, which is accessible from the Control Panel, you can find the tools to help users with disabilities, shown in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,1)">Figure 5.38</span>. The tools shown in the figure are just a sampling of the available tools. If you’re not sure where to start or what settings might help, a questionnaire asks you about routine tasks and provides a personalized recommendation for settings that will help you better use your computer.</p>
					
					<div class="soundByteContain noTMargin">
					<div class="soundByteContainContent"
						 onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/letting_your_computer_clean_up_after_itself/index.html','_blank')">
						<div class="soundByte">
							<span class="icon greenSpeaker"> </span>
							<span class="title">Sound Byte</span>
							Letting Your Computer Clean Up After Itself
						</div>
						In this Sound Byte, you’ll learn how to use the various maintenance utilities within the OS. In addition, you’ll learn how to use Task Scheduler to clean up your hard drive automatically. You’ll also learn the best times of the day to schedule these maintenance tasks and why they should be done on a routine basis to make your system more efficient. 
					</div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Whether you use Windows, OS X, Linux, or another operating system, a fully featured OS is available to meet your needs. As long as you keep the operating system updated and regularly use the available utilities to fine tune your system, you should experience little trouble from your OS.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding13">Windows Ease of Access Tools</div>
						<div class="orangeWrap">
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(38,1)" style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.38.jpg) no-repeat scroll 10px 33px #FFFFFF; height: 240px; overflow: hidden;">
							
							<span class="strongDHeading TMargin5"><strong>Figure 5.38</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							
							<figcaption class="bottomPos"></em>
						</figcaption></figure>
					</div>
					
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to Part 2:</strong>
							<span class="dot">Watch <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/Chapter_5_Part_2/Chapter_5_Part_2.html','_blank')" >Replay Video 5.2</span>.</span>
							<span class="dot"><span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(18)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="39" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">Which feature of the OS do you think is most useful?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Task Manager</li>
						<li>Disk Defragmenter</li>
						<li>File Explorer</li>
						<li>System Restore</li>
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="40" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<h1><span class="chapter">5</span> Chapter Review</h1>
			<div class="largerTitle">summary//</div>

				<img src="assets/images/pics/OperatingSmall.jpg" class="floatPositioned">
				<h2>Operating System Fundamentals</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent1 strong">What software is included in systems software?</span>

			<br/>
			<ul class="dotted">
				<li><span class="innerLi">System software is the set of software programs that helps run the computer and coordinates instructions between application software and hardware devices. It consists of the operating system (OS) and utility programs.</span></li>
				<li><span class="innerLi">The OS controls how your computer system functions.</span></li>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Utility programs are programs that perform general housekeeping tasks for the computer, such as system maintenance and file compression.</span></li>
			</ul>
				
				<h4>2. What are the different kinds of operating systems?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">There are many different kinds of operating systems.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Real-time operating systems (RTOSs) require no user intervention. They are designed for systems with a specific purpose and response time (such as robotic machinery).</span></li>	
						<li><span class="innerLi">A multiuser operating system (network operating system) provides access to a computer system by more than one user at a time.</span></li>
					</ul>
			
			
					
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Smartphones have their own specific operating systems, which allow the user to multitask.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Tablets use operating systems (such as iOS, Android, and Windows 8) that allow interaction with touchscreen interfaces.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Gaming consoles use operating systems developed specifically for those particular devices.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Current operating systems for desktops, laptops, and netbooks have multitasking and networking capabilities.</span></li>
					</ul>
				<br/>	
					<h4>3. What are the most common operating systems?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Microsoft Windows is the most popular OS. It has evolved into a powerful multiuser OS. The most recent release is Windows 8.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Another popular OS is the Mac OS, which is designed to work on Apple computers. Apple’s most recent release, Mac OS X, is based on the UNIX OS.</span></li>	
						<li><span class="innerLi">There are various versions of UNIX on the market, although UNIX is most often used on networks.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Linux is an open source OS based on UNIX and designed primarily for use on personal computers, although it is often used on servers and supercomputers.</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<img src="assets/images/pics/orgastraSmall.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:13px;margin-top:19px;" />
				<h2>What the Operating System Does</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent4 strong">How does the operating system provide a means for users to interact with the computer?</span>


			<ul class="dotted TMargin5 clearLeft">
				<li><span class="innerLi">The OS provides a user interface that enables users to interact with the computer.</span></li>
			</ul>
				
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
			
			<page index="41" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
		<section>
			<![CDATA[
				<ul class="dotted">
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Most OSs today use a graphical user interface (GUI). Unlike the command-and menu-driven interfaces used many years ago, GUIs display graphics and use the point-and-click technology of the mouse and cursor (or touch-sensitive screens), making the OS more user-friendly. Common features of GUIs include windows, menus, and icons.</span></li>
				</ul>
				
					
					<h4>5. How does the operating system help manage resources such as the processor, memory, storage, hardware, and peripheral devices?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">When the OS allows you to perform more than one task at a time, it is multitasking. To provide for seamless multitasking, the OS controls the timing of the events on which the processor works.</span></li>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">As the OS coordinates the activities of the processor, it uses RAM as a temporary storage area for instructions and data the processor needs. The OS is therefore responsible for coordinating the space allocations in RAM to ensure that there is enough space for the waiting instructions and data. If there isn’t sufficient space in RAM for all the data and instructions, then the OS allocates the least necessary files to temporary storage on the hard drive, called <em>virtual memory</em>.</span></li>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">The OS manages storage by providing a file-management system that keeps track of the names and locations of files and programs.</span></li>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Programs called <em>device drivers</em> facilitate communication between devices attached to the computer and the OS. Device drivers translate the specialized commands of devices to commands that the OS can </span></li>
					</ul>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
			<![CDATA[
				<p class="moreSpacing" style="margin-left:10px;">understand, and vice versa, enabling the OS to communicate with every device in the computer system. Device drivers for common devices are included in the OS software.</p>
				
				<h4>6. How does the operating system interact with application software?</h4>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">All software applications need to interact with the CPU. For programs to work with the CPU, they must contain code that the CPU recognizes.</span></li>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Rather than having the same blocks of code appear in each application, the OS includes the blocks of code to which software applications refer. These blocks of code are called <em>application programming interfaces</em> (APIs).</span></li>
					</ul>	
					
				
					<img src="assets/images/pics/bootsSmall.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:13px;margin-top:19px;" />
				<h2>The Boot Process: Starting Your Computer</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent7 strong">How does the operating system help the computer start up?</span>


			<ul class="dotted TMargin5 clearLeft">
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">When you start your computer, it runs through a special process called the <em>boot process</em>.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">The boot process consists of four basic steps: (1) The basic input/output system (BIOS) is activated when the user powers on the CPU. (2) In the POST check, the BIOS verifies that all attached devices are in place. (3) The OS is loaded into RAM. (4) Configuration and customization settings are checked.</span></li>
			</ul>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="42" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
		<section>
			<![CDATA[
				<img src="assets/images/pics/windowsSmall.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:13px;" />
				<h2>The Windows Interface</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent8 strong">What are the main features of the Windows interface?</span>
			<br/>
				<ul class="dotted">
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">In Windows 8, the Start screen provides your first interaction with the OS and is the first image you see on your monitor once the system has booted up. It provides you with access to your computer’s apps, tools, and commonly used programs.</span></li>
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">The Windows 8 interface is designed for touch screen devices.</span></li>
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Windows 8 apps run full screen and feature commands hidden in app bars.</span></li>
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Non-Windows 8 programs run on the desktop.</span></li>
				</ul>
				
				<img src="assets/images/pics/stackSmall.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:13px;margin-top:19px;" />
				<h2>Organizing Your Computer: File Management</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent9 strong">How does the operating system help me keep my computer organized?</span>

				<ul class="dotted">
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">The OS allows you to organize the contents of your computer in a hierarchical structure of directories that includes files, folders, libraries, and drives.</span></li>
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">File Explorer helps you manage your files and folders by showing the location and contents of every drive, folder, and file on your computer.</span></li>
					<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Creating folders is the key to organizing files because folders keep related documents together.</span></li>
				</ul>
			]]>
			</section>
			<section>
			<![CDATA[
				<ul class="dotted">
					<li><span class="innerLi">Following naming conventions and using proper file extensions are also important aspects of file management.</span></li>
				</ul>
				
				<img src="assets/images/pics/workmanSmall.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:13px;margin-top:19px;" />
				<h2>Utility Programs</h2>
				<span class="prePseudoLi preContent10 strong">&nbsp; What utility programs are included in system software and what do they do?</span>

				<ul class="dotted">
					<li><span class="innerLi">Some utility programs are incorporated into the OS; others are sold as stand-alone off-the-shelf programs.</span></li>
					<li><span class="innerLi">Common Windows utilities include those that enable you to adjust your display, add or remove programs, compress files, clean unnecessary files off your system, check for lost files and errors, restore your system to an earlier setting, back up your files, and check on programs that have stopped running.</span></li>
				</ul>
				
				<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent semibold textBlack">
							Don't forget to use the study aids included in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or on the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://wps.prenhall.com/bp_evans_techinaction_10/','_blank')">Companion Website</span>. And don’t forget the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/index.html','_blank')">Replay Videos</span>.
						</div>
						</div>
					<br>
					<img src="assets/images/layout/techTouchS5.png" class="techTown" onclick="window.open('http://pearsonhighered.com/techtown','_blank')">
			]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="43" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">chapter 5 glossary//</div>
					
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>app bars</span> 193<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>application programming interface (API)</span> 186<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>application software</span> 174<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Authentication</span> 188<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>basic input/output system (BIOS)</span> 187<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>boot process</span> 187<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>charms</span> 194<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>cluster</span> 208<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>command-driven interface</span> 181<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Device Driver</span> 185<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>directory</span> 198<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Disk Cleanup</span> 206<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>disk defragmenting</span> 208<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>distributions (distros)</span> 179<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>error-checking</span> 206<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>event</span> 182<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>extension (file type)</span> 200<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file</span> 198<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file allocation table (FAT)</span> 207<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file compression utility</span> 205<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>File Explorer</span> 198<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>File History</span> 209<br/>
					

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file management</span> 198<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file name</span> 200<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>file path</span> 202<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>folder</span> 198<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>graphical user interface (GUI)</span> 178<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>interrupt</span> 183<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>interrupt handler</span> 183<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>kernel (supervisor program)</span> 188<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>library</span> 198<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Linux</span> 178<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Mac OS</span> 178<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>menu-driven interface</span> 181<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Microsoft account</span> 188<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>multitask</span> 174<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>multiuser OS (network OS)</span> 175<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>operating system (OS)</span> 174<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>paging</span> 184<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>path separator</span> 202<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>pinning</span> 194<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>platform</span> 179<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Plug and Play (PnP)</span> 185<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>power-on self-test (POST)</span> 188<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>preemptive multitasking</span> 183<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>real-time operating system (RTOS)</span> 175<br/>
				<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Recycle Bin</span> 202<br/>				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="44" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Refresh your PC</span> 189<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>registry</span> 188<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>root directory</span> 198<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>sector</span> 208<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>source code</span> 197<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>spooler</span> 183<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Start screen</span> 193<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>swap file (page file)</span> 184<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>system files</span>188<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>System Restore</span> 207<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>system restore point</span> 207<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>system software</span> 174<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>taskbar</span> 195<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Task Manager</span> 207<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>thrashing</span> 184<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>track</span> 208<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>UNIX</span> 176<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>user interface</span> 174<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>utility program</span> 174<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>virtual memory</span> 184<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows</span> 177<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8</span> 177<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8 apps</span> 193<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Windows 8 interface</span> 193<br/>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="45" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<div class="title">making the transition to...next semester//</div>
			<ol>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Organizing Your Files</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Despite all the good advice, you may not have taken the time to organize your files on your computer. On the Start screen, click File Explorer, and select Documents. Then, use the Snipping Tool to show your current file organization. If your system is well organized, explain how you set up your file-management system. If you haven’t used file-management features to organize your documents, develop a plan that outlines how you’ll set up libraries, folders, and subfolders for your files.</span></li>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Deciding on a New Computer</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">You decide it is time to buy a new computer. Decide whether you want a desktop, laptop, tablet, or netbook and then describe how the choice may affect the OS you get.</span></li>
				<ol>
					<li><span class="notStrong">Discuss the advantages and disadvantages of Windows, Mac, and Linux operating systems.</span></li>
					<li><span class="notStrong">Research whether you can use multiple operating systems on a single machine. Why might this be an important feature for you to consider?</span></li>
					<li><span class="notStrong">Research how your smartphone and personal music player might sync with your computer’s OS.</span></li>
					<li><span class="notStrong">Explain which OS would be most useful to you and why.</span></li>
				</ol>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Creating a Backup Plan</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Your computer just shut down unexpectedly, but fortunately, you were able to get it back up and running without any loss of data. However, this was too close of a call, so you decide to back up your precious files once and for all. Research the specific steps you’ll need to take to create a back </span></li>
			
			</ol>

		]]>
	</section>
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<p style="margin-left:15px;">up initially and then maintain a current backup as your files change. Include in your research what stand-alone programs or OS tools you’ll need to use, as well as any hardware devices or accessories you’ll require. Then research the process of creating a disk image. What’s the difference between creating a system backup and a disk image?</p>
			
		<br/>	
			<div class="title">making the transition to...the workplace//</div>
			<ol>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Using a Web-Based OS</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Your new job requires you to collaborate and visit with sales and management teams within the United States as well as globally. Discuss the benefits and disadvantages of using a web-based OS as a means to help you perform your job better.</span></li>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Top-Five Utility Programs</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Create a list of the top-five utilities you feel every computer should have. For each utility, discuss whether it is included in the OS and/or if there are alternatives that can be downloaded for free or that can be purchased as stand-alone programs. Then, for each recommendation, include a review of the utility that has been written in the past year—make sure you document your sources.</span></li>
				<li><span class="innerLi">Accessibility Features</span><br/><span class="innerLi notStrong">Windows offers a lot of great accessibility tools for those needing extra assistance. The vice president of human resources at the company you work for has asked you to research some stand-alone accessibility programs to determine what else, if anything, is available. List software that is available to help those who have special computing needs.</span></li>
			</ol>
		]]>
	</section>
	</page>
	
	<page index="46" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<div class="title">
				team time //
			</div>
			<h3>Choosing the Best OS</h3>
			<h4>Problem</h4>
			<p class="moreSpacing">You’re the owner of a technology consulting firm. Your current assignments include advising several startup clients on their technology requirements. The companies include a fashion design company, a small financial planning company, and an IT networking firm. The companies are holding off on buying anything until they hear from you as to the hardware and software they should purchase. Obviously, one of the critical decisions for each company is the choice of OS.</p>
			<h4>Task</h4>
			<p class="moreSpacing">Recommend the appropriate OS for each company.</p>

			<h4>Process</h4>

			<ol>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Break up into teams that represent the three primary operating systems: Windows, Mac, or Linux. (Additional teams could be assigned to consider smartphone or tablet operating systems.)</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">As a team, research the pros and cons of your OS. What features does it have that would benefit each company? What features does it not have that each company would need? Why would your OS be the appropriate (or inappropriate) choice for each company? Why is your OS better (or worse) than either of the other options?</span></li>
			</ol>

		]]>
	</section>
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			
			<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
			<ol>
				<li class="liHide"></span></li>
				<li class="liHide"></span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Develop a presentation that states your position with regard to your OS. Your presentation should have a recommendation and include facts to back it up.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">As a class, decide which OS would be the best choice for each company.</span></li>
			</ol>
			<h4>Conclusion</h4>
			<p class="moreSpacing">Because the OS is the most critical piece of software in the computer system, the selection should not be taken lightly. The OS that is best for a fashion design agency may not be best for a financial planning firm. An IT networking firm may have different needs altogether. It is important to make sure you consider all aspects of the work environment and the type of work being done to ensure a good fit.</p>
				
			]]>
		</section>
	</page>
	
	<page index="47" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<div class="title">ethics project//</div>
			<h3>Software Piracy</h3>
			<p class="moreSpacing">In this exercise, you’ll research and then role-play a complicated ethical situation. The role you play may or may not match your own personal beliefs, but your research and use of logic will enable you to represent whichever view is assigned. An arbitrator will watch and comment on both sides of the arguments, and together, the team will agree on an ethical solution.</p>
			
			
			<h4>Problem</h4>
			<p class="moreSpacing">Software publishers spend millions of dollars developing new products. Illegal copies of software, including OS software, rob the developers and their shareholders of their rightful profits. In addition, some say that pervasive software piracy, especially in China, could potentially cause job loss for U.S. software companies. However, some people believe that when they buy the software, they have the right to distribute their copies as they like, thus violating the software license agreement they accepted when installing the software.</p>
			
			
			<h4>Research Areas to Consider</h4>
			<span class="psudoUlLi">Software piracy</span>
			<span class="psudoUlLi">Software licensing agreements</span>
			<span class="psudoUlLi">CD piracy</span>
			<span class="psudoUlLi">China’s antipiracy efforts/laws</span>
			
			
		]]>
	</section>
	<section>
		<![CDATA[
			<h4>Process</h4>
			<ol>				
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Divide the class into teams.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Research the areas cited above and devise a scenario in which an individual has been accused of software piracy.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Team members should write a summary that provides background information for their character—for example, representative of a software developer, public consumer of the software, or arbitrator—and that details their character’s behaviors to set the stage for the roleplaying event. Then, team members should create an outline to use during the role-playing event.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Team members should arrange a mutually convenient time to meet for the exchange, using either the collaboration feature of <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or the discussion board feature of your course management software or by meeting in person.</span></li>
				<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="notStrong">Team members should present their case to the class or submit a PowerPoint presentation for review by the rest of the class, along with the summary and resolution they developed.</span></li>
			</ol>
			
			<h4>Conclusion</h4>
			<p class="moreSpacing">As technology becomes ever more prevalent and integrated into our lives, more and more ethical dilemmas will present themselves. Being able to understand and evaluate both sides of the argument, while responding in a personally or socially ethical manner, will be an important skill.</p>
		]]>
	</section>
</page>


	<page index="48" type="full" distinction="chapterStartB">
			<section>
				<!--new image title set up.-->
				<![CDATA[
				<section>
				
				<div class="chapterStartBox">
					<div class="chapterStartDesc" style="padding-top: 32px;">
						Information Technology Ethics</div>
						<div class="chapterStartNumberFocus">Technology <br/>in Focus</div>
				</div>
				<div class="loader"></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="49" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="tocB">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<h2 class="semibold">Technology in Focus: <br/>Information Technology Ethics</h2>
					<hr>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,50)" style="display:inline;">What Is Ethics? </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,50)">pp.221-222</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,51)" style="display:inline;">Personal Ethics </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,51)">pp. 222-225</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,54)" style="display:inline;">Personal Ethics and Your Work Life </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,54)">pp. 225-226</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,55)">Technology and Ethics: </span>
					<span>How One Affects the Other (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,55)">p. 226</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,56)" style="display:inline;">Social Justice: </span>
					<span>Brain Technology: Creating Cyborgs? (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,56)">pp. 227-229</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,59)" style="display:inline;">Intellectual Property: </span>
					<span>International Pirates (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,59)">pp. 230-232</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,62)" style="display:inline;">Privacy: </span>
					<span>Can Employers Peer into YourPersonal Life? <br/>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,62)">pp. 233-235</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,65)" style="display:inline;">E-Commerce: </span>
					<span>E-Commerce: Geolocation: <br/>Who Knows Where You Are? (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,65)">pp. 236-238</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,68)" style="display:inline;">Electronic Communication: </span>
					<span>Does Free Speech Have a Price? <br/>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,68)">pp. 239-241</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div class="BMargin10">
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,71)" style="display:inline;">Computer Abuse: </span>
					<span>Computer Abuse: Cyberbullying: <br/>Who Should Protect Children from Each Other? (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,71)">pp. 242-244</span>)</span>
					</div>
					
					<div>
					<span class="orangeHeading" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,74)" style="display:inline;">Using Computers to Support Ethical Conduct: </span>
					<span>(<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.switchPage(0,74)">p. 245</span>)</span>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					
					<img src="assets/images/figures/5B.jpg">
					
					<div class="loader"></div>
					
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>

	<page index="50" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				
				<div class="BMargin10 strong font_23 font_fff">

					<div class="floatRight height100"
						 style="padding:12px 21px; 
								width:208px;
								background-color:#009ecb">
						Information Technology Ethics</div>
					<div class="height100"
						 style="padding:12px 21px; 
						 		width:122px;
								background-color:#8dc63f;">Technology in Focus</div>
					
				</div>
				<p>The ethical choices we make have a far-reaching impact on our lives. In this Technology in Focus feature, we examine how technology and ethics affect each other. We’ll discuss several key issues related to technology and ethics, including the following:</p>
				<ul class="dotted">
					<li><span class="innerLi">Intellectual property rights</span></li>
					<li><span class="innerLi">Privacy</span></li>
					<li><span class="innerLi">E-commerce</span></li>
					<li><span class="innerLi">Free speech</span></li>
					<li><span class="innerLi">Computer abuse</span></li>
				</ul>
				<p>But first, let’s get started by asking an important question:</p>
				<p>What is ethics?</p>
				
				<br/>
				<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">What Is Ethics?</span>
				<p><span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Ethics</span> is the study of the general nature of morals and of the specific moral choices individuals make. Morals involve conforming to established or accepted ideas of right and wrong (as generally dictated by society) and are usually viewed as being black and white. Ethical issues often involve subtle distinctions, such as the difference between fairness and equity. Ethical principles are the guidelines you use to make decisions each day.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">For example, say you stop to use a photocopier on campus. You discover a copy of the upcoming final exam for your psychology course that your teacher left behind in class. Do you give it back to your professor without looking at the questions? Do you share it with your friends so you can all get good grades on the final? Do you give a copy to your friend who really needs to pass the course in order to prevent losing his or her financial aid?</p>
					<p class="start"><strong>Doesn’t everyone have the same basic ethics?</strong> There are many systems of ethical conduct. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(51,0)">Figure 1</span> lists the five major ethical systems.</p>
				
				<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(50,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_0.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 308px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos">
   				</figcaption></figure>

				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="51" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes leftPadding10 cond">Systems of Ethics</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
						
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(51,0)" style="
							width:400px;
							height:265px;
							background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_1.jpg) #fff no-repeat 6px 28px">
							<span class="strongDHeading font_15" style="margin:6px 0 0 7px"><strong>Figure 1</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:5px;margin-bottom:5px;"><em>(Solomin Andrey/Fotolia; Sergey Galushko/Fotolia; kentoh/Fotolia; Alexmillos/Fotolia; Scanrail/Fotolia)</em>
	   					</figcaption></figure>
   					</div>
					
					<br/>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Aren’t laws meant to guide people’s ethical actions?</strong> Laws are formal, written standards designed to apply to everyone. Laws are enforced by government agencies and interpreted by the courts. However, it’s impossible to pass laws that cover every possible behavior in which humans can engage. Therefore, ethics provide a general set of unwritten guidelines for people to follow.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Is unethical behavior the same as illegal behavior?</strong> Unethical behavior isn’t necessarily illegal. Take the death penalty. In many U.S. states, putting convicted criminals to death for certain crimes is legal. However, many people consider it unethical to execute a human for any reason.</p>
					
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(51,1)" class="readMore"></a>
					<br/>
					
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Which system of ethics works best?</strong> There is no universal agreement on which is the best system of ethics. Most societies use a blend of different  systems. Regardless of the ethical system of the society in which you live, all ethical decisions are greatly influenced by personal ethics.</p>
					<br/>
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Personal Ethics</span>
					<p class="moreSpacing"><strong>What are personal ethics?</strong> Every day you say and do certain things, and each time, you’re making decisions. As you choose your words and actions, you’re following a set of <span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>personal ethics</span>—a set of formal or informal ethical principles you use to make decisions in your life. Some people have a clear, well-defined set of principles they follow. Others’ ethics are inconsistent or are applied differently in different situations. It can be challenging to ad here to your own ethical principles if the consequences of  your decisions might lead to an unhappy result. For example, to get the job of your dreams, should you say on your résumé that you’ve already finished your degree, even though you’re still one credit short? Is this lying? Is such </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="52" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>behavior justified in this setting? After all, you do intend to finish that last credit, and you would work really hard for this company if you were hired. If you tell the truth and state that you haven’t finished college yet, you might be passed over for the position. Making this choice is an ethical decision (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(52,0)">see Figure 2</span>).</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(52,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_2.jpg) no-repeat 0px 38px;
							    height: 405px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 2</span> It would be nice if there were signposts to ethical conduct, but the issues are complex. <em>(Iqoncept/Shutterstock)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start"><strong>How do a person’s ethics develop?</strong> Naturally, your family plays a major role in establishing the values you cherish in your own life, and these might include a cultural bias toward certain ethical positions (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(52,1)">see Figure 3</span>). Your religious affiliation is another major influence on your ethics, because most religions have established codes of ethical conduct. How these sets of ethics interact with the values of the larger culture is often challenging. Issues such as abortion, the death penalty, and war often create conflict between personal ethical systems and the larger society’s established legal-ethical system.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(52,1)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_3.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 316px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 3</span> Many different forces shape your personal ethics. <em>(Noam Armonn/Shutterstock;
AISPIX by Image Source/Shutterstock; Rachel Donahue/iStockphoto; Rob Marmion/Shutterstock)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="53" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">As you mature, your life experiences also affect your personal ethics. Does the behavior you see around you make sense within the ethical principles that your family,  your church, or your first-grade teacher taught you? Has your experience led you to abandon some ethical rules and adopt others? Have you modified how and when you apply these laws of conduct depending on what’s at stake?</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>What if I’m not sure what my personal ethics are?</strong> When you have a clear idea of what values are important to you, it may be easier to handle situations in your life that demand ethical action. Follow these steps to help define a list of personal values:</p>
					<ol>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi"><strong>Describe yourself.</strong> Write down words that describe who you are, based on how others view you. Would a friend describe you as honest, or helpful, or kind? These keywords will give you a hint as to the values and behaviors that are important to you.</span></li>
						<li class="moreSpacing"><span class="innerLi"><strong>List the key principles you believe in.</strong> Make a list of the key principles that influence your decisions. For example, would you be comfortable working in a lab that used animals for medical research? If not, is it because you value protecting any living being? How important is it to you that you never tell a lie? Or do you feel it is kind to lie in some situations? List the key ideas you believe to be important in conducting your life. Do you always behave this way, or are you “flexible”? Are there situations in which your answers might change (say, if the medical research was to cure cancer or the lie was to protect someone’s feelings)?</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><strong>Identify external influences.</strong> Where did your key principles come <br/>from—your parents? Your friends? Spiritual advisors? Television and movies? You may want to question some of your beliefs once you actually identify where they came from.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><strong>Consider “why.”</strong> After writing down your beliefs, think about <em>why</em> you believe them. Have you accepted them without investigation? Do they stand up in the context of your real-world experiences?</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><strong>Prepare a statement of values.</strong> Distill what you have written into a short statement. By having a well-defined statement of the values you hold most important in your own life, which you can refer to in times of challenge, it will be easier for you to make ethical decisions.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p class="start"><strong>What are the benefits to ethical living?</strong> Society has established its own set of rules of conduct in the form of laws. Ignoring or being inconsistent in following these rules can have an immediate impact. And more and more research is showing the health benefits of ethical living. When your day-to-day decisions are in conflict with your ethical principles, you often develop stress and anger.</p>
					<p class="start">Perhaps even happiness itself is a result of living ethically (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(54,0)">see Figure 4</span>). <span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Positive psychology</span> is a new focus in the field of psychology. Pioneered by Dr. Martin Seligman of the University of Pennsylvania, this field works to discover the <em>causes</em> of happiness instead of addressing the treatment of mental dysfunctions. Dr. Seligman’s research has shown that by  identifying your personal strengths and values and then aligning your life so that you can apply them every day you can be happier (and suffer less </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="54" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>depression)—an effect equivalent to that of antidepressant medication and therapy. Thus, finding a way to identify and then apply your ethics and values to your daily life can impact your health and happiness.</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Personal Ethics and Your Work Life</span>
					<p><strong>How do employers affect personal ethics?</strong> You may have a set of personal ethics that guide your behavior, but do your ethics change when you go to work? Of course, your employer expects you to follow the rules of conduct established for the business. However, this doesn’t mean you need to blindly follow corporate practices that you feel are unethical or detrimental to society (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(54,1)">see Figure 5</span>).</span></p>
					<p class="start"><strong>If you spot unethical behavior at your company, what do you do?</strong> <span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Whistle-blowers</span> are people who report businesses to regulatory agencies for committing illegal acts or who expose unethical (but still legal) </p>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(54,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_4.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 188px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 4</span> The field of positive psychology shows that living and working ethically affects your happiness. <em>(Yuri Arcurs/Shutterstock; Yuri Arcurs/Shutterstock)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				
				
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(54,1)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_5.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 320px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 5</span> How should you respond if you see people in authority at the company’s work behaving unethically? <em>(Shapiro Mike/CSL, CartoonStock Ltd)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				<br/>
				
					<p>acts committed by their employers by publicizing unethical behavior through various media outlets. The Sarbanes–Oxley Act of 2002 requires companies to provide mechanisms for employees and third parties to report complaints, including ethics violations, anonymously. In addition, many businesses are using their websites to allow whistle-blowers to report wrongdoing anonymously, replacing previously used e-mail and telephone hotline  systems, which did not shield employees from being identified. With an online system, it’s easier for a company to sort and classify complaints and designate them for appropriate action.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="55" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>Should your employer have control over your conduct outside of the office?</strong> Do behavior, integrity, and honesty off the job relate to job performance? They might. But even if they don’t, from your employer’s perspective, your actions could reflect poorly on your employer. Consider the Transportation Security Administration (TSA) officer who was fired from his job at Chicago’s O’Hare airport for making racist remarks about certain types of passengers on his Facebook page. He claimed his remarks were just an exercise of his First Amendment right to free speech. Obviously, his TSA supervisors thought his comments reflected poorly on the agency. Therefore, although your ethics might dictate one mode of behavior, you need to consider how your employer might view your actions.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><strong>How does making ethical choices in a business setting differ from making personal ethical choices?</strong> Most personal ethical decisions involve few people. However, before making an ethical choice for a business, you need to consider the effect your choice will have on all of the business’s stakeholders. <span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Stakeholders</span> are those people or entities who are affected by the operations of a business. Typical business stakeholders include customers, suppliers, employees, investors (shareholders), financial lenders, and society at large.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<a onclick="compTia.togglePopup(55,0)" class="readMore"></a>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong">Technology and Ethics: How One Affects the Other</span>
					<p>Because technology moves faster than rules can be formulated to govern it, how technology is used is often left up to the individual and the guidance of his or her personal ethics. In the rest of this Technology in Focus feature, we explore situations in which ethics and technology affect each other: social justice (brain technology), intellectual property (international piracy), privacy (personal privacy and technology), e-commerce (geolocation), electronic communication (free speech), and computer abuse (cyberbullying).</p>
					<p class="start">Ethical considerations are never clear-cut. They’re complex, and reasonable people can have different, yet equally valid, views. We present alternative viewpoints in each setting for you to consider and discuss. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(55,1)">Figure 6</span> summarizes the issues we’ll be discussing.</p>
					
					<br/>
					<div class="smallHeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes headingOrangeFullheight leftPadding10 cond">Ethics in Computing</div>
					<div class="orangeWrap">
						
						<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(55,1)" style="
							width:400px;
							height:210px;
							background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_6.jpg) #fff no-repeat 40px 28px">
							<span class="strongDHeading font_15" style="margin:6px 0 0 7px"><strong>Figure 6</strong> Click to reveal the table</span>
							<figcaption class="bottomPos" style="margin-left:5px;margin-bottom:5px;">
	   					</figcaption></figure>
   					</div>
					
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="56" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">Social Justice</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Brain Technology: Creating Cyborgs?</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p class="moreSpacing">A <span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>cyborg</span>, short for “cybernetic organism,” is an entity that contains both biological and artificial (e.g., electronic, mechanical, or robotic) components. How close are we to creating cyborgs in your lifetime? Perhaps closer than you think. Consider the sophisticated artificial limbs already available, the installation of which could technically classify an individual as a cyborg.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">But most people aren’t getting upset about prosthetic limbs. Altering the human brain raises eyebrows, though. Technological advances are being applied to the field of brain research at an increasing rate. Human brain and neurological tissue have a limited ability to regenerate and repair themselves, leading to severe handicaps after injuries or diseases that affect the brain and central nervous system, such as Parkinson’s disease. Research is proceeding in three main areas:</p>
					<ol>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Brain-computer interfaces (BCIs)</span>: BCIs work to establish a direct communication pathway between the brain and external devices, such as robotic limbs, computers, and wheelchairs, allowing thought to direct or control the device.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Neurostimulation</span>: Techniques such as deep brain stimulation involve the transplantation of devices that transmit electrical impulses to the brain for treating movement disorders like Parkinson’s disease as well as chronic pain. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) is a noninvasive technique for changing brain activity by exposing it to magnetic fields and is used in treating migraines, strokes, and Parkinson’s disease.</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi"><span class="strongDBlue"  glossary>Neural stem cells</span>: Research is underway to determine how neural stem cells respond during strokes, multiple sclerosis, and Parkinson’s disease and other neurological disorders. The goal is to develop effective therapies by producing or enhancing neural stem cells to make them more effective in resisting adverse events.</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<p>Outcomes of these fields of research have been focused on the treatment of severe medical conditions. However, military organizations are interested in applying BCIs to control fighter aircraft, drones, and other weapons systems. The gaming industry is also interested in BCI technology, since it could provide the capability for thought-controlled video games. And neurostimulation and neural stem cell research hold the potential for not just treating illnesses but possibly enhancing human brain function to allow humans to progress beyond their normal brain potential.</p>
					<p class="start">So how should technology be allowed to affect human brain function (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(57,0)">Figure 7</span>)? If we can create a “smarter” or “more athletic” human, should we do so? Where do we draw the line between humans and machines? </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>	
		
		<page index="57" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>If a smart bomb (a bomb guided by computer technology) zeroes in on a military target and destroys it, a “machine” is responsible for the carnage. But if the bomb is guided by a human being connected to it through a BCI, who bears the responsibility? Where do we separate the person from the machine if we reach this point?</p>
					
				<br/>
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="notStrong">Who is responsible for controlling the direction and outcomes of brain technology research?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">If a missile controlled by a person connected to a weapons system through a BCI accidently destroys a civilian target, who is responsible…human or machine?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">When do the benefits of medical research outweigh the risks of the technology being used in illegal, evil, or immoral ways?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Does enhancing our brain capabilities with technology make us less human?</span></li>
					</ol>	
					
				<br/>
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.ninds.nih.gov/research/tbi/index.htm','_blank')">Traumatic Brain Injury Research (TBI)</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://neurosurgery.ucla.edu/body.cfm?id=621','_blank')">Brain Injury Research Center (BIRC)</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.sport.co.uk/nfl/new-research-program-aims-to-combat-brain-injuries/3841491/','_blank')">New Research Program Aims To Combat Brain Injuries</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(57,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_7.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 430px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 7</span> What boundaries should there be on the enhancement of the human brain using technology? <em>(Vladgrin/Fotolia)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="58" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Brain Technology Research Will Provide Medical “Miracles”</h4>
					
					<p>Advocates of brain technology research argue that it will allow for the treatment of currently untreatable catastrophic illnesses and injuries, thus alleviating human suffering.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Society will dictate what the acceptable uses of brain technology are, just as they have done for other types of advancements (such as atomic energy).</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Technology is not responsible for the actions or the consequences of the actions of people. Governments can put controls in place to limit the uses of brain technology just as the United States and Russia have done with strategic arms limitation agreements for nuclear weapons.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Technology has provided new tools that allow us to exercise unprecedented control over neurological systems. Ignoring these areas of research provides no relief for afflicted individuals.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Brain Technology Will Radically Change Society if It Is Misused</h4>
					
					<p>Critics maintain that the directions brain research will take cannot be adequately controlled and that creating humans with “enhanced” capabilities poses too much of a danger to society.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">No one can ultimately prevent or control the results of brain technology research from being used for military purposes.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">If technology is used irresponsibly, it might create strife between the groups that have access to enhanced brain technology and those who do not.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Integrating technology into human beings and altering their body chemistry essentially destroys what it means to be “human.”</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="59" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">Intellectual Property</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">International Pirates</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p class="moreSpacing">Intellectual property (such as music, writing, and software) is protected by copyright law. But there have been challenges in enforcing these standards in other countries. What happens to “fair trade” if some countries refuse to enforce copyright laws? How should the trade partners of these countries respond?</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing"><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://NationMaster.com','_blank')">NationMaster.com</span> estimated that in 2011, 82% of China’s computers ran on pirated software. For comparison, the estimated piracy levels in the United States and Sweden are 20% and 25%, respectively. This discrepancy means that businesses in China don’t have to budget for operating system or productivity software, which gives them an advantage in the international marketplace. Although some companies, like Microsoft, continue to do business in China despite the high levels of piracy, smaller companies often can’t survive there. For example, Tom Adams, chief executive of Rosetta Stone, pulled his company and its language training software products out of China. He describes China as a “kleptocratic society” and worries about the amount of theft of his software in that environment.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">In fact, the chief executives of 12 major software companies—Microsoft, Adobe, Autodesk, Symantec, and others—have lobbied the U.S. administration and lawmakers to continue to put pressure on China to crack down on illegal copying (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(60,0)">see Figure 8</span>). With a potential market of more than one billion people, and an increasing number of technologically hungry purchasers, companies dread the idea of missing out on the Chinese market. In 2010, talks between the U.S. and China resulted in promises by the Chinese government of stricter enforcement of antipiracy laws and implementation of aggressive antipiracy media campaigns. But to date, software companies have failed to see any significant increases in software sales in China, indicating the Chinese government’s actions have been ineffective.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">It is not just China that has weakly enforced copyright laws. Countries such as Armenia, Bangladesh, Yemen, Libya, and Vietnam all have higher rates of piracy than China. The Business Software Alliance estimates the monetary losses from software piracy at more than $63 billion worldwide for 2011, although there is debate around the exact value.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Most people have had the opportunity to participate in the piracy of copyrighted materials through illegal peer-to peer sharing and the use of torrents. This behavior is now multiplied to the level of nations, and the consequences are still being explored.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="60" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="notStrong">Should a government be penalized for failing to actively enforce the laws it has enacted within its own country? If so, what should the penalties be, and how should they be enforced?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Does each government have the right to make its own decision on a stand against piracy?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">How can other countries respond to international piracy?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Does individual piracy have any connection to the enforcement of copyright laws on an international level?</span></li>
					</ol>
					
				<br/>
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.computerweekly.com/news/2240175845/Software-piracy-international-in-scope-says-Fast','_blank')">Software piracy international in scope, says Fast</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://portal.bsa.org/globalpiracy2011/downloads/study_pdf/2011_BSA_Piracy_Study-Standard.pdf','_blank')">2011 BSA Global Software Piracy Study</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/movies/moviesnow/la-et-mn-sxsw-2013-megaupload-founder-kim-dotcom-speaks-20130311,0,6911740.story','_blank')">SXSW 2013: Megaupload chief Kim Dotcom vows never to go to prison</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(60,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_8.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 315px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 8</span> A crackdown on pirated media in China underscores that issues of intellectual property play an important role in international trade. <em>(MARK/epa/Corbis)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="61" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">International Copyright Protections Need to Be Vigorously Enforced</h4>
					
					<p>Artists and software developers depend on the integrity of the protection of intellectual property, both within the United States and internationally, to make a fair profit on their work.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">If other countries do not fight piracy, artists and developers have a disadvantage in the marketplace.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">By allowing massive piracy, some countries are stealing from others.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Every country needs to have a common understanding and enforcement of intellectual property laws for trade to be fair and beneficial to everyone.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Global Business Demands Understanding Other Cultures</h4>
					
					<p>Most countries have laws on their books regarding intellectual property. It is not the job of the United States to tell a foreign government how to conduct its internal affairs.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">The existing laws on intellectual property have worked to serve the interests of these countries. If U.S. companies do not want to sell to the billion-person market of China, then that is their choice.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Piracy exists within the United States, so it is hypocritical to be chastising foreign governments for software piracy.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Companies can pursue restitution for piracy through the foreign court systems.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="62" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">Privacy</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Can Employers Peer into Your Personal Life?</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p>Like respect and dignity, privacy is a basic human right. What, exactly, is privacy? Simply stated, privacy is the right to be left alone to do as one pleases. The idea of privacy is often associated with hiding something (a behavior, a relationship, or a secret). However, privacy really means not being required to explain your behavior to others. But social media sites such as Facebook are inherently about sharing information with others. Does this mean there is no such thing as personal privacy (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(63,0)">see Figure 9</span>) on social media sites?</p>
					<p class="start">Facebook and other social media allow you to set privacy filters on your personal information. You can choose to share information publically, share it with just with your friends, or keep it totally private. Employers now routinely check social media sites to gather publically shared information on prospective employees. But recently, many government agencies, such as police departments and some private employers, have been asking job seekers for access to their <em>private</em> Facebook information, as well.</p>
					<p class="start">Sometimes this is blatant, such as what happened to a Maryland corrections officer who was seeking reinstatement. During an interview, he was asked for his Facebook password. The interviewer then proceeded to log on to his account, purportedly to see if he had any gang affiliations.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Although this might seem like a legitimate reason for a prison system to screen candidates, the U.S. Senate disagrees. In May 2012, legislators proposed the Password Protection Act to prevent employers from demanding passwords to private sites from employees. That same month, Maryland became the first state to enact a law that prohibits employers from asking current and prospective employees for their access codes to social networking sites. Employers are currently prohibited from asking prospective employees information related to their gender, race, religion, age, and sexual orientation, but this information is often found in social media site profiles. Facebook has also warned employers against this practice, as it violates the terms-of-use agreement for the site.</p>
					<p class="start">Often, however, employer research is more subtle. For example, employers often encourage prospective employees to “friend” them on Facebook. Although these company profiles are set up specifically so that prospective employees can learn information about the company, once prospective employees “friend” the company, company representatives can often see more information about these would-be employees than what is visible in their public profile.</p>
					<p class="start">The American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) and other privacy advocates have begun voicing opposition to these practices, citing erosion of personal privacy rights. You wouldn’t give a prospective employer the keys to your house so they could poke around in your personal life. But doesn’t it have almost the same effect if you let them see your private information in a social media profile?</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="63" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Employers—especially small businesses—argue that hiring decisions are so critical that they need to gather as much information as possible and that people voluntarily surrendering passwords is not a violation of prospective employees’ rights. But critics of these practices say that job seekers may feel powerless to refuse these invasions of their privacy for fear they’ll be turned down for a job.</p>
					<p class="start">The control and privacy of information will continue to be a fine balancing act for the foreseeable future, with em ployers trying to gather intelligence while appeasing the concerns of privacy advocates. Leaving a trail of electronic breadcrumbs is to a certain extent inevitable. But cleaning up or hiding your “trail” is still important to many users, not because they’re trying to hide something but because they value their basic right to privacy.</p>
					
				<br/>
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="notStrong">Should you be able to decide exactly what information on a social networking site you share with others? Would you be willing to pay for this privilege?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Do you know what your privacy settings are on the social media sites you use? Is there any information being shared publicly that you weren’t aware was being shared?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Should employers be allowed to ask prospective employees for their passwords to social media sites? Is this practice still legal in the United States?</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">Is there any information on sites you use that you want to restrict potential employers from seeing? Do these sites allow you to restrict the information you wish to protect?</span></li>
					</ol>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('https://www.privacyrights.org/fs/fs7-work.htm','_blank')">Workplace Privacy and Employee Monitoring</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.aclu.org/technology-and-liberty/workplace-privacy','_blank')">Workplace Privacy</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.fdic.gov/about/privacy/responsibilities.html','_blank')">FDIC Employee Privacy Act Responsibilities</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(63,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_9.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 285px;margin-right:-2px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 9</span> What information are you sharing on Facebook and with whom? <br/><em>(Copyright © 2011 by Facebook Inc.)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="64" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Employers Have No Right to Job Seekers’ Private Social Media Information</h4>
					
					<p>The advocates of protecting privacy in the United States argue that the right to privacy is a basic human right that should be afforded to everyone. Personal privacy concerns should outweigh the business needs of a corporation.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Social media sites have an inherent duty to protect the data of their users.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">If employers are screening private information, they might misuse or lose control of the data or violate current employment law.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Default privacy settings on social media sites should all be opt-in, allowing users the ultimate control over who views their data.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Employers Are Entitled to Gather Personal Information Directly Related to Employment</h4>
					
					<p>Advocates for unrestricted sharing of information feel that business concerns outweigh privacy concerns. Businesses should have the right to screen all data in social media sites to determine the character and fitness of employment candidates.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Volunteering password information does not violate an individual’s right to privacy.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Users can make their own privacy decisions and choose not to post or share sensitive information (opt out).</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">In the digital age, loss of a certain amount of privacy is inevitable.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="65" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">E-Commerce</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Geolocation: Who Knows Where You Are?</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p class="moreSpacing">“Where are you?” is the burning social-networking question these days, and your smartphone probably has the answer. The technology is called geolocation (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(66,0)">see Figure 10</span>), and smartphones have a GPS chip that can calculate your exact position. Services such as Foursquare, Gowalla, Brightkite, and Loopt are all hoping you’ll use their geolocation services to find your friends or let your friends find you. Through the apps, you can receive recommendations of places to visit or things to do nearby. Businesses are using geolocation apps to promote their products and offer rewards for “check-ins” to help drive customers to their location.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">When you sign up on Foursquare and other social media sites, you can choose what information is publically available, such as your location or your Facebook profile. Foursquare is designed to make it convenient to see where your friends are and who’s in the venue where you’re currently “checked in.” You might be cautious and choose to make personal and location information only accessible to your friends…or it might all be public. But what if another app you know nothing about is using your information in a way never intended by the social media sites you joined?</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Consider the controversy that erupted around the iPhone app “Girls Around Me.” The app used data from Foursquare to create a local map that showed how many individuals logged into Foursquare were in geographic locations near you. It also allowed you to view Facebook profiles of people “around you” if they had their Facebook profiles linked to their Foursquare account. The app developer, i-Free, promoted the app as a tool to see what was happening in a wider range of locations instead of just one at a time. It viewed its tool as a way to let users identify “hot spots” of activity that had a lot of people checked in. i-Free said the app was just like looking in the window of a location to see how crowded it was, but it was also aggregating publically available information provided by other social media services.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Critics of the app decried it as a tool for stalkers that provided more information than people could gain by glancing in a window. They argued that the app violated the privacy of Foursquare users because they had no knowledge of how the Girls Around Me app was using their information. Many detractors argued that just because you agreed to make certain information public on Foursquare doesn’t mean you automatically agree to the use of that same information on other apps that might function in a different (and perhaps objectionable) way. Foursquare claimed that i-Free was violating the terms of its information-sharing agreement and changed its application programming interfaces (APIs) to effectively disable the Girls Around Me app. i-Free removed the app from the App Store for retooling.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="66" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start moreSpacing">But the question remains, when you leave your home and announce your constant whereabouts through tweets and check-ins, do you lose your privacy in exchange for “fun” and “convenience”? Although you can set certain levels of privacy in the apps, there is still the potential for someone with bad intentions (stalkers, robbers) to follow your updates. And do you really know how the information you make public will be used by other app creators? In addition to opening yourself up to potential stalking or robbery, geolocation devices also can track the activities you might not want publicized, and that once documented can later be used against you.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">It wasn’t long ago that we were concerned about using our real names online, but now we’re comfortable with sharing our exact location in a very public way. As Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg said, “People have really gotten comfortable not only sharing more information and different kinds, but more openly and with more people.” But does such acceptance justify neglecting to maintain certain levels of privacy? Again, it seems that technology has moved more quickly than society can address the potential risks and dangers.</p>
					
					<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="notStrong">Do the benefits of geolocation outweigh the risks?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">What other devices besides cell phones track and record our movements/locations as digital records?</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"></span></li>
						<li class="liHide"></span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">How have social networks increased the risks of geolocation?</span></li>
						<li><span class="notStrong">What risks do geolocation pose for college students? How can users mitigate those risks?</span></li>
					</ol>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.pcworld.com/article/192803/geolo.html','_blank')">Geolocation 101: How It Works, the Apps, and Your Privacy</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.isaca.org/Groups/Professional-English/wireless/GroupDocuments/Geolocation_WP.pdf','_blank')">Geolocation: Risk, Issues and Strategies</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://empb.org/2013/01/on-geolocation-and-ethics/','_blank')">On Geolocation and Ethics</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(66,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_10.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 285px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 10</span> Geolocation applications help you find cool places and businesses. But who do you want to find you with geolocation? <em>(Cseke Timea/Fotolia)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="67" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Geolocation Devices Do Not Threaten Privacy</h4>
					
					<p>The advocates of using geolocation devices with minimal concern for threatened privacy are those who believe the social norm has shifted and people have become comfortable with sharing more information.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Businesses are adopting geolocation apps as a part of their social media strategy in order to drive customers to their business. They would lose revenue if such activities ceased.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">As the devices and apps become better and more precise, they may become useful as public safety and news-gathering devices.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Society may need to reevaluate its views about how much privacy is needed in people’s digital lives, as well as the degree of an individual’s responsibility for making sensible decisions about sharing information through the Internet.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Geolocation Devices Are a Threat to Privacy</h4>
					
					<p>The advocates for tighter privacy controls and awareness campaigns about the potential risks of using geolocation devices suggest that the threats are too big to ignore. Society has become too complacent with privacy issues.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Privacy settings on apps and GPS devices should be more restrictive in order to avoid broadcasting one’s location and risking personal assault.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Laws and regulations will need to be created as to the use and distribution of digital location information.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Consumers need to be educated about geolocation and the ways it can affect them so that they are able to make informed choices.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="68" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">Electronic Communication</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Does Free Speech Have a Price?</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p>In early 2006, when Google launched its search engine services in China, it conceded to the Chinese government’s demands that it self-censor its search engine, restricting search results for sensitive information such as the details of the Tiananmen Square protests and of human rights groups. This decision prompted much discussion, with some condemning Google’s decision for putting business profits over what they saw as basic human rights (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(69,0)">see Figure 11</span>). Google justified its actions by stating that a company must operate within the rules of the market in which it operates and that the benefits of increased access to information for people in China “outweighed our discomfort in agreeing to censor some results.” And, compared with search results from Baidu.com, the leading Chinese search engine, Google was not censoring all information.</p>
					<p class="start">However, in 2010, Google announced that it was no longer willing to censor search results and moved the site to Hong Kong, where it hoped there would be less censorship. The departure was a reaction to a sophisticated, targeted cyberattack that Google believes was done to gather information on Chinese human rights activists. At that time, Google had about a 35% market share.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">Microsoft had only a 1% share of the market, so it decided to partner with Baidu.com to provide English-language search results for China’s largest search engine. Microsoft stated it would agree to abide by Chinese censorship laws (so search terms like <em>freedom</em> and <em>democracy</em> deliver filtered results), thereby respecting the laws of the countries where it operates. However, before honoring any censor requests, Microsoft insisted that Chinese authorities made legally binding requests in writing.</p>
					<p class="start">So how did it all work out? As of the third quarter of 2011, Google’s market share has dropped to 18% in China, whereas Baidu.com has increased its market share to 78%. So far, Microsoft’s decision to keep censoring its searches appears to have paid off…at least from a monetary perspective. But is the financial result more important than the social implications of their behavior?</p>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Is there anything else that Google could do that would have a major impact on China’s censorship laws?</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Has Microsoft’s compliance with censorship laws furthered the Chinese government’s cooperation in combating software piracy in China? Are Microsoft’s financial incentives even deeper than just Internet market share?</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="68" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<ol class="strong">
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li class="liHide"><span></span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Can the U.S. government compel technology companies to take a firmer stance on free speech in China and elsewhere by instituting criminal charges if U.S. companies do not take reasonable steps to protect human rights?</span></li>
					</ol>
					
				<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://articles.cnn.com/2010-01-13/tech/google.china.analysis_1_google-network-thousands-of-search-terms-search-engine?_s=PM:TECH','_blank')">Google vs. China: Free speech, finances or both?</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.cfr.org/china/media-censorship-china/p11515','_blank')">Media Censorship in China</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.google.com/publicpolicy/issues/freedom-of-expression.html','_blank')">Freedom of expression</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(68,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_11.jpg) no-repeat 50px 0;
							    height: 460px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 11</span> Is free speech possible in countries (such as China) where information availability is restricted by law? <em>(Kentoh/Shutterstock)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="70" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">U.S. Companies Should Comply with Local Laws in Foreign Countries</h4>
					
					<p>Those in favor of Microsoft’s actions to remain in China feel that if a company chooses to operate in a foreign country, it knows the local laws and should be prepared to work within those laws as it does business. It is not the place of a company to try to change laws of foreign countries.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Microsoft conducts businesses in other countries that have censorship laws, so why not participate in China?</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Working in China does not mean a company supports all of China’s policies.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Microsoft’s presence continues to advance the progress the Chinese government is making toward democracy. U.S. companies can ethically stay in China if they make an effort to improve human rights there. U.S. companies operating in China should agree on guidelines that respect human rights.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">A U.S. company’s presence has no impact on reform—reform must come from within.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">U.S. Companies Should Put What Is Right Ahead of What Is Financially Expedient</h4>
					
					<p>Those in favor of Google’s actions believe that international corporations should begin to take a firm stance against governments that do not promote basic human rights.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">China will never change unless there are financial and political incentives to do so. Google’s departure helps pressure the Chinese government.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Google’s withdrawal from China threatens the viability of many advertising resellers in China. Will this added pressure help or hinder human rights efforts?</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Google’s decision to leave helps put pressure on China’s government to play by global standards. China cannot expect to compete in the global marketplace while refusing to have a global exchange of ideas.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="71" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="HeadingMultiGreen">Computer Abuse</div>
					
					<h2 class="blueHeading">Cyberbullying: Who Should Protect Children from Each Other?</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin">Summary of the Issue</h4>
					
					<p>Cyberbullying is just like normal bullying, but it involves the use of digital technologies such as the Internet, cell phones, or video (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(72,0)">see Figure 12</span>). There are many types of cyberbullying, some of which might result in criminal charges depending on the type of incident:</p>
					
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Bombarding a victim with harassing instant messages or text messages</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Stealing a password and then using the victim’s account to embarrass the victim by sending harassing, threatening, or lewd messages while pretending to be the victim</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Spreading rumors or lies on social networking sites</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Posting embarrassing photos or videos on the web (such as candid nude shots taken in a locker room)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Infecting the victim’s computer with malware, usually to spy on the victim</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="start">The effects of cyberbullying can be devastating. Infamous cases include Alexis Pilkington, who at 17 committed suicide after being repeatedly taunted on social networking sites, and Tyler Clementi, a Rutgers freshman who committed suicide after his roommate showed fellow students videos of him having sex.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start lessSpacing">Signs that a child is a victim of cyberbullying are often the same as the signs of depression. A child may:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Suddenly lose interest in normal activities</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Be reluctant to go to school</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Lose his or her appetite</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Have trouble sleeping</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Appear upset after using the Internet</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Experience unusual mood swings (such as bursting into tears for no apparent reason)</span></li>
					</ul>
					<p class="start lessSpacing">Signs that a child might be perpetrating cyberbullying include the following:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Using the Internet excessively</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Sending large volumes of text messages</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Clearing the computer screen when others enter a room</span></li>
						<li class="lessSpacing"><span class="innerLi">Conducting clandestine Internet activities (refusal to say what he or she is doing)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<p class="lessSpacing">Vigilance over children’s online activities is obviously key to spotting both victims and perpetrators of cyberbullying.</p>
					<p class="start lessSpacing">But who is responsible for monitoring children? Parents obviously need to protect their children, but bullying usually doesn’t happen until children are exposed to other children, such as in school. So should teachers shoulder the responsibility for detecting, reporting, and mitigating cyberbullying? Children often spend more time in school during the day than under the supervision of their parents. But cyberbullying activities don’t </p>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="72" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>just take place in school. Most children have access to the Internet at home and can carry on campaigns of terror from their bedrooms.</p>
					<p class="start">There is currently no federal law prohibiting cyberbullying, but the recently passed law against cyberstalking may cover this area. According to the Cyberbullying Research Center (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://cyberbullying.us','_blank')">cyberbullying.us</span>), as of April 2012, 49 states had antibullying laws on the books. However, only 40 state laws cover electronic harassment, and a mere 14 state laws cover cyberbullying. Many legislatures are reluctant to pass laws that instruct parents on how to raise their children because this tends to raise issues about personal freedom. Therefore, anti-cyberbullying laws tend to place the burden of detection on the schools. For instance, the Massachusetts law requires schools to provide age-appropriate education on bullying to students, to train school employees in detection and prevention of bullying, and to have plans developed for detecting and reporting bullying.</p>
					
					<br/>	
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Questions to Think About and Research</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">What level of responsibility should school employees have for protecting children from cyberbullying?</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">Should there be federal laws that make cyberbullying a crime? If so, how would these laws be enforced?</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi notStrong">What types of education for children would be beneficial in preventing cyberbullying? When should these programs begin, and how often should children be required to participate?</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Research Suggestions</span>
					<ol class="strong">
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.stopbullying.gov/cyberbullying/index.html','_blank')">stopbullying.gov</span></li>
						<li><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.stopcyberbullying.org/index2.html','_blank')">Like Stopcyberbullying on Facebook</span></li>
					</ol>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(72,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_12.jpg) no-repeat 55px 0;
							    height: 445px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 12</span> Cyberbullying involves the use of digital technologies both to bully and to broadcast acts of bullying. <em>(Rawdon Wyatt/Alamy)</em>
   				</figcaption></figure>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="73" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>POINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Parents Must Protect Their Children from Cyberbullying</h4>
					
					<p>Proponents of parental responsibility for detecting and preventing cyberbullying feel that it’s a personal behavior issue. Individuals are responsible for their own behavior as long as it doesn’t harm others. Parents should be allowed to educate their children according to their own standards of behavior and preferences in terms of moral behavior (such as religion).</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Parents are ultimately responsible for protecting their children.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Bullying is a personal behavior issue, and all decisions regarding personal freedom and behavior should be made by parents.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Because educating children about bullying is key to preventing it, the content of such training needs to be controlled by parents.</span></li>
					</ol>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<h2>COUNTERPOINT</h2>
					<h4 class="noTMargin noBMargin" style="color:#01af3e;">Schools Must Bear the Responsibility for Protecting Students from Cyberbullying</h4>
					
					<p>Cyberbullying affects society because it can severely damage an individual’s self-esteem. Cyberbullying is similar to other hate crimes and should enlist public officials (such as educators) in enforcement of the laws.</p>
					<ol style="color:#01af3e;">
						<li><span style="color:black;">Parents do not supervise their children 24/7 and therefore require help from other responsible adults to protect their children.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Parents need to be assured that publicly funded institutions such as schools and libraries are “safe havens” where their children will not be exposed to malicious activities.</span></li>
						<li><span style="color:black;">Educators have better resources than most parents for teaching children about the serious effects of cyberbullying.</span></li>
					</ol>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="74" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<span class="orangeHeading normalFontFamily strong font_16">Using Computers to Support Ethical Conduct</span>
					<p class="moreSpacing">Although there are many opportunities to use computers and the Internet unethically, we can also use technology to support ethical conduct. For example, many charitable organizations use the Internet and other technology tools for fundraising. When tornados struck in Texas in April 2012, the Salvation Army (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(74,0)">see Figure 13</span>) and other charities received many pledges via their websites.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">And, as we discussed in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.generatePages(1)">Chapter 1</span>, the web is also a tool for organizing aid to areas in crisis. When a major earthquake struck Haiti in 2010, Ushahidi allowed organizations and individuals conducting relief efforts to collect and disseminate the latest information on victims and aid efforts.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">More recently, after a devastating tornado hit Joplin, Missouri, in May 2011, folks used the Red Cross website and Facebook to locate friends and family members. The level of personal interaction the web supports and the speed at which information can be exchanged are allowing computer technology to support ethical conduct in powerful new ways.</p>
					<p class="start moreSpacing">Throughout your life, you’ll encounter many ethical challenges relating to information technology. Your personal ethics—combined with the ethical guidelines your company provides and the general ethical environment of society—will guide your decisions.</p>
				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<p class="start">For further information on ethics, check out the following websites:</p>
					<ul class="dotted">
						<li><span class="innerLi">Ethics in Computing (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://ethics.csc.ncsu.edu','_blank')">ethics.csc.ncsu.edu</span>)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">The Center for Ethics in Science and Technology (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://ethicscenter.net','_blank')">ethicscenter.net</span>)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Business Ethics: The Magazine of Corporate Responsibility (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://business-ethics.com','_blank')">business-ethics.com</span>)</span></li>
						<li><span class="innerLi">Council for Ethical Leadership at Capital University (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://businessethics.org','_blank')">businessethics.org</span>)</span></li>
					</ul>
					
					<br/>
					<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(74,0)"
						style="background:url(assets/images/figures/fig5b_13.jpg) no-repeat 0px 0;
							    height: 275px;
								margin-top: 0px;">
						<figcaption class="bottomPos"><span>Figure 13</span> Technology helps charities solicit donations.
   				</figcaption></figure>	
				
						<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent">

							<strong>Before moving on to the next Chapter:</strong>
							<span class="dot"><span onclick="compTia.modules.toggleModule(22)" class="strongDBlue">check your understanding</span> of what you've learned so far.</span>
						</div>
					</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>

		<page index="75" type="Full" distinction="poll">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="pollHead">POLL</div>
				<img src="assets/images/pics/pollFPO.png" class="floatRight" style="margin: 74px 6px 0 0;" />
				<div style="width:410px">
					<div class="font_20 BMargin25">What would you do if you saw a student cheat on a test?</div>
					<ol class="pollQuestions">
						<li>Nothing—it doesn't affect me.</li>
						<li>Nothing, but it would bother me a lot.</li>
						<li>Report it to the instructor.</li>
						<li>Talk to the student about it after the test.</li>
						
					</ol>
					<div class="blueSubmit Lmargin22"></div>
				</div>
				
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>
		
		<page index="76" type="ColumnColumn" distinction="chapterReview">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="title">Information Technology Ethics glossary//</div>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Brain-computer interfaces (BCIs)</span> 227<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Cyborg</span> 227<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>ethics</span> 221<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Neural stem cells</span> 227<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Neurostimulation</span> 227<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>personal ethics</span> 222<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>positive psychology</span> 224<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>stakeholders</span> 226<br/>
					<span class="strongDBlue" glossary>whistle-blowers</span> 225<br/>
					
					

				]]>
			</section>
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
					<div class="ColShiftSpacer"></div>
					
					<div class="purpleContain">
						<div class="purpleContent semibold textBlack">
							Don't forget to use the study aids included in <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://www.myitlab.com','_blank')">MyITLab</span> or on the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://wps.prenhall.com/bp_evans_techinaction_10/','_blank')">Companion Website</span>. And don’t forget the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_techinaction_10/video/index.html','_blank')">Replay Videos</span>.
						</div>
						</div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</page>

		</chapter>
</ebook>		