<?xml version="1.0"?>
<ebook>
	<chapter index="6">


<popup page="3" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[

					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.1Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 153px 42px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.1</span>
						Moore’s Law illustrates the amazing pace of growth in CPU capabilities.
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="4" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<p style="font-size:20px; color:#01af86;margin-left:260px;margin-bottom:-48px;margin-top:21px;"><strong>What Kind of Computer User Are You?</strong></p>
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.2Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll center 65px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont" style="margin-left:200px;">
					  <span>Figure 6.2</span>
						<em>(llaszlo/Shutterstock; ColorBlind Images/Iconica/Getty Images; olly/Shutterstock)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="5" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.3Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll center 65px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.3</span>
						ExpressCards add functionality to your laptop. <em>(Editorial Image, LLC/Alamy; Editorial Image, LLC/Alamy)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="6" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.4Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll center 25px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont" >
					  <span>Figure 6.4</span>
						The Intel i5 and i7 CPU chips run many of the laptop and desktop offerings on the market today. <em>(David Caudery/PC Format Magazine/Future/Getty Images)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="6" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.5Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 48px 56px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont" >
					  <span>Figure 6.5</span>
						The System Properties window identifies your computer’s CPU as well as its speed. This computer has an Intel i7 running at 2.2 GHz. <em>To access your system settings, move your mouse to the lower-left corner of your screen and right-click. From the menu that displays, choose <strong>System.</strong></em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
		
		<popup page="8" distinction="popupFeature" customscript="compTia.features.setupVideo('6_6_1')">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage">
		
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Hyperthreading</div>
		<div class="padding70">
		  <a data="6_6_1" style="color:#01567a;"></a>
		</div>
		<div class="wideVideoGraphic">
		  <video autoplay="autoplay" width="768" height="420" class="Lmargin22">
			<source src="" type="video/mp4">
			  <source src="" type="video/ogg">
			  Your browser does not support the video tag.
		  </video>
			</div>
		  </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<popup page="8" distinction="readMoreFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[

				  <div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
					<div class="column">
					  <div class="innerColLeft">
						
						<p class="start">Benchmarks are generated by running software programs specifically designed to push the limits of CPU performance. Articles are often published comparing CPUs, or complete systems, based on their benchmark performance. Investigate a few, using sites like <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://cpubenchmark.net','_blank')">cpubenchmark.net</span>, before you select the chip that’s best for you.</p>
						
						</div>
					  </div>
					  <div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
						  
						  </div>
						</div>
					  </div>
						</div>

				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="9" distinction="bbFeature">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[

						<div class="content">
						  <div class="column">
							<div class="innerColLeft">
								<strong class="font_16">Not Much Power at All</strong>
								<p>The amount of power a CPU requires is very important to designers looking to extend the battery life of an ultrabook or tablet. Intel has created a CPU nicknamed Claremont that can run off only the power of a reading lamp. In fact, the CPU can even be powered by the small solar battery cells used to run solar-powered calculators.</p>
								<p class="start">Could these so-called <em>near threshold voltage (NTV)</em> CPUs be the beginning of a new series of devices? What kind of design changes are on the horizon once a system can be solar-powered?</p>
								
							
							</div>
						  </div>
						  <div class="column">
							<div class="innerColRight">
							</div>
						  </div>
						</div>
					]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="9" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure class="normalFont" style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.7Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 79px 45px transparent">
					<figcaption>
					  <span>Figure 6.7</span>
						The Performance tab of the Windows Task Manager utility shows you how busy your CPU is. <br/><em>To access the Performance tab, move your cursor to the lower-left corner and right-click. From the menu, select <strong>Task Manager</strong>, and then click the <strong>Performance</strong> tab.</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<!--interactive-->
		<popup page="10" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftLeft">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">How to Evaluate a CPU</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.8</strong>  Click on the colored parts of the circle to view more information</div>
			
			<figure style="	width:878px;height:486px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.8/circle.png) 265px 84px no-repeat">

					<div class="overlayButtons">
						
					<div style="top: 67px; left: 318px; height: 121px; width: 145px; transform: rotate(24deg);" roll="orangeArrow.png"></div>
					<div style="height: 146px; width: 137px; left: 269px; top: 184px; transform: rotate(23deg);" roll="greyArrow.png"></div>
					<div style="height: 144px; width: 147px; top: 246px; left: 397px; transform: rotate(-67deg);" roll="blueArrow.png"></div>
					<div style="height: 124px; left: 455px; width: 156px; top: 130px; transform: rotate(25deg);" roll="greenArrow.png"></div>

					</div>
					<div class="overlayImages">
						<div style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.8/orangeArrow.png); top: 54px; width: 301px; height: 149px;" roll="orangeArrow.png"></div>
						<div roll="greyArrow.png" style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.8/greyArrow.png); width: 291px; height: 148px; left: 4px; top: 237px;"></div>
						<div roll="blueArrow.png" style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.8/blueArrow.png); height: 150px; width: 285px; left: 555px; top: 259px;"></div>
						<div roll="greenArrow.png" style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.8/greenArrow.png); width: 302px; height: 148px; left: 556px; top: 63px;"></div>
					</div>
			</figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="11" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure class="normalFont" style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.9Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 42px 25px transparent">
					<figcaption>
					  <span>Figure 6.9</span>
						A computer system’s memory has many different levels, ranging from the small amounts in the CPU to the much slower but more plentiful storage of a mechanical hard drive.
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="12" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure class="normalFont" style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.10Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 145px 45px transparent">
					<figcaption>
					  <span>Figure 6.10</span>
						A DIMM memory module holds a series of RAM chips. <em>(Hugh Threlfall/Alamy)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="13" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure class="normalFont" style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.11Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 55px 35px transparent">
					<figcaption>
					  <span>Figure 6.11</span>
						The Resource Monitor’s Memory tab shows a detailed breakdown of how the computer is using memory. <br/><em>To access the Resource Monitor, in the Task Manager, click the <strong>Performance</strong> tab, click <strong>Open Resource Monitor</strong>, and then click the <strong>Memory</strong> tab.</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="14" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage ramTable">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashesTable">Sample RAM Allocation</div>



			<strong>Figure 6.12</strong></span>
			<br><br>
					<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" class=" ramTable">
						<thead><tr class="font_15">
							<th><div class="blueGradHeading">Application</div></th>
							<th><div class="blueGradHeading alignLeft" style="width:330px">RAM Recommended</div></th>
						</tr></thead>
						<tbody class="font_15">
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Windows 8 (64 bit)</div></td>
							<td><div>2 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Microsoft Office Professional 2010</div></td>
							<td><div>512 MB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Internet Explorer 9</div></td>
							<td><div>512 MB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div>iTunes 10</div></td>
							<td><div>1 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Adobe Photoshop Elements 9</div></td>
							<td><div>2 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="darkBlueGrad">
							<td><div style="height: 41px;"><strong>Total RAM required to run all <br/>programs simultaneously</strong></div></td>
							<td><div style="height: 41px;"><strong>6 GB</strong></div></td>
						</tr>
					</tbody></table>
					
			 </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="14" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.13Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 37px 85px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.13</span>
						Adding RAM to a computer is quite simple and relatively inexpensive. On a laptop, you often gain access through a panel on the bottom. <br/><em>(Editorial Image, LLC/Alamy; Editorial Image, LLC/Alamy)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="14" distinction="readMoreFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[

				  <div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
					<div class="column">
					  <div class="innerColLeft">
						<ul class="dotted">
							<p>Be sure that you purchase a memory module that’s compatible with your computer. Also be sure to follow the installation instructions that come with the RAM module. Typically, you simply line up the notches and gently push the memory module in place.</p>
							<p class="start">RAM is a relatively inexpensive system upgrade. The cost of RAM does fluctuate in the marketplace as much as 400% over time, though, so if you’re considering adding RAM, you should watch the prices of memory in online and print advertisements.</p>
						</div>
					  </div>
					  <div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
						  
						  </div>
						</div>
					  </div>
						</div>

				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<popup page="15" distinction="digDeeperFeature" customscript="compTia.features.popupScroll()" closescript="$('#readMoreFeature .scroll').off('mousedown mouseup')">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="headerText font_20" style="top:38px">How a Mechanical Hard Drive Works</div>
				<div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColLeft">
							<p>The thin metal platters that make up a hard drive are covered with a special magnetic coating that enables the data to be recorded onto one or both sides of the platter. Hard drive manufacturers prepare the disks to hold data through a process called <em>low-level formatting</em>. In this process, concentric circles, each called a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>track</span>, and pie-shaped wedges, each called a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>sector</span>, are created in the magnetized surface of each platter, setting up a gridlike pattern that identifies file locations on the hard drive. A separate process called <em>high-level formatting</em> establishes the catalog that the computer uses to keep track of where each file is located on the hard drive. More detail on this process is presented in the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(15,1)">Dig Deeper feature “How Disk Defragmenter Utilities Work” in Chapter 5</span>.</p>
							<p class="start">Hard drive platters spin at a high rate of speed, some as fast as 15,000 revolutions per minute (rpm). Sitting between the platters are special “arms” that contain read/write heads (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)">see Figure 6.15</span>). A <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>read/write head</span> moves from the outer edge of the spinning platter to the center, as frequently as 50 times per second, to retrieve (read) and record (write) the magnetic data to and from the hard drive platter. As noted earlier, the average total time it takes for the read/write head to locate the data on the platter and return it to the CPU for processing is called its <em>access time</em>. A new hard drive should have an average access time of approximately 12 ms.</p>
							<p class="start">Access time is mostly the sum of two factors—seek time and latency:</p>
							<ol>
								<li><span class="innerLi">The time it takes for the read/write heads to move over the surface of the disk, moving to the correct track, is called the <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>seek time</span>. (Sometimes people incorrectly refer to this as access time.)</span></li>
								<li><span class="innerLi">Once the read/write head locates the correct track, it may need to wait for the correct sector to spin to the read/write head. This waiting time is called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary="latency (rotational delay)">latency</span> (or <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>rotational delay</span>).</span></li>
							</ol>
							<p class="start">The faster the platters spin (or the faster the rpm), the less time you’ll have to wait for your data to be accessed. Currently, most hard drives for home systems spin at 7,200 rpm.</p>
							<p class="start">The read/write heads don’t touch the platters of the hard drive; rather, they float above them on a thin cushion of air at a height of 0.5 microinches. As a matter of comparison, a human hair is 2,000 microinches thick and a particle of dust is larger than a human hair. Therefore, it’s critical to keep your hard drive free from all dust and dirt because even the smallest particle could find its way between the read/write head and the disk platter, causing a <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>head crash</span>—a stoppage of the hard drive that often results in data loss.</p>
							<p class="start">SSDs free you from worry about head crashes at all. The memory inside an SSD is constructed with electronic transistors, meaning there are no platters, no motors, and no read/write arms. Instead, a series of cells are constructed in the silicon wafers. If high voltage is applied, electrons move in and you have one state. Reverse the voltage and the electrons flow in another direction, marking the cell as storing a different value. The limiting factor for an SSD’s lifespan is how many times data can be written to a cell. But the current generation of SSDs is proving to have very strong performance over time. Intel, one manufacturer of SSDs, says its drives will last five years when being written to heavily (20 GB per day).</p>
							<p class="start">Capacities for hard drives in personal computers can exceed 4,000 GB (4 TB). Increasing the amount of data stored in a hard drive is achieved either by adding more platters or by increasing the amount of data stored on each platter. How tightly the tracks are placed next to each other, how tightly spaced the sectors are, and how closely the bits of data are placed affect the measurement of the amount of data that can be stored in a specific area of a hard drive platter. Modern technology continues to increase the standards on all three levels, enabling massive quantities of data to be stored in small places.</p>
							</div>
					</div>
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
							<figure  onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)"
						 		style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.15.png) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent;
						  	height: 250px;margin-top:300px;">
							<figcaption class="bottomPos">
							  <span>Figure 6.15</span>
							   The hard drive is a stack of platters enclosed in a sealed case. Special arms fit between each platter. The read/write heads at the end of each arm read data from and save data to the platters. <em>(skaljac/Shutterstock)</em>
							</figcaption></figure>
						</div>
					</div>
				</div></div>
						<div class="additional">
						
						
						<div class="ad">
							<figure onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(0)"
								class="showOverflow height100"
								style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.15Big.png) no-repeat scroll 150px 72px transparent">
							  <figcaption class="bottomPos">
							  <span>Figure 6.15</span>
							   The hard drive is a stack of platters enclosed in a sealed case. Special arms fit between each platter. The read/write heads at the end of <br/>each arm read data from and save data to the platters. <em>(skaljac/Shutterstock)</em>
							 
							</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div></div></div></div>

						
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
	<!--Duplicate chapter 5 popup Dig Deeper page 36 for link connection to Dig Deeper chapter 6-->
			<popup page="15"  distinction="digDeeperFeature" customscript="compTia.features.popupScroll()" closescript="$('#digDeeperFeature .scroll').off('mousedown mouseup')">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="headerText">How Disk Defragmenter Utilities Work</div>
				<div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
				  <div class="column">
					<div class="innerColLeft">
						<p><span class="strongDBlue" glossary>Disk defragmenting</span> programs group together related pieces of files on the hard drive, allowing the OS to work more efficiently. To understand how disk defragmenter utilities work, you first need to understand the basics of how a hard disk drive stores files. A hard disk drive is composed of several platters, or round, thin plates of metal, covered with a special magnetic coating that records the data. The platters are about 3.5 inches in diameter and are stacked onto a spindle. There are usually two or three platters in any hard disk drive, with data stored on one or both sides. Data is recorded on hard disks in concentric circles called <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>tracks</span>. Each track is further broken down into pie-shaped wedges, each called a  <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>sector</span> (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)">see Figure 5.35</span>). The data is further identified by <span class="strongDBlue" glossary>clusters</span>, which are the smallest segments within the sectors.</p>
						<p class="start">When you want to save (or write) a file, the bits that make up your file are recorded onto one or more clusters of the drive. To keep track of which clusters hold which files, the drive also stores an index of all sector numbers in a table. To save a file, the computer looks in the table for clusters that aren’t already being used. It then records the file information on those clusters. When you open (or read) a file, the computer searches through the table for the clusters that hold the desired file and reads that file. Similarly, when you delete a file, you’re actually not deleting the file itself but rather the reference in the table to the file.</p>
						<p class="start">So, how does a disk become fragmented? When only part of an older file is deleted, the deleted section of the file creates a gap in the sector of the disk where the data was originally stored. In the same way, when new information is added to an older file, there may not be space to save the new information sequentially near where the file was originally saved. In that case, the system writes the added part of the file to the next available location on the disk, and a reference is made in the table as to the location of this file fragment. Over time, as files are saved, deleted, and modified, the bits of information for various files fall out of order and the disk becomes fragmented.</p>
						<p class="start">Disk fragmentation is a problem because the OS isn’t as efficient when a disk is fragmented. It takes longer to locate a whole file because more of the disk must be searched for the various pieces, slowing down your computer. Defragmenting tools take the hard drive through a defragmentation process in which pieces of files scattered over the disk are placed together and arranged sequentially on it. Also, any unused portions of clusters that were too small to save data in before are grouped, increasing the available storage space on the disk. <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(2)">Figure 5.36</span> shows before and after shots of a fragmented disk that has gone through the defragmentation process. The disk defragmentation utility in Windows 8 is set by default to automatically defragment the hard drive on a regular basis. Macs don’t have a defragmentation utility built into the system. Those users who feel the need to defragment their Mac can use iDefrag, an external program from Coriolis Systems. For more about hard disks and defragmenting, check out the <span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://media.pearsoncmg.com/ph/bp/bp_evans_soundbytes_9/hard_disk_anatomy_interactive/index.html','_blank')">Sound Byte “Hard Disk Anatomy.”</span></p>
						
					</div>
				</div>
				<div class="column">
					<div class="innerColRight">

							<figure style="
								    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.35.png) no-repeat 48px 0 transparent;
    								height: 275px;
    								margin-top: 42px;"
    								onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)">
							  <figcaption class="bottomPos">
								<span>Figure 5.35</span> On a hard disk platter, data is recorded onto tracks, which are further divided into sectors and clusters.
							  </figcaption>
							</figure>
					
				
						<figure style="
								    background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.36.png) no-repeat -8px 0 transparent;
    								height: 400px;
    								margin-top: 320px;
									margin-right:-33px;"
    								onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(2)">
							  <figcaption class="bottomPos" style="width:325px;">
								<span>Figure 5.36</span> Defragmenting the hard drive arranges file fragments so that they are located next to each other. This makes the hard drive run more efficiently.
							  </figcaption>
							</figure>
					</div>
				</div>
			</div></div>
			<div class="additional">
						<div class="ad">

							<figure onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(0)"
								class="showOverflow height100 width100"
								style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.35Big.png) no-repeat scroll 290px 0 transparent">
								<figcaption class="topPos" style="width: 350px; margin-right:15;">
								<span>Figure 5.35</span> On a hard disk platter, data is recorded onto tracks, which are further divided into sectors and clusters.
							  </figcaption>
							  </figure>

						
					</div>
					
					<figure onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(0)"
								class="showOverflow height100 width100"
								style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig5.36Big.png) no-repeat scroll 86px -4px transparent">
								<figcaption class="topPos rightPos" style="width: 175px; margin-right:60px;">
								<span>Figure 5.36</span> Defragmenting the hard drive arranges file fragments so that they are located next to each other. This makes the hard drive run more efficiently.
							  </figcaption>
							  </figure>

						</div>
					</div>
				</div>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
			
	
		
		<popup page="16" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftLeft">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Relative Data Transfer Speeds for Nonvolatile Storage Options</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.14</strong></div>
			
			<figure style="height:420px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.14Big.jpg) 60px 90px no-repeat">

			</figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="17" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.16Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 155px 45px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.16</span>
						Blu-ray lasers have a shorter wavelength and so can store a much higher density of information than CDs and DVDs.
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="18" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.17Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 190px 10px transparent;margin-bottom:-38px;">
					<figcaption class="normalFont" style="margin-bottom:50px;">
					  <span>Figure 6.17</span>
						In Windows, the free and used capacity of each device in the computer system is shown in the Computer window. The General tab of the Properties dialog box gives you more-detailed information. 
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				<p><em>To view the Computer window, launch File Explorer (previously called Windows Explorer), and then click <strong>Computer</strong>.<br/>
				To view the pie chart, right-click the <strong>C dive</strong>, and select <strong>Properties</strong>.</em></p>	
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
<popup page="18" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftRight">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashesTable">Sample Hard Drive Space Requirements</div>



			<strong>Figure 6.18</strong></span>
					<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" class=" font_13">
						<thead><tr class="blueGradHeading thickerHeader alignLeft">
							<th><div style="width:184px">Application/Data</div></th>
							<th><div style="width:184px">Hard Drive Space Required</div></th>
							<th><div>Heavy Cloud Storage User</div></th>
						</tr></thead>
						<tbody class="thickerCells">
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Windows 8 (64 bit)</div></td>
							<td><div>20 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>20 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Microsoft Office 2010 Professional</div></td>
							<td><div>3.5 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>3.5 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Adobe Photoshop Elements 9</div></td>
							<td><div>2 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>2 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Adobe Premiere Pro CS5.5</div></td>
							<td><div>10 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>10 GB</div></td>
						</tr>
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Video library of movies</div></td>
							<td><div>80 GB (about 40 HD movies)</div></td>
							<td><div>Streamed through online services</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div >Music library</div></td>
							<td><div>50 GB (about 7,000 songs)</div></td>
							<td><div>Stored in cloud (iCloud or Amazon Cloud Drive)</div></td>
						</tr>
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Photographs</div></td>
							<td><div>5 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>Stored in iCloud or Dropbox</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="greenGrad font_15">
							<td><div><strong>Total storage in use</strong></div></td>
							<td><div><strong>170.5 GB</strong></div></td>
							<td><div><strong>35.5 GB</strong></div></td>
						</tr>
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Full backup</div></td>
							<td><div>170.5 GB</div></td>
							<td><div>Done to cloud using Carbonite</div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="greenGrad font_15">
							<td><div><strong>Total required</strong></div></td>
							<td><div><strong>341 GB</strong></div></td>
							<td><div><strong>35.5 GB</strong></div></td>
						</tr>
					</tbody></table>
					
			 </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="19" distinction="popupFeature" customscript="compTia.features.setupVideo('6_19_1')">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage">
		
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">RAID Configuration</div>
		<div class="padding70">
		  <a data="6_19_1" style="color:#01567a;"></a>
		</div>
		<div class="wideVideoGraphic">
		  <video autoplay="autoplay" width="688" height="376">
			<source src="" type="video/mp4">
			  <source src="" type="video/ogg">
			  Your browser does not support the video tag.
		  </video>
			</div>
		  </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<popup page="19" distinction="bbFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[

						<div class="content">
						  <div class="column">
							<div class="innerColLeft">
								<strong class="font_16">Where’s the Free TV?</strong>
								
								<p>Most major networks are streaming content for free so that you can catch full episodes of most popular TV series on the go. Subscription channels like HBO and Showtime all have free streaming of content. If you have HBO at home, you can watch any show from their HBO GO website on your laptop or tablet. If you’re interested in more international viewing, head to Squid TV and select live broadcasts from countries around the world.</p>
								<p class="start">If you’re looking for homemade shows, sites like Justin.tv and Ustream are filled with live and archived video webcasts. Once you decide to start making television instead of just watching, you can webcast your own television show directly from the Ustream webapp using your webcam or smartphone video camera.</p>
								
								
							</div>
						  </div>
						  <div class="column">
							<div class="innerColRight">
								
							</div>
						  </div>
						</div>

				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="20" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Evaluating Storage</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.20</strong> Click on colors to reveal information</div>
			
			<figure style="	width:878px;height:486px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.20/circle.jpg) 265px 103px no-repeat">

					<div class="overlayButtons">
						
				<div roll="orangeArrow.png" style="top: 97px; width: 220px; left: 298px; height: 84px;"></div>
				<div roll="grayArrow.png" style="width: 117px; left: 289px; height: 216px; top: 162px; transform: rotate(137deg);"></div>
				<div roll="greenArrow.png" style="left: 436px; width: 127px; transform: rotate(-19deg); height: 154px; top: 181px;"></div>

					</div>
					<div class="overlayImages">
						<div roll="grayArrow.png" style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.20/grayArrow.png); height: 131px; width: 273px; top: 234px;"></div>
						<div style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.20/greenArrow.png); height: 131px; width: 273px; top: 157px; left: 554px;" roll="greenArrow.png"></div>
						<div style="background-image: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.20/orangeArrow.png); height: 131px; width: 276px; top: 61px;" roll="orangeArrow.png"></div>
					</div>
			</figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<popup page="24" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[

					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.22Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 153px 42px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.22</span>
						Video card processors produce so much heat that video cards have their own fan—or two. <em>(nikkytok/Fotolia)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="24" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<figure style=" background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.23Big.jpg) no-repeat scroll 0px 135px transparent;">
				<figcaption class="normalFont bottomPos">
				  <span>Figure 6.23</span>
					 The GPU is specialized to handle processing of photos, videos, and video game images. It frees up the CPU to work on other system demands.</em>
				</figcaption>
				</figure>

		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="25" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[

					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.24Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 20px 73px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.24</span>
						(a) AMD Radeon technology supports (b) six monitors, which can be combined in any way. <em>(AMD; AMD)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="26" distinction="trendsFeature" customscript="compTia.features.popupScroll()" closescript="$('#readMoreFeature .scroll').off('mousedown mouseup')">
			<section><![CDATA[
			<div class="headerText" style="line-height:22px; text-align:center; margin-top:-12px;">Thunderbolt: The New Standard<br/>for Data Transfer</div>

				<div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColLeft">
							<p>Faster is always better, and the newest input/output standard, Thunderbolt, is faster than anything seen before. And speed isn’t its only advantage.</p>
					  		<p class="start">Intel used fiber optics—the transmission of digital data through pure glass cable as thin as human hair—to develop the new input/output technology named Thunderbolt. Thunderbolt supports blazingly fast transfer rates of 10 Gb/s, zooming past even the theoretical limit of the new USB 3.0, which is 4.8 Gb/s. How fast is that? Intel says that Thunderbolt could transfer a full-length HD movie in under 30 seconds or copy in just 10 minutes a library of music that would take a solid year to play through. And Thunderbolt can supply much more power to devices than the USB standard allows. It also has a very slim connector design, allowing laptop designers to make their systems even thinner (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)">see Figure 6.26</span>).</p>
					  		<p class="start">But one of the greatest hopes that comes with Thunderbolt is that the technology will be able to replace a number of different ports, cleaning up the cluttered design we see now on the sides of laptops and the backs of desktop units. The first devices using this technology appeared in May 2011 when Apple introduced Thunderbolt ports on the MacBook Pro series. It looks like a single thin port that supports both the video standard DisplayPort and the bus standard PCI Express (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,3)">see Figure 6.27</span>). So Thunderbolt can connect monitors to computers using VGA, DisplayPort, DVI, or HDMI and can connect systems to external hard drives that use USB, FireWire, or eSATA. One Thunderbolt port can support several devices because the cables can be daisychained (connected one after another in a serial fashion), so having just one Thunderbolt port on a laptop allows you to connect up to six different peripherals to your system.</p>
							<p class="start">Thunderbolt technology also gives you a two-for-one deal, because each connector can support two separate channels to send and receive data, each one still operating at the full 10 Gb/s bandwidth.</p>
							<p class="start">What will this mean to laptop designers? Some speculate we’ll see the heavy, heat-producing video cards currently integrated into gaming laptops become external graphics boxes. An incredibly thin, light laptop design would let you be wonderfully mobile all day, and then when you come home, you’d attach one cable. It would run from your Thunderbolt port to your 60-inch HDTV and then continue on to a separate graphics processor box. That same laptop would then be running a huge high-definition monitor with a high-resolution graphics and physics engine.</p>
							<p class="start">Apple is not the only company that will be using the Intel technology. Hard-drive companies like LaCie and Western Digital, as well as audio/video processing companies like Avid and Apogee, have announced Thunderbolt products. And the USB community may need to put up a bit of a fight to keep their standard around. But the allure of incredible speed, great versatility, and small, thin packaging is going to make the Thunderbolt technology a trend to watch.</p>
							<p class="start">Could Thunderbolt make USB a thing of the past?</p>
							</div>
					</div>
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
							<figure  onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(1)" 
						 		style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.26.png) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent;
						  	height: 355px;margin: 0px 0 0 0px;">
							<figcaption class="bottomPos">
							  <span>Figure 6.26</span>
							  Thunderbolt ports are very thin, allowing for new <br/>design options? <em>(Kendall Martin)</em>
							</figcaption></figure>
				
				<figure onclick="compTia.togglePopup(26,3)" 
						 		style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.27.png) no-repeat scroll -6px 0px transparent;
						  	height: 170px;margin: 40px 0 0 -9px;">
							<figcaption class="bottomPos">
							  <span>Figure 6.27</span>
							  Thunderbolt can carry two channels of information on the same connector.
							</figcaption></figure>
				</div></div></div></div>


						<div class="additional">
						
						<div class="ad">
							<figure onclick="compTia.additionalPopupContent(0)"
								class="showOverflow height100"
								style="background: url(assets/images/figures/fig6.26Big.png) no-repeat scroll 0px 0px transparent">
							  <figcaption class="rightPos topPos" style="margin-right:45px;">
							  <span>Figure 6.26</span>
								Thunderbolt ports are very thin, allowing for new <br/>design options? <em>(Kendall Martin)</em>
							 
							</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
						</div></div></div></div>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="26" distinction="bbFeature">
			<section>
				<![CDATA[
				<div class="content">
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColLeft">
							<p><strong class="larger">Auto Tech: Can Your Car Do This?</strong></p>
							
							<p>Cool technology isn’t just for your laptop. The automotive industry is making its own technological advances as well. For example, the OnStar system distributes sensors around the car that let your car call for help if it detects a crash and you’re not responsive. OnStar reports the direction and number of impacts, the car’s rollover status, and the car’s maximum velocity on impact so medical workers can come better prepared.</p>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
						</div>
					</div>
			  	</div>

	 		 ]]>
		</section>
	</popup>
		
		<popup page="26" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftLeft">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Do You Need to Upgrade Your Video Card?</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.25</strong></div>
			
			<figure style="height:477px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.25Big.jpg) 114px 4px no-repeat">

			<figcaption class="bottomPos">
					  <span></span>
						<em></em>
					</figcaption></figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="26" distinction="popupFeature" customscript="compTia.features.setupVideo('6_27_1')" closescript="$('.arrowLeft,.arrowRight','#features').off('click')">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage">
				<div class="close hide"></div>
					
					
					<div class="redirect" onclick="compTia.togglePopup(0);$('video').each(function(){this.pause()});window.setTimeout(function(){compTia.togglePopup(26,0)},250)"> </div>
					<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Thunderbolt: The New Standard for Data Transfer</div>
					<div class="padding70">
					  <a style="padding-left:99px;color:#01567a" data="6_27_1"></a>
					
						
					</div>
					<div class="wideVideoGraphic">
					  <video autoplay="autoplay" width="688" height="448">
						<source src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/compatia/video/b.mp4" type="video/mp4">
						  <source src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/compatia/video/b.ogv" type="video/ogg">
						  Your browser does not support the video tag.
					  </video>
				</div>
		  </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		
		<popup page="28" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<p><span class="strongDBlue">For more info on surround sound, check out this </span><span class="strongDBlue" style="position: relative;z-index: 2;" onclick="window.open('http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JLVazsghkGA','_blank')" style="text-decoration:underline;">YouTube video</span></p>

					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.28Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 210px 68px transparent;margin-top:-56px;">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.28</span>
						Dolby Digital 7.1 surround sound gives you better-quality audio output.
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="29" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.29Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll 210px 30px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.29</span>
						Sample Home Recording Studio Setup. <em>(simon5586/Fotolia; aleksangel/Fotolia; Maksym Yemelyanov/Fotolia; <br/>Sashkin/Fotolia; Mariusz Blach/Fotolia; AbsentAnna/Fotolia; M-Audio)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="29" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftLeft">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Do You Need to Upgrade Your Audio Subsystem?</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.30</strong></div>
			
			<figure style="height:480px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.30Big.jpg) 190px 0px no-repeat">

			<figcaption class="bottomPos">
					  <span></span>
						<em></em>
					</figcaption></figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="30" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
				<div class="ActiveGraphicPage reliableTable">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Utilities to Keep Your System Reliable</div>



			<strong class="shiftLeft17">Figure 6.31</strong></span>
			<br><br>
					<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" class="shiftLeft17 reliableTable">
						<thead><tr class="font_15">
							<th><div class="blueGradHeading">To Avoid This Problem</div></th>
							<th><div class="blueGradHeading">Use This Tool</div></th>
							<th><div class="blueGradHeading">For More Info</div></th>
						</tr></thead>
						<tbody class="font_15">
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Your hard drive is running low on space, making it run slowly</div></td>
							<td><div style="line-height:40px;">Disk Cleanup utility</div></td>
							<td><div><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.moveTo(5,0)">Chapter 5</span></div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightestBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Your system is slowing down, browsers or other programs are behaving strangely</div></td>
							<td><div>Antivirus software Spyware and adware removal software</div></td>
							<td><div><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.moveTo(9,0)">Chapter 9</span></div></td>
						</tr>
						
						<tr class="lightBlueGrad">
							<td><div>Files are spread across many spots on the hard drive, making the hard drive run slowly</div></td>
							<td><div style="line-height:40px;">Disk Defragmenter utility</div></td>
							<td><div><span class="strongDBlue" onclick="compTia.moveTo(5,0)">Chapter 5</span></div></td>
						</tr>
						
						
					</tbody></table>
					
			 </div>
		  ]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="31" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.32Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll center 20px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.32</span>
						Mac’s Time Machine keeps copies of files, folders, and libraries and can restore your system back to any previous point in time.
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="32" distinction="readMoreFeature" >
			<section><![CDATA[

				<div class="content"><div class="columnContain">
				  <div class="column">
					<div class="innerColLeft">
						<p class="start">If you’re having a software problem that can be replicated, use the Steps Recorder to capture the exact steps that lead to it. In Windows 8, display the Charms bar, select Search, then type “ste” in the search box. Now run the Steps Recorder and go through the exact actions that create the problem you’re having. At any particular step, you can click the Add Comment button and add a comment about any part of the screen. The Steps Recorder then produces a documented report, complete with images of your screen and descriptions of each mouse movement you made. You can then e-mail this report to customer support to help technicians resolve the problem.</p>
						</div>
				</div>
					<div class="column">
						<div class="innerColRight">
							
						  </div>
						</div>
				</div></div>
					

						</div>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="33" distinction="popupFeature">
			<section><![CDATA[
								<div class="ActiveGraphicPage shiftLeft">
		<div class="close"> </div>
		<div class="HeadingOrangeBackDiagDashes">Key Items in System Evaluation</div>
			<div class="figureHeader"><strong>Figure 6.33</strong></div>
			
			<figure style="height:490px;
							background:url(assets/images/figures/fig6.33Big.jpg) 208px -15px no-repeat">

			<figcaption class="bottomPos">
					  <span></span>
						<em></em>
					</figcaption></figure>
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="33" distinction="popupImage">
			<section><![CDATA[
					<figure style="background:url('assets/images/figures/fig6.34Big.jpg') no-repeat scroll center 20px transparent">
					<figcaption class="normalFont">
					  <span>Figure 6.34</span>
						An electronics garbage dump can cause environmental concerns like the leaching of lead and mercury into the ground. <em>(Minnesota Public Radio; Tim Post/AP Photo)</em>
					</figcaption>
					</figure>
				]]>
			</section>
		</popup>
		
		<popup page="34" distinction="ethicsFeature" customscript="" closescript="">
			<section><![CDATA[

				<div class="content">
				<div class="headerText">Free Hardware for All</div>
				<div class="columnContain">
				
				  <div class="column">
					<div class="innerColLeft">
						
						<p>The open source software movement has flourished over the past decade. In response to increasing prices and the limitations placed on commercially available software, programmers began to donate time to design, develop, and support software systems. These products, like Gimp (a photo-editing tool), were then made freely available.</p>
					  	<p class="start">In the world of hardware, a similar but different approach called the open source hardware movement has flourished. Because hardware projects require materials and tools to assemble, products distributed as open source are not free in terms of cost, but they are free from any restrictions on how you modify them. Sample open source hardware projects include video game systems, audio equipment, and 3-D printers. </p>
						<p class="start">Is open hardware good for the world? Does it undermine the intellectual property of others who want to create hardware resources and sell them for a profit? What is the impact on developing countries if they have immediate access to hardware designs instead of being required to purchase</p>
						
						</div>
				</div>
				<div class="column">
					<div class="innerColRight">
						<p>these items from a for-profit company? Follow the future of open source hardware by keeping an eye on conferences like the Open Hardware Summit (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://openhardwaresummit.org','_blank')">openhardwaresummit.org</span>), developer and supplier sites like littleBits (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://littlebits.cc','_blank')">littlebits.cc</span>), and homebrew blogs like Procrastineering (<span class="strongDBlue" onclick="window.open('http://procrastineering.blogspot.com','_blank')">procrastineering.blogspot.com</span>).</p>
						  
					</div>
				</div>
			</div></div>
									
			]]></section>
		</popup>
		
	</chapter>
</ebook>